<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;]>
<chapter xml:id="chapter-intro" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Introduction to syslog-ng</title>
    <para>This chapter introduces the &product; application in a non-technical manner, discussing how and why is it useful, and the benefits it offers to an existing IT infrastructure.</para>
    <section>
        <title>What syslog-ng is</title>
        <para>The syslog-ng application is a flexible and highly scalable system logging application that is ideal for creating centralized and trusted logging solutions. The main features of syslog-ng are summarized below.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Reliable log transfer</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application enables you to send the log messages of your hosts to remote servers using the latest protocol standards. The logs of different servers can be collected and stored centrally on dedicated log servers. Transferring log messages using the <phrase condition="pe"><trademark>RLTP</trademark></phrase><phrase condition="ose">TCP</phrase> protocol ensures that no messages are lost.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Secure logging using TLS</emphasis>: Log messages may contain sensitive information that should not be accessed by third parties. Therefore, syslog-ng supports the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol to encrypt the communication. TLS also allows the mutual authentication of the host and the server using X.509 certificates.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Direct database access</emphasis>: Storing your log messages in a database allows you to easily search and query the messages and interoperate with log analyzing applications. The syslog-ng application supports the following databases: MSSQL, MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, and SQLite.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Heterogeneous environments</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application is the ideal choice to collect logs in massively heterogeneous environments using several different operating systems and hardware platforms, including Linux, Unix, BSD, Sun Solaris, HP-UX, Tru64, and AIX.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Filter and classify</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application can sort the incoming log messages based on their content and various parameters like the source host, application, and priority. Directories, files, and database tables can be created dynamically using macros. Complex filtering using regular expressions and boolean operators offers almost unlimited flexibility to forward only the important log messages to the selected destinations.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Parse and rewrite</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application can segment log messages to named fields or columns, and also modify the values of these fields.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>IPv4 and IPv6 support</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application can operate in both IPv4 and IPv6 network environments; it can receive and send messages to both types of networks.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>What syslog-ng is not</title>
        <para>The syslog-ng application is not log analysis software. It can filter log messages and select only the ones matching certain criteria. It can even convert the messages and restructure them to a predefined format, or parse the messages and segment them into different fields. But syslog-ng cannot interpret and analyze the meaning behind the messages, or recognize patterns in the occurrence of different messages.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Why is syslog-ng needed?</title>
        <para>Log messages contain information about the events happening on the hosts. Monitoring system events is essential for security and system health monitoring reasons.</para>
        <para>The original syslog protocol separates messages based on the priority of the message and the facility sending the message. These two parameters alone are often inadequate to consistently classify messages, as many applications might use the same facility &mdash; and the facility itself is not even included in the log message. To make things worse, many log messages contain unimportant information. The syslog-ng application helps you to select only the really interesting messages, and forward them to a central server.</para>
        <para>Company policies or other regulations often require log messages to be archived. Storing the important messages in a central location greatly simplifies this process.</para>
        <para>For details on how can you use syslog-ng to comply with various regulations, see the <emphasis>Regulatory compliance and system logging</emphasis> whitepaper <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://syslog-ng.com/documentation"
					>available here</link></para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="syslog-ng_whatsnew">
        <title>What is new in &product; &version;?</title>
        <para>Version &version; of &product; includes the following main features:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Version <phrase condition="pe">5.4</phrase><phrase condition="ose">3.7</phrase> of &abbrev; can directly send log messages to <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://www.elastic.co/products/elasticsearch/">Elasticsearch</link>, allowing you to search and analyze your data in real time, and visualize it with <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://www.elastic.co/products/kibana/">Kibana</link>.</para>
                <para>For details, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-elasticsearch"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Version <phrase condition="pe">5.4</phrase><phrase condition="ose">3.7</phrase> of &abbrev; can directly publish log messages to the <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://kafka.apache.org">Apache Kafka</link> message bus, where subscribers can access them.</para>
                <para>For details, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-kafka"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Version <phrase condition="pe">5.3</phrase><phrase condition="ose">3.7</phrase> of &abbrev; can send plain-text log files to the <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://hadoop.apache.org/">Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS)</link>, allowing you to store your log data on a distributed, scalable file system. This is especially useful if you have huge amount of log messages that would be difficult to store otherwise, or if you want to process your messages using Hadoop tools (for example, Apache Pig).</para>
                <para>For details, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-hdfs"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The &abbrev; application can separate a message consisting of whitespace or comma-separated <userinput>key=value</userinput> pairs (for example, Postfix log messages) into name-value pairs. For details, see <xref linkend="key-value-parser"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>IPv6 addresses can be filtered using a new filter. For details, see <xref linkend="filter-netmask6"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>TLS-support has been added to <xref linkend="reference-destination-riemann"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <userinput>format-welf</userinput> function has been added to <xref linkend="reference-template-functions"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>You can generate a unique ID for every message using the <userinput>use-uniqid()</userinput> option. For details, see <xref linkend="global-use-uniqid"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>You can use the new <command>syslog-debun</command> tool to generate &abbrev; debug bundles. For details, see <xref linkend="syslog-debun.1"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <parameter>tcp()</parameter>, <parameter>tcp6()</parameter>, <parameter>udp()</parameter>, <parameter>udp6()</parameter> source and destination drivers have been deprecated, as all of their functionality can be achieved with the <parameter>network()</parameter> driver. For help on migrating to the <parameter>network()</parameter> driver, see <xref linkend="source-tcpudp-to-network"/> and <xref linkend="destination-tcpudp-to-network"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>You can write new destinations to &abbrev; using Java and Python. That way, you can use the existing Java and Python libraries to quickly and easily extend &abbrev; to send your log data to a vast number of services and applications.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For a more detailed list, see <xref linkend="ose-changes"/> and <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://github.com/balabit/syslog-ng/releases/">https://github.com/balabit/syslog-ng/releases/</link>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Who uses syslog-ng?</title>
        <para>The syslog-ng application is used worldwide by companies and institutions who collect and manage the logs of several hosts, and want to store them in a centralized, organized way. Using syslog-ng is particularly advantageous for:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Internet Service Providers;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Financial institutions and companies requiring policy compliance;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Server, web, and application hosting companies;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Datacenters;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wide area network (WAN) operators;</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Server farm administrators.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="supported-platforms" condition="ose">
        <title>Supported platforms</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>supported architectures</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>supported operating systems</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>The &product; application is highly portable and is known to run on a wide range of hardware architectures (x86, x86_64, SUN Sparc, PowerPC 32 and 64, Alpha) and operating systems, including Linux, BSD, Solaris, IBM AIX, HP-UX, Mac OS X, Cygwin, Tru64, and others.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The source code of &product; is released under the GPLv2 license and is <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://github.com/balabit/syslog-ng">available on GitHub</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>See <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://syslog-ng.org/3rd-party-binaries/">the list of precompiled &abbrev; binary packages</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</chapter>
