<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../shared/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<section xml:id="relaying-log-messages" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Configuring syslog-ng relays</title>
    <para>This section describes how to configure &abbrev; as a relay.</para>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="procedure-configuring-syslog-ng-relays.xml"/>
    <section xml:id="example-how-relaying-works">
        <title>How relaying log messages works</title>
        <para>Depending on your exact needs about relaying log messages, there are many scenarios and &abbrev; options that influence how the log message will look like on the logserver. Some of the most common cases are summarized in the following example.</para>
        <para>Consider the following example: <emphasis>client-host &gt; syslog-ng-relay &gt; syslog-ng-server</emphasis>, where the IP address of <parameter>client-host</parameter> is <userinput>192.168.1.2</userinput>. The <parameter>client-host</parameter> device sends a syslog message to <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter>. Depending on the settings of <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter>, the following can happen.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>By default, the <parameter>keep-hostname()</parameter> option is disabled, so <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter> writes the IP address of the sender host (in this case, <userinput>192.168.1.2</userinput>) to the HOST field of the syslog message, discarding any IP address or hostname that was originally in the message.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If the <parameter>keep-hostname()</parameter> option is enabled on <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter>, but name resolution is disabled (the <parameter>use-dns()</parameter> option is set to <userinput>no</userinput>), <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter> uses the HOST field of the message as-is, which is probably <userinput>192.168.1.2</userinput>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>To resolve the <userinput>192.168.1.2</userinput> IP address to a hostname on <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter> using a DNS server, use the <userinput>keep-hostname(no)</userinput> and <userinput>use-dns(yes)</userinput> options. If the DNS server is properly configured and reverse DNS lookup is available for the <userinput>192.168.1.2</userinput> address, &abbrev; will rewrite the HOST field of the log message to <parameter>client-host</parameter>.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>It is also possible to resolve IP addresses locally, without relying on the DNS server. For details on local name resolution, see <xref linkend="example-local-dns"/>.</para>
                </note>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The above points apply to the &abbrev; server (<parameter>syslog-ng-server</parameter>) as well, so if <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter> is configured properly, use the <userinput>keep-hostname(yes)</userinput> option on <parameter>syslog-ng-server</parameter> to retain the proper HOST field. Setting <userinput>keep-hostname(no)</userinput> on <parameter>syslog-ng-server</parameter> would result in &abbrev; rewriting the HOST field to the address of the host that sent the message to <parameter>syslog-ng-server</parameter>, which is <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter> in this case.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you cannot or do not want to resolve the <userinput>192.168.1.2</userinput> IP address on <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter>, but want to store your log messages on <parameter>syslog-ng-server</parameter> using the IP address of the original host (that is, <parameter>client-host</parameter>), you can enable the <parameter>spoof-source()</parameter> option on <parameter>syslog-ng-relay</parameter>. However, <parameter>spoof-source()</parameter> works only under the following conditions:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The &abbrev; binary has been compiled with the <parameter>--enable-spoof-source</parameter> option.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The log messages are sent using the highly unreliable UDP transport protocol. (Extremely unrecommended.)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
</section>
