<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
%entities;
]> 
<chapter xml:id="chapter-fips" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Federal Information Processing Standards (FIPS)</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>Federal Information Processing Standards</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>FIPS</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Starting from &abbrev; version 5.0.4, LTS versions are FIPS-compliant.</para>
    
    <section>
        <title>Installing FIPS-compliant &abbrev;</title>
        <para>For the FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev;, you are required to use the new license file. It uses SHA-512 algorithm, and therefore is accepted by the FIPS-compliant version. The non-FIPS-compliant &abbrev; will accept both the previously released license files and the new license files as well.</para>
        <para>The following Linux platforms are supported:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>debian-etch, debian-lenny, debian-squeeze </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>suse-10.1, sles-10.2, sles-11.0, sles-11.1 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>rhel-4, rhel-5, rhel-6 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>ubuntu-hardy, ubuntu-lucid </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev; is installed using a dedicated installer. The FIPS-compliant &abbrev; installer will replace the existing non-FIPS-compliant &abbrev; and the tools shipped with it to its FIPS-compliant counterpart. For the supported plaforms both .run and native installers are available. The name of the FIPS-compliant &abbrev; installers includes the 'fips' specifier, for example: <filename>syslog-ng-premium-edition-fips-5.0.4-linux-glibc2.3.6-amd64.run</filename>.</para>
        <para>Upgrading from a non-FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev; to a FIPS-compliant version is simple, in most cases you can use your old configuration files. After starting the FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev;, it will print those options in your configuration that cannot be used with the FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev;.</para>
        <para>To check the version of &abbrev;, use the <parameter>-V</parameter> command line option. It will display version details, modules, and enabled options. In the FIPS-compliant version the <parameter>Enable-FIPS</parameter> option is set to <parameter>on</parameter> while in the non-FIPS-compliant version it is set to <parameter>off</parameter>.</para>
        <para>The startup message will also indicate this, the FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev; will display the following: <parameter>FIPS-mode='enabled' </parameter>.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Limitations of the FIPS-compliant &abbrev;</title>
        <para>The FIPS-compliant &abbrev; is compatible with the non-FIPS-compliant version with the following limitations:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The FIPS-compliant version can only be run on Linux platforms.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev; uses only those cryptographic algorithms that are considered to be secure according to the FIPS-140 standard, therefore the support of some hashing and encryption algorithms have been removed (for example MD5 and DES).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>There is no database support in the FIPS-compliant version (neither as source nor as destination).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The layout of the Certiface Authority directory (ca-dir) and the Certificate Revocation List directory (crl-dir) cannot be hashed with MD5. If the layout of your Certiface Authority directory (ca-dir) or the Certificate Revocation List directory is hashed with MD5, you must rehash it with SHA-1 to be able to use it with the FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev;.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>To use verified TLS/SSL communtication in the FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev;, you are required to use certificates that are using one of the SHA-1 or SHA-2 algorithms ('SHA1', 'SHA224', 'SHA256', 'SHA384' or 'SHA512').</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The FIPS-comliant version of &abbrev; is unable to use DES or MD5 during the SNMP-authentication.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>To use logstore with the FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev; you are required to set the cipher to one of the AES-based algorithms and to set the digest to one of the SHA-1 or SHA-2 algorithms ('SHA1', 'SHA224', 'SHA256', 'SHA384' or 'SHA512').</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>With the FIPS-compliant version of &abbrev;, you will be unable to use the previously generated logstores that do not meet the abovementioned requirements. However, previously generated logstores that meet those requirements can be used.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Legal Notice of FIPS Compliance of Syslog-ng Premium Edition</title>
        <para>Syslog-ng Premium Edition version 5.0.4 and the subsequent releases may claim FIPS compliance by use of the OpenSSL FIPS Object Module v2.0.5 cryptographic component.
            This component was certified by the Open Source Software Institute and obtained the FIPS-140-2 validation Level 1 (certificate number 1747) from the U.S. National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) and the Communications Security Establishment Canada (CSEC).</para>
        <para>The FIPS-compliant version of syslog-ng Premium Edition v5.0.4 and the subsequent releases exclusively use the OpenSSL FIPS Object Module indicated above for crypthograpy.
            The build process of the FIPS-compliant version of syslog-ng Premium Edition complies with the OpenSSL FIPS 140-2 Security Policy Version 2.0.5f.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>
