<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
 [
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../shared/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<chapter xml:id="chapter-multithreading" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Multithreading and scaling in &abbrev;</title>
    <indexterm significance="preferred">
        <primary>multithreading in &abbrev;</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>scaling to multiple CPUs</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>threading</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>performance</primary>
        <secondary>using multithreading</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Starting with version <phrase condition="pe">4 F1</phrase><phrase condition="ose">3.3</phrase>, &abbrev; can process sources and destinations in multithreaded mode to scale to multiple CPUs or cores for increased performance. Starting with version <phrase condition="ose">3.6</phrase><phrase condition="pe">5 F4</phrase>, this multithreaded mode is the default.</para>
    <section xml:id="multithreading-in-syslog-ng">
        <title>Multithreading concepts of &abbrev;</title>
        <para>This section is a brief overview on how &abbrev; works in multithreaded mode. It is mainly for illustration purposes: the concept has been somewhat simplified and may not completely match reality.</para>
        <note>
            <para>The way &abbrev; uses multithreading may change in future releases. The current documentation applies to version &version;.</para>
        </note>
        <para>&abbrev; always uses multiple threads:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>A main thread that is always running</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>A number of worker threads that process the messages. You can influence the behavior of worker threads using the <parameter>threaded()</parameter> option and the <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> command-line option.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Some other, special threads for internal functionalities. For example, certain destinations run in a separate thread, independently of the multithreading (<parameter>threaded()</parameter>) and <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> settings of &abbrev;.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The maximum number of worker threads &abbrev; uses is the number of CPUs or cores in the host running &abbrev; (up to 64). You can limit this value using the <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> command-line option that sets the maximum total number of threads &abbrev; can use, including the main &abbrev; thread. However, the <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> option does not affect the supervisor of &abbrev;. The supervisor is a separate process (see <xref linkend="syslog-ng.8"/>), but certain operating systems might display it as a thread. In addition, certain destinations always run in a separate thread, independently of the multithreading (<parameter>threaded()</parameter>) and <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> settings of &abbrev;.</para>
        <para>When an event requiring a new thread occurs (for example, &abbrev; receives new messages, or a destination becomes available), &abbrev; tries to start a new thread. If there are no free threads, the task waits until a thread finishes its task and becomes available. There are two types of worker threads:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Reader threads read messages from a source (as many as possible, but limited by the <parameter>log-fetch-limit()</parameter> and <parameter>log-iw-size()</parameter> options. The thread then processes these messages, that is, performs filtering, rewriting and other tasks as necessary, and puts the log message into the queue of the destination. If the destination does not have a queue (for example, usertty), the reader thread sends the message to the destination, without the interaction of a separate writer thread.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Writer threads take the messages from the queue of the destination and send them to the destination, that is, write the messages into a file, or send them to the syslog server over the network. The writer thread starts to process messages from the queue only if the destination is writable, and there are enough messages in the queue, as set in the <parameter>flush-lines()</parameter> and the <parameter>flush-timeout()</parameter> options. Writer threads stop processing messages when the destination becomes unavailable, or there are no more messages in the queue.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Sources and destinations affected by multithreading</title>
            <para>The following list describes which sources and destinations can use multiple threads. Changing the <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> command-line option changes the number of threads available to these sources and destinations.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <parameter>tcp</parameter> and <userinput>syslog(tcp)</userinput> sources can process independent connections in separate threads. The number of independent connections is limited by the <parameter>max-connections()</parameter> option of the source. Separate sources are processed by separate thread, for example, if you have two separate <parameter>tcp</parameter> sources defined that receive messages on different IP addresses or port, &abbrev; will use separate threads for these sources even if they both have only a single active connection.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <parameter>udp</parameter>, <parameter>file</parameter>, and <parameter>pipe</parameter> sources use a single thread for every source statement.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <parameter>tcp</parameter>, <parameter>syslog</parameter>, and <parameter>pipe</parameter> destinations use a single thread for every destination.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <parameter>file</parameter> destination uses a single thread for writing the destination file, but may use a separate thread for each destination file if the filename includes macros.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Sources and destinations not affected by multithreading</title>
            <para>The following list describes sources and destinations that use a separate thread even if you disable multithreading in &abbrev;, in addition to the limit set in the <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> command-line option.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem condition="pe">
                <para>The <parameter>logstore</parameter> destination uses separate threads for writing the messages from the journal to the logstore files, and also for timestamping. These threads are independent from the setting of the <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> command-line option.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Every <parameter>sql</parameter> destination uses its own thread. These threads are independent from the setting of the <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> command-line option.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <parameter>java</parameter> destinations use one thread, even if there are multiple Java-based destinations configured. This thread is independent from the setting of the <parameter>--worker-threads</parameter> command-line option.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="configuring-multithreading">
        <title>Configuring multithreading</title>
        <para>Starting with version <phrase condition="ose">3.6</phrase><phrase condition="pe">5 F4</phrase>, &abbrev; runs in multithreaded mode by default. You can enable multithreading in &abbrev; using the following methods:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Globally using the <userinput>threaded(yes)</userinput> option.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Separately for selected sources or destinations using the <userinput>flags("threaded")</userinput> option.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <example>
            <title>Enabling multithreading</title>
            <para>To enable multithreading globally, use the <parameter>threaded</parameter> option:</para>
            <synopsis>options {threaded(yes) ; };</synopsis>
            <para>To enable multithreading only for a selected source or destination, use the <userinput>flags("threaded")</userinput> option:</para>
            <synopsis>source s_tcp_syslog { network(ip(127.0.0.1) port(1999) flags("syslog-protocol", "threaded") ); };</synopsis>
        </example>
    </section>
<!-- This section below is re-used in the syslog-ng pe performance whitepaper executive summary section. There are two different files and the reference to the entities is different on purpose. -->
    <xi:include href="../../shared/multithreading-performance.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</chapter>
