<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;]>
<chapter xml:id="chapter-intro" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Introduction to syslog-ng</title>
    <para>This chapter introduces the &product; application in a non-technical manner, discussing how and why is it useful, and the benefits it offers to an existing IT infrastructure.</para>
    <section xml:id="what-syslog-ng-is">
        <title>What syslog-ng is</title>
        <para>The &product; (&abbrev;) application is a flexible and highly scalable system logging application that is ideal for creating centralized and trusted logging solutions. Among others, &abbrev; allows you the following.</para>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Secure and reliable log transfer</title>
            <para>The &abbrev; application enables you to send the log messages of your hosts to remote servers using the latest protocol standards. You can collect and store your log data centrally on dedicated log servers. Transfer log messages using the <phrase condition="pe6"><trademark>RLTP</trademark></phrase><phrase condition="ose">TCP</phrase> protocol ensures that no messages are lost.</para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Disk-based message buffering</title>
                <para>To minimize the risk of losing important log messages, the &abbrev; application can store messages on the local hard disk if the central log server or the network connection becomes unavailable. The syslog-ng application automatically sends the stored messages to the server when the connection is reestablished, in the same order the messages were received. The disk buffer is persistent – no messages are lost even if syslog-ng is restarted.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Secure logging using TLS</title>
                <para>Log messages may contain sensitive information that should not be accessed by third parties. Therefore, &abbrev; supports the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol to encrypt the communication. TLS also allows you to authenticate your clients and the logserver using X.509 certificates.</para>
            </formalpara>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Flexible data extraction and processing</title>
            <para>Most log messages are inherently unstructured, which makes them difficult to process. To overcome this problem, &abbrev; comes with a set of built-in parsers, which you can combine to build very complex things.</para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Filter and classify</title>
                <para>The &abbrev; application can sort the incoming log messages based on their content and various parameters like the source host, application, and priority. You can create directories, files, and database tables dynamically using macros. Complex filtering using regular expressions and boolean operators offers almost unlimited flexibility to forward only the important log messages to the selected destinations.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Parse and rewrite</title>
                <para>The &abbrev; application can segment log messages to named fields or columns, and also modify the values of these fields. You can process JSON messages, key-value pairs, and more.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <para>To get the most information out of your log data, &abbrev; allows you to correlate log messages and aggregate the extracted information into a single message. You can also use external information to enrich your log data.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Big data clusters</title>
            <para>The log data that your organization has to process, store, and review increases daily, so many organizations use big data solutions for their logs. To accomodate this huge amount of data, &abbrev; natively supports storing log messages in HDFS files and Elasticsearch clusters.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Message queue support</title>
            <para>Large organizations increasingly rely on queuing infrastructure to transfer their data. For that purpose, &abbrev; supports Apache Kafka<phrase condition="ose">, the Advanced Message Queuing Protocol (AMQP), and the Simple Text Oriented Messaging Protocol (STOMP)</phrase>.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>SQL, NoSQL, and monitoring</title>
            <para>Storing your log messages in a database allows you to easily search and query the messages and interoperate with log analyzing applications. The syslog-ng application supports the following databases: MongoDB, MSSQL, MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, and SQLite.</para>
            <para condition="ose">&abbrev; also allows you to extract the information you need from your log data, and directly send it to your Graphite, Redis, or Riemann monitoring system.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Wide protocol and platform support</title>
            <formalpara>
                <title>syslog protocol standards</title>
                <para>syslog-ng not only supports legacy BSD syslog (RFC3164) and the enhanced RFC5424 protocols, but also JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) and journald message formats.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Heterogeneous environments</title>
                <para>The &abbrev; application is the ideal choice to collect logs in massively heterogeneous environments using several different operating systems and hardware platforms, including Linux, Unix, <phrase condition="pe6">Microsoft Windows, </phrase>BSD, Sun Solaris, HP-UX, Tru64, and AIX.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>IPv4 and IPv6 support</title>
                <para>The syslog-ng application can operate in both IPv4 and IPv6 network environments, and can receive and send messages to both types of networks.</para>
            </formalpara>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect condition="pe">
            <title>Excellent performance</title>
            <para>Depending on the exact &abbrev; configuration, environment, and other parameters, &abbrev; is capable of processing:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Over 635,000 messages per second (over 235 MB of data per second) when receiving messages from multiple connections and storing them in text files.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Over 615,000 messages per second (over 230 MB of data per second) when receiving messages from multiple secure (TLS-encrypted) connections and storing them in text files.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="what-syslog-ng-is-not">
        <title>What syslog-ng is not</title>
        <para>The syslog-ng application is not log analysis software. It can filter log messages and select only the ones matching certain criteria. It can even convert the messages and restructure them to a predefined format, or parse the messages and segment them into different fields. But syslog-ng cannot interpret and analyze the meaning behind the messages, or recognize patterns in the occurrence of different messages.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="why-do-you-need-syslog-ng">
        <title>Why is syslog-ng needed?</title>
        <para>Log messages contain information about the events happening on the hosts. Monitoring system events is essential for security and system health monitoring reasons.</para>
        <para>The original syslog protocol separates messages based on the priority of the message and the facility sending the message. These two parameters alone are often inadequate to consistently classify messages, as many applications might use the same facility &mdash; and the facility itself is not even included in the log message. To make things worse, many log messages contain unimportant information. The syslog-ng application helps you to select only the really interesting messages, and forward them to a central server.</para>
        <para>Company policies or other regulations often require log messages to be archived. Storing the important messages in a central location greatly simplifies this process.</para>
        <para condition="pe">For details on how can you use &abbrev; to comply with various regulations, see the <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://pages.balabit.com/regulatory-compliance-and-system-logging.html">Regulatory compliance and system logging whitepaper</link>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="syslog-ng-whatsnew">
        <title>What is new in &product; &version;?</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>For details on the news and highlights of &product; &version;, see the <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-whatsnew"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>For details on changes in The &product; &version; Administrator Guide, see <xref linkend="pe-changes"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="syslog-ng-users">
        <title>Who uses syslog-ng?</title>
        <para>The syslog-ng application is used worldwide by companies and institutions who collect and manage the logs of several hosts, and want to store them in a centralized, organized way. Using syslog-ng is particularly advantageous for:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Internet Service Providers</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Financial institutions and companies requiring policy compliance</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Server, web, and application hosting companies</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Datacenters</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Wide area network (WAN) operators</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Server farm administrators.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <xi:include href="../../xml-stylesheet/common/syslog-ng-public-references.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="supported-platforms" condition="pe">
        <title>Supported platforms</title>
        <indexterm> <primary>supported architectures</primary> </indexterm>
        <indexterm> <primary>supported operating systems</primary> </indexterm>
        <para>The &product; application is officially supported on the following platforms. Note that the following table is for general reference only, and is not always accurate about the supported platforms and options available for specific platforms. The latest version of this table is available at <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://www.balabit.com/log-management-software/supported-platforms">https://www.balabit.com/log-management-software/supported-platforms</link>. Unless explicitly noted otherwise, the subsequent releases of the platform (for example, Windows Server 2008 R2 and its service packs in case of Windows Server 2008) are also supported.</para>
        <table>
            <title>Platforms supported by &product;</title>
            <tgroup cols="7">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry/>
                        <entry align="left"> x86 </entry>
                        <entry align="left"> x86_64 </entry>
                        <entry align="left"> SPARC </entry>
                        <entry align="left"> SPARC64 </entry>
                        <entry> PowerPC </entry>
                        <entry> IA64 </entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> AIX 7.1 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> CentOS 5 </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> CentOS 6 </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry> CentOS 7 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry> Debian 7 (wheezy) </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry> Debian 8 (jessie) </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> FreeBSD 10 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> HP-UX 11i v3 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry align="left"> Oracle Linux 6 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry align="left"> Oracle Linux 7 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry align="left"> openSUSE 11 </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry align="left"> Red Hat EL 6 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry align="left"> Red Hat EL 7 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry align="left"> SLES 12 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> Solaris 10 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry align="left"> Solaris 11 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry> Ubuntu 12.04 LTS (Precise Pangolin) </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry> Ubuntu 14.04 LTS (Trusty Tahr) </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry> Ubuntu 16.04 LTS (Xenial Xerus) </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> Windows Server 2008 </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> Windows Server 2012 </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> Windows Vista </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> Windows 7 </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> Windows 8 </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row condition="pe6">
                        <entry> Windows 10 </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> &#10004; </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                        <entry> - </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <warning>
            <para>Certain sources and destinations are not supported on every platform (particularly, the <parameter>sql()</parameter><phrase condition="pe6"> source and</phrase> destination, and the <parameter>hdfs()</parameter> destination). For details, see the description of the specific source and destination.</para>
        </warning>
        <xi:include href="../../common/wnt/warning-rhel6-python.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
        <para condition="pe6">The central &abbrev; server can be installed on Microsoft Windows platforms as well, in this case you can configure &abbrev; using a configuration file, like on any other platform. However, if you want only to forward eventlog and other log messages from Windows to your central logserver, you can use the &agent; application. The &agent; can be managed centrally from a domain controller, and can be configured from a graphical interface as well. The &agent; application is available as part of &product;.</para>
        <para>For details about the syslog-ng Agent for Windows application, see the <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://syslog-ng.com/documents/html/syslog-ng-pe-6.0-guides/en/syslog-ng-windows-agent-guide-admin/html/index.html">&agent; documentation</link>. For an agent-less solution, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-wec-guide"/>.</para>
        <para>For using &abbrev; on other platforms (for example, AIX, FreeBSD, HP-UX, Solaris, Microsoft Windows), see <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://www.balabit.com/documents/syslog-ng-pe-6.0-guides/en/syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin/html/supported-platforms.html">&pe; 6 LTS</link>.</para>
        <section xml:id="certified-packages" condition="pe">
            <title>Certified packages</title>
            <indexterm> <primary>RedHat Ready</primary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>Novell Ready</primary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>certified packages</primary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>&abbrev; certifications</primary> </indexterm>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="ready-logos.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="&imgroot;/ready-logos.png" contentwidth="5cm"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>Starting from version 4.0, &product; is <emphasis>Novell Ready</emphasis> certified for the following platforms:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 10 on the x86 and x86_64 AMD64 &amp; Intel EM64T architectures</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 11 on the x86 and x86_64 AMD64 &amp; Intel EM64T architectures</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Starting from version 4.0, &product; is <emphasis>RedHat Ready</emphasis> certified for the following platforms:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 2.1 on the x86 architecture</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 3 on the x86_64 AMD64 &amp; Intel EM64T architecture</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 4 on the x86 and x86_64 AMD64 &amp; Intel EM64T architectures</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 5 on the x86 and x86_64 AMD64 &amp; Intel EM64T architectures</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6 on the x86 and x86_64 AMD64 &amp; Intel EM64T architectures</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Starting from version 5.4, &product; is <emphasis>MapR</emphasis> certified.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
