<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE procedure
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../shared/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<procedure xml:id="compiling-syslog-ng" condition="ose" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Compiling syslog-ng from source</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>compiling syslog-ng OSE</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>installing syslog-ng OSE from source</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Purpose:</title>
        <para/>
    </formalpara>
    <para>To compile syslog-ng Open Source Edition (OSE) from the source code, complete the following steps. Alternatively, you can use precompiled binary packages on several platforms. For a list of third-party packages available for various Linux, UNIX, and other platforms, see the <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://syslog-ng.org/3rd-party-binaries/">&abbrev; third-party binaries page</link>.</para>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Steps:</title>
        <para/>
    </formalpara>
    <step>
        <para>Download the latest version of syslog-ng OSE from <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://github.com/balabit/syslog-ng/">GitHub</link>. The source code is available as a tar.gz archive file.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Install the following packages that are required to compile syslog-ng. These packages are available for most UNIX/Linux systems. Alternatively, you can also download the sources and compile them.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>A version of the <emphasis>gcc</emphasis> C compiler that properly supports Thread Local Storage (TLS), for example, version 4.5.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis>GNU flex</emphasis> lexical analyser generator, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://flex.sourceforge.net/">available here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis>bison</emphasis> parser generator, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/bison/">available here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The development files of the <emphasis>glib</emphasis> library, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://freshmeat.net/projects/glib/">available here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The development files of the <emphasis>Autoconf Archive</emphasis> package, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/autoconf-archive/">available here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The &abbrev; application now uses PCRE-type regular expressions by default. It requires the <parameter>libpcre</parameter> library package, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/pcre/files/pcre/">available here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <xi:include href="../../shared/chunk/para-java-requirements.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </step>
    <step>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>destinations</primary>
            <secondary>http()</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>http()</primary>
            <secondary>compiling</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>If you want to post log messages as HTTP requests using the <parameter>http()</parameter> destination, install the development files of the <emphasis>libcurl</emphasis> library. This library is not needed if you use the <parameter>--disable-http</parameter> compile option. Alternatively, you can use a Java-based implementation of the HTTP destination.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>spoof_source</primary>
            <secondary>compiling</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>If you want to use the spoof-source function of syslog-ng, install the development files of the <emphasis>libnet</emphasis> library, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://libnet.sourceforge.net"
            >available here</link>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>destinations</primary>
            <secondary>smtp()</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>smtp()</primary>
            <secondary>compiling</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>If you want to send e-mails using the <parameter>smtp()</parameter> destination, install the development files of the <emphasis>libesmtp</emphasis> library. This library is not needed if you use the <parameter>--disable-smtp</parameter> compile option.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>If you want to use the <emphasis>/etc/hosts.deny</emphasis> and <emphasis>/etc/hosts.allow</emphasis> for TCP access, install the development files of the <emphasis>libwrap</emphasis> (also called TCP-wrappers) library, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://ftp.porcupine.org/pub/security/index.html"> available here</link>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Enter the new directory and issue the following commands. (If the <filename>./configure</filename> file does not exist, for example, because you cloned the repository from GitHub instead of using a release tarball, execute the <command>./autogen.sh</command> command.)</para>
        <synopsis>$ ./configure
$ make
$ make install</synopsis>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Uncompress the syslog-ng archive using the</para>
        <synopsis>tar xvfz syslog-ng-x.xx.tar.gz</synopsis>
        <para>or the</para>
        <synopsis>unzip -c syslog-ng-x.xx.tar.gz | tar xvf -</synopsis>
        <para>command. A new directory containing the source code of syslog-ng will be created.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Enter the new directory and issue the following commands:</para>
        <synopsis>$ ./configure
$ make
$ make install</synopsis>
        <para>These commands will build syslog-ng using its default options.</para>
        <note>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>On Solaris, use <parameter>gmake</parameter> (GNU make) instead of <parameter>make</parameter>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <indexterm>
                        <primary>silent rules</primary>
                        <see>silent building</see>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm>
                        <primary>silent building</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <para>To build &abbrev; with less verbose output, use the <command>make V=0</command> command. This results in shorter, less verbose output, making warnings and other anomalies easier to notice. Note that silent-rules support is only available in recent automake versions.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </note>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>If needed, use the following options to change how syslog-ng is compiled using the following command syntax:</para>
        <synopsis>$ ./configure --compile-time-option-name</synopsis>
        <note>
            <para>You can also use <emphasis>--disable options</emphasis>, to explicitly disable a feature and override autodetection. For example, to disable the TCP-wrapper support, use the <emphasis>--disable-tcp-wrapper</emphasis> option. For the list of available compiling options, see <xref linkend="syslog-ng-compile-options"/>.</para>
        </note>
        <warning>
            <para>The default linking mode of syslog-ng is <parameter>dynamic</parameter>. This means that syslog-ng might not be able to start up if the <parameter>/usr</parameter> directory is on NFS. On platforms where syslog-ng is used as a system logger, the <parameter>--enable-mixed-linking</parameter> is preferred.</para>
        </warning>
    </step>
</procedure>
