<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section [
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;]>
<section xml:id="syslog-ng-compile-options" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" condition="ose">
    <title>Compiling options of &abbrev;</title>
    <para>When compiling &abbrev; from source, you can use the following compiling options.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-all-modules</emphasis> This option will turn on or off all modules and most features when enabled, unless a feature is explicitly disabled, or not detected automatically. Currently, this means that you must explicitly enable the <parameter>pacct()</parameter> source, since it is not detected automatically (all other modules are compiled automatically if the required libraries are available).</para>
            <para>This also means that the Sun Streams source is enabled on every platform, not only on Solaris, causing a compile error. Use <userinput>--enable-all-modules</userinput> together with <userinput>--disable-sun-streams</userinput>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--disable-http</emphasis> Disable support for the <parameter>http()</parameter> destination that is based on <emphasis>libcurl</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--disable-python</emphasis> Disable support for Python-based modules.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--disable-json</emphasis> Disable JSON support. It also disables <parameter>json-parser</parameter>, and the <parameter>format-cim</parameter> and <parameter>format-json</parameter> template functions. Also, it disables JSON support even if the <parameter>json-c</parameter> library is installed and detected (see <emphasis>--enable-json</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--disable-smtp</emphasis> Disable SMTP support. By default, SMTP support is enabled if the libesmtp library is detected.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>destinations</primary> <secondary>amqp()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>amqp()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-amqp</emphasis> Enable the amqp destination (enabled by default). The source of the RabbitMQ client is included in the source code package of &abbrev;. To use an external client instead, use the <parameter>--with-librabbitmq-client=system</parameter> compiling option. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-amqp"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-debug</emphasis> Include debug information.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-dynamic-linking</emphasis> Compile syslog-ng as a completely dynamic binary. If not specified syslog-ng uses mixed linking (<parameter>--enable-mixed-linking</parameter>): it links dynamically to system libraries and statically to everything else.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>geoip</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-geoip</emphasis> Enable GEOIP support, required for the <parameter>geoip2</parameter> template function and the <parameter>geoip2-parser</parameter> (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libmaxminddb</parameter> library is detected).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-ipv6</emphasis> Enable IPv6 support.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-java</emphasis> Enable support for Java-based modules. For other requirements, see the description of the Java-based module (for example, <xref linkend="destination-elasticsearch-prerequisites"/>) that you want to use.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-java-modules</emphasis> Compile the Gradle projects of every Java module available in <filename>modules/java-modules</filename>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>json-parser</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>format-json</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>format-cim</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-json</emphasis> Enables JSON support (by default, it uses the <parameter>json-c</parameter> library included in the source code package of &abbrev;). JSON support is required for <parameter>json-parser</parameter>, and the <parameter>format-cim</parameter> and <parameter>format-json</parameter> template functions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-linux-caps</emphasis> Enable support for capabilities on Linux. For details, see <xref linkend="syslog-ng.8"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>destinations</primary> <secondary>mongodb()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>mongodb()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-mongodb</emphasis> Enable the mongodb destination (enabled by default). The source of the MongoDB client is included in the source code package of &abbrev;. To use an external MongoDB client instead, use the <parameter>--with-libmongo-client=system</parameter> compiling option. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-mongodb"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>sources</primary> <secondary>pacct()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>pacct()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-pacct</emphasis> Enable using the <parameter>pacct()</parameter> driver to collect process-accounting logs on Linux systems.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-python</emphasis> Enable support for Python-based modules.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>destinations</primary> <secondary>redis()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>redis()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-redis</emphasis> Enable the redis destination (enabled by default). The source of the libhiredis client (0.11 or newer) must be available. To specify the location of the library, use the <userinput>--with-libhiredis=&lt;path-to-libhiredis&gt;</userinput> compiling option. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-redis"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>destinations</primary> <secondary>riemann()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>riemann()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-riemann</emphasis> Enable the riemann destination (enabled by default). The source of the libriemann client must be available. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-riemann"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-spoof-source</emphasis> Enable spoof_source feature (disabled by default).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>destinations</primary> <secondary>sql()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>sql()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-sql</emphasis> Enables the sql() destination (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libdbi</parameter> library version 0.9 or newer is installed and detected).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>ssl support</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-ssl</emphasis> Enable SSL support, required for encrypted message transfer, as well as template functions that calculate hashes and UUIDs (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libopenssl</parameter> library is detected).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-sun-door</emphasis> Enable Sun door support even if not detected (autodetected by default).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-sun-streams</emphasis> Enable Sun STREAMS support even if not detected (autodetected by default).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>systemd</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-systemd</emphasis> Enable systemd support on Linux platforms (autodetected by default) (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libsystemd-daemon</parameter> library is detected).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--enable-tcp-wrapper</emphasis> Enable using <emphasis>/etc/hosts.deny</emphasis> and <emphasis>/etc/hosts.allow</emphasis> for TCP access (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libwrap</parameter> libraries are detected).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--with-embedded-crypto</emphasis> If this option is set, the crypto library is linked directly into libsyslog-ng: the sources of libsyslog-ng-crypto will be appended to the libsyslog-ng sources, and -crypto is not built.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--with-ivykis</emphasis> Specifies which ivykis implementation to use (default value: internal). The source of ivykis is included in the source code package of &abbrev; and is used by default. To use an external implementation instead, use the <parameter>--with-ivykis=system</parameter> compiling option.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>destinations</primary> <secondary>http()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>http()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--with-libcurl</emphasis> Specifies the path to the libcurl library. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-http-nonjava"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>destinations</primary> <secondary>redis()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>redis()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--with-libhiredis</emphasis> Specifies the path to the libhiredis library (0.11 or newer). For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-redis"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>destinations</primary> <secondary>mongodb()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>mongodb()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--with-libmongo-client</emphasis> Specifies which MongoDB client to use (default value: internal). The source of the mongodb client is included in the source code package of &abbrev;. To use an external MongoDB client instead, use the <parameter>--with-libmongo-client=system</parameter> compiling option. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-mongodb"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <indexterm> <primary>destinations</primary> <secondary>amqp()</secondary> </indexterm>
            <indexterm> <primary>amqp()</primary> <secondary>compiling</secondary> </indexterm>
            <para><emphasis>--with-librabbitmq-client</emphasis> Specifies which RabbitMQ client to use (default value: internal). The source of the rabbitmq client is included in the source code package of &abbrev; and is used by default. To use an external client instead, use the <parameter>--with-librabbitmq-client=system</parameter> compiling option. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-amqp"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--with-module-dir</emphasis> Specifies a single directory where the &abbrev; Makefile will install the modules.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--module-install-dir</emphasis> Specifies &abbrev;'s module installation directory (normally <filename>$prefix/lib/syslog-ng</filename>). All Java-based SCLs use this option.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--with-module-path</emphasis> Specifies a colon-separated (:) list of directories, where the &abbrev; binary will search for modules.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--with-python</emphasis> Specifies which Python version to use, for example, <userinput>--with-python=2.7</userinput></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--with-timezone-dir</emphasis> Specifies the directory where syslog-ng looks for the timezone files to resolve the <parameter>time-zone()</parameter> and <parameter>local-time-zone()</parameter> options. If not specified, the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/share/zoneinfo/</filename> and <filename>/usr/share/zoneinfo/</filename> directories are checked, respectively. Note that HP-UX uses a unique file format (<parameter>tztab</parameter>) to describe the timezone information, but that format is currently not supported in syslog-ng. As a workaround, copy the zoneinfo files from another, non-HP-UX system to the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/share/zoneinfo/</filename> directory of your HP-UX system.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><emphasis>--without-compile-date</emphasis> Removes the compilation date from the binary. For example, as openSUSE checks if recompilation changes the binary to detect if dependent packages need to be rebuilt or not, and including the date changes the binary every time.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</section>
