<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE procedure
 [  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
 %entities;]>
<procedure xml:id="compiling-syslog-ng" condition="ose" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Compiling syslog-ng from source</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>compiling syslog-ng OSE</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>installing syslog-ng OSE from source</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Purpose:</title>
        <para/>
    </formalpara>
    <para>To compile syslog-ng Open Source Edition (OSE) from the source code, complete the following steps. Alternatively, you can use precompiled binary packages on several platforms. For a list of third-party packages available for various Linux, UNIX, and other platforms, see <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://syslog-ng.com/3rd-party-binaries">third-party binaries page</link>.</para>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Steps:</title>
        <para/>
    </formalpara>
    <step>
        <para>Download the latest version of syslog-ng OSE from <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://github.com/balabit/syslog-ng">GitHub</link>. The source code is available as a tar.gz archive file.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Download the latest version of the EventLog library <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://www.balabit.com/downloads/files/eventlog/0.2/"
                >here</link>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Install the following packages that are required to compile syslog-ng. These packages are available for most UNIX/Linux systems. Alternatively, you can also download the sources and compile them.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>A version of the <emphasis>gcc</emphasis> C compiler that properly supports Thread Local Storage (TLS), for example, version 4.5 (at least version. For building recent gcc versions on Solaris, see <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://jblopen.com/node/16">http://jblopen.com/node/16</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis>GNU flex</emphasis> lexical analyser generator, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://flex.sourceforge.net/"
                        >available here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis>bison</emphasis> parser generator, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/bison/"
                    >available here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The development files of the <emphasis>glib</emphasis> library, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://freshmeat.net/projects/glib/"
                        >available here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </step>
    <step>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>spoof_source</primary>
            <secondary>compiling</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>If you want to use the spoof-source function of syslog-ng, install the development files of the <emphasis>libnet</emphasis> library, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="http://libnet.sourceforge.net"
            >available here</link>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>destinations</primary>
            <secondary>smtp()</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>smtp()</primary>
            <secondary>compiling</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>If you want to send e-mails using the <parameter>smtp()</parameter> destination, install the development files of the <emphasis>libesmtp</emphasis> library. This library is not needed if you use the <parameter>--disable-smtp</parameter> compile option.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>If you want to use the <emphasis>/etc/hosts.deny</emphasis> and <emphasis>/etc/hosts.allow</emphasis> for TCP access, install the development files of the <emphasis>libwrap</emphasis> (also called TCP-wrappers) library, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="ftp://ftp.porcupine.org/pub/security/index.html"> available here</link>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Uncompress the eventlog archive using the</para>
        <synopsis>$ tar xvfz eventlog-x.x.x.x.tar.gz</synopsis>
        <para>or the</para>
        <synopsis>$ gunzip -c eventlog-x.x.x.x.tar.gz | tar xvf -</synopsis>
        <para>command. A new directory containing the source code of eventlog will be created.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>By default, eventlog creates a file used by the syslog-ng configure script in the <emphasis>/usr/local/lib/pkgconfig</emphasis> directory. Issue the following command to add this directory to your PKG_CONFIG_PATH:</para>
        <synopsis>PKG_CONFIG_PATH=/usr/local/lib/pkgconfig:$PKG_CONFIG_PATH</synopsis>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Enter the new directory and issue the following commands:</para>
        <synopsis>$ ./configure
$ make
$ make install</synopsis>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Uncompress the syslog-ng archive using the</para>
        <synopsis>tar xvfz syslog-ng-x.xx.tar.gz</synopsis>
        <para>or the</para>
        <synopsis>unzip -c syslog-ng-x.xx.tar.gz | tar xvf -</synopsis>
        <para>command. A new directory containing the source code of syslog-ng will be created.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Enter the new directory and issue the following commands:</para>
        <synopsis>$ ./configure
$ make
$ make install</synopsis>
        <para>These commands will build syslog-ng using its default options.</para>
        <note>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>On Solaris, use <parameter>gmake</parameter> (GNU make) instead of <parameter>make</parameter>.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <indexterm>
                        <primary>silent rules</primary>
                        <see>silent building</see>
                    </indexterm>
                    <indexterm>
                        <primary>silent building</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <para>To build &abbrev; with less verbose output, use the <command>make V=0</command> command. This results in shorter, less verbose output, making warnings and other anomalies easier to notice. Note that silent-rules support is only available in recent automake versions.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </note>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>If needed, use the following options to change how syslog-ng is compiled using the following command syntax:</para>
        <synopsis>$ ./configure --compile-time-option-name</synopsis>
        <note>
            <para>You can also use <emphasis>--disable options</emphasis>, to explicitly disable a feature and override autodetection. For example, to disable the TCP-wrapper support, use the <emphasis>--disable-tcp-wrapper</emphasis> option.</para>
        </note>
        <warning>
            <para>Starting with syslog-ng Open Source Edition 3.0.2, default linking mode of syslog-ng is <parameter>dynamic</parameter>. This means that syslog-ng might not be able to start up if the <parameter>/usr</parameter> directory is on NFS. On platforms where syslog-ng is used as a system logger, the <parameter>--enable-mixed-linking</parameter> is preferred.</para>
        </warning>
        <itemizedlist xml:id="syslog-ng-compile-options">
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--disable-json</emphasis> Disable JSON support. It also disables <parameter>json-parser</parameter>, and the <parameter>format-json</parameter> template function. Also, it disables JSON support even if the <parameter>json-c</parameter> library is installed and detected (see <emphasis>--enable-json</emphasis>).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--disable-smtp</emphasis> Disable SMTP support. By default, SMTP support is enabled if the libesmtp library is detected.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>destinations</primary>
                    <secondary>amqp()</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>amqp()</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-amqp</emphasis> Enable the amqp destination (enabled by default). The source of the RabbitMQ client is included in the source code package of &abbrev;. To use an external client instead, use the <parameter>--with-librabbitmq-client=system</parameter> compiling option. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-amqp"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-debug</emphasis> Include debug information.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-dynamic-linking</emphasis> Compile syslog-ng as a completely dynamic binary. If not specified syslog-ng uses mixed linking (<parameter>--enable-mixed-linking</parameter>): it links dynamically to system libraries and statically to everything else.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>geoip</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-geoip</emphasis> Enable GEOIP support, required for the <parameter>geoip</parameter> template function (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libgeoip</parameter> library is detected).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-ipv6</emphasis> Enable IPv6 support.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>json-parser</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>format-json</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-json</emphasis> Enables JSON support (enabled automatically if the <parameter>json-c</parameter> 0.9 or newer library is installed and detected).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-linux-caps</emphasis> Enable support for capabilities on Linux. For details, see <xref linkend="syslog-ng.8"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>destinations</primary>
                    <secondary>mongodb()</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>mongodb()</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-mongodb</emphasis> Enable the mongodb destination (enabled by default). The source of the MongoDB client is included in the source code package of &abbrev;. To use an external MongoDB client instead, use the <parameter>--with-libmongo-client=system</parameter> compiling option. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-mongodb"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>sources</primary>
                    <secondary>pacct()</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>pacct()</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-pacct</emphasis> Enable using the <parameter>pacct()</parameter> driver to collect process-accounting logs on Linux systems.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-pcre</emphasis> Enable using PCRE-type regular expressions. Requires the <parameter>libpcre</parameter> library package, <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/pcre/files/pcre/">available here</link>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-spoof-source</emphasis> Enable spoof_source feature (disabled by default).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>destinations</primary>
                    <secondary>sql()</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>sql()</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-sql</emphasis> Enables the sql() destination (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libdbi</parameter> library is installed and detected).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>ssl support</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-ssl</emphasis> Enable SSL support, required for encrypted message transfer, as well as template functions that calculate hashes and UUIDs (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libopenssl</parameter> library is detected).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-sun-door</emphasis> Enable Sun door support even if not detected (autodetected by default).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-sun-streams</emphasis> Enable Sun STREAMS support even if not detected (autodetected by default).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>systemd</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-systemd</emphasis> Enable systemd support on Linux platforms (autodetected by default) (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libsystemd-daemon</parameter> library is detected).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--enable-tcp-wrapper</emphasis> Enable using <emphasis>/etc/hosts.deny</emphasis> and <emphasis>/etc/hosts.allow</emphasis> for TCP access (enabled automatically if the <parameter>libwrap</parameter> libraries are detected).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--with-embedded-crypto</emphasis> If this option is set, the crypto library is linked directly into libsyslog-ng: the sources of libsyslog-ng-crypto will be appended to the libsyslog-ng sources, and -crypto is not built.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--with-ivykis</emphasis> Specifies which ivykis implementation to use (default value: internal). The source of ivykis is included in the source code package of &abbrev; and is used by default. To use an external implementation instead, use the <parameter>--with-ivykis=system</parameter> compiling option.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>destinations</primary>
                    <secondary>mongodb()</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>mongodb()</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--with-libmongo-client</emphasis> Specifies which MongoDB client to use (default value: internal). The source of the mongodb client is included in the source code package of &abbrev; and is used by default. To use an external MongoDB client instead, use the <parameter>--with-libmongo-client=system</parameter> compiling option. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-mongodb"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>destinations</primary>
                    <secondary>amqp()</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>amqp()</primary>
                    <secondary>compiling</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para><emphasis>--with-librabbitmq-client</emphasis> Specifies which RabbitMQ client to use (default value: internal). The source of the rabbitmq client is included in the source code package of &abbrev; and is used by default. To use an external client instead, use the <parameter>--with-librabbitmq-client=system</parameter> compiling option. For details on using this destination, see <xref linkend="configuring-destinations-amqp"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--with-module-dir</emphasis> Specifies a single directory where the &abbrev; Makefile will install the modules.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--with-module-path</emphasis> Specifies a colon-separated (:) list of directories, where the &abbrev; binary will search for modules.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--with-timezone-dir</emphasis> Specifies the directory where syslog-ng looks for the timezone files to resolve the <parameter>time_zone()</parameter> and <parameter>local_time_zone()</parameter> options. If not specified, the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/share/zoneinfo/</filename> and <filename>/usr/share/zoneinfo/</filename> directories are checked, respectively. Note that HP-UX uses a unique file format (<parameter>tztab</parameter>) to describe the timezone information; that format is currently not supported in syslog-ng. As a workaround, copy the zoneinfo files from another, non-HP-UX system to the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/share/zoneinfo/</filename> directory of your HP-UX system.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>--without-compile-date</emphasis> Removes the compilation date from the binary. For example, as openSUSE checks if recompilation changes the binary to detect if dependent packages need to be rebuilt or not, and including the date changes the binary every time.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </step>
</procedure>
