<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE procedure
 [  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../shared/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
 %entities;]>
<procedure xml:id="procedure-configuring-mutual-tls-client" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Configuring TLS on the syslog-ng clients</title>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Purpose:</title>
        <para/>
    </formalpara>
    <para>Complete the following steps on every syslog-ng client host. Examples are provided using both the legacy BSD-syslog protocol (using the <parameter>network()</parameter> driver) and the new IETF-syslog protocol standard (using the <parameter>syslog()</parameter> driver):</para>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Steps:</title>
        <para/>
    </formalpara>
    <step>
        <para>Create an X.509 certificate for the syslog-ng client.<!--The
                        <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter (or the <parameter>Common
                        Name</parameter> parameter if the <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter>
                    parameter is empty) must contain the hostname or the IP address (as resolved
                    from the syslog-ng clients and relays) of the client.--></para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Copy the certificate (for example <filename>client_cert.pem</filename>) and the matching private key (for example <filename>client.key</filename>) to the syslog-ng client host, for example into the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d</filename> directory. The certificate must be a valid X.509 certificate in PEM format. If you want to use a password-protected key, see <xref linkend="tls-password-protected-keys"/>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Copy the CA certificate of the Certificate Authority (for example <filename>cacert.pem</filename>) that issued the certificate of the syslog-ng server (or the self-signed certificate of the syslog-ng server) to the syslog-ng client hosts, for example into the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d</filename> directory.</para>
        <para>Issue the following command on the certificate: <command>openssl x509 -noout -hash -in cacert.pem</command> The result is a hash (for example <userinput>6d2962a8</userinput>), a series of alphanumeric characters based on the Distinguished Name of the certificate.</para>
        <para>Issue the following command to create a symbolic link to the certificate that uses the hash returned by the previous command and the <userinput>.0</userinput> suffix.</para>
        <para><command>ln -s cacert.pem 6d2962a8.0</command></para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Add a destination statement to the syslog-ng configuration file that uses the <userinput>tls( ca-dir(path_to_ca_directory) )</userinput> option and specify the directory using the CA certificate. The destination must use the <parameter>network()</parameter> or the <parameter>syslog()</parameter> destination driver, and the IP address and port parameters of the driver must point to the syslog-ng server. Include the client's certificate and private key in the <parameter>tls()</parameter> options.</para>
        <example>
            <title>A destination statement using mutual authentication</title>
            <para>The following destination encrypts the log messages using TLS and sends them to the <userinput>1999/TCP</userinput> port of the syslog-ng server having the <userinput>10.1.2.3</userinput> IP address. The private key and the certificate file authenticating the client is also specified.</para>
            <synopsis>destination demo_tls_destination {
    network("10.1.2.3" port(1999)
        transport("tls")
        tls( ca-dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d")
             key-file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/client.key")
             cert-file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/client_cert.pem")) ); };</synopsis>
            <synopsis>destination demo_tls_syslog_destination {
    syslog("10.1.2.3" port(1999)
        transport("tls")
            tls( ca-dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d")
                 key-file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/client.key")
                 cert-file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/client_cert.pem")) ); };</synopsis>
        </example>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Include the destination created in Step 2 in a log statement.</para>
        <warning>
            <para>The encrypted connection between the server and the client fails if the <parameter>Common Name</parameter> or the <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter of the server certificate does not the hostname or the IP address (as resolved from the syslog-ng clients and relays) of the server.</para>
            <para>Do not forget to update the certificate files when they expire.</para>
        </warning>
    </step>
</procedure>