<!DOCTYPE chapter
 [  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../shared/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
 %entities;]>
<procedure xml:id="procedure-configuring-mutual-tls-server" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Configuring TLS on the syslog-ng server</title>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Purpose:</title>
        <para/>
    </formalpara>
    <para>Complete the following steps on the syslog-ng server:</para>
    <formalpara>
        <title>Steps:</title>
        <para/>
    </formalpara>
    <step>
        <para>Copy the certificate (for example <filename>syslog-ng.cert</filename>) of the syslog-ng server to the syslog-ng server host, for example into the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d</filename> directory. The certificate must be a valid X.509 certificate in PEM format.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Copy the CA certificate (for example <filename>cacert.pem</filename>) of the Certificate Authority that issued the certificate of the syslog-ng clients to the syslog-ng server, for example into the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d</filename> directory.</para>
        <para>Issue the following command on the certificate: <command>openssl x509 -noout -hash -in cacert.pem</command> The result is a hash (for example <userinput>6d2962a8</userinput>), a series of alphanumeric characters based on the Distinguished Name of the certificate.</para>
        <para>Issue the following command to create a symbolic link to the certificate that uses the hash returned by the previous command and the <userinput>.0</userinput> suffix.</para>
        <para><command>ln -s cacert.pem 6d2962a8.0</command></para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Copy the private key (for example <filename>syslog-ng.key</filename>) matching the certificate of the syslog-ng server to the syslog-ng server host, for example into the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d</filename> directory. The key must be in PEM format. If you want to use a password-protected key, see <xref linkend="tls-password-protected-keys"/>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Add a source statement to the syslog-ng configuration file that uses the <userinput>tls( key-file(key_file_fullpathname) cert-file(cert_file_fullpathname) )</userinput> option and specify the key and certificate files. The source must use the source driver (<parameter>network()</parameter> or <parameter>syslog()</parameter>) matching the destination driver used by the syslog-ng client. Also specify the directory storing the certificate of the CA that issued the client's certificate.</para>
        <para>For the details of the available <parameter>tls()</parameter> options, see <xref linkend="tlsoptions"/>.</para>
        <example>
            <title>A source statement using TLS</title>
            <para>The following source receives log messages encrypted using TLS, arriving to the <userinput>1999/TCP</userinput> port of any interface of the syslog-ng server.</para>
            <synopsis>source demo_tls_source {
    network(ip(0.0.0.0) port(1999)
        transport("tls")
               tls( key-file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/syslog-ng.key")
                    cert-file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/syslog-ng.cert")
                    ca-dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d")) ); };</synopsis>
            <para>A similar source for receiving messages using the IETF-syslog protocol:</para>
            <synopsis>source demo_tls_syslog_source {
                        syslog(ip(0.0.0.0) port(1999)
                        transport("tls")
                        tls( key-file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/syslog-ng.key")
                        cert-file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/syslog-ng.cert")
                        ca-dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d")) ); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <warning>
<!--<para>The encrypted connection between the server and the client fails if the
                            <parameter>Common Name</parameter> or the
                        <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter of the client certificate
                        does not the hostname or the IP address (as resolved from the syslog-ng
                        clients and relays) of the server.</para>-->
            <para>Do not forget to update the certificate and key files when they expire.</para>
        </warning>
    </step>
</procedure>
