<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="so-contents" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Summary of contents</title>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-intro"/> describes the main functionality and purpose of &abbrev;.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-concepts"/> discusses the technical concepts and philosophies behind &abbrev;.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-install"/> describes how to install &abbrev; on various UNIX-based platforms using the precompiled binaries.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-quickstart"/> provides a briefly explains how to perform the most common log collecting tasks with &abbrev;.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-configuration-file"/> discusses the configuration file format and syntax in detail, and explains how to manage large-scale configurations using included files and reusable configuration snippets.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-sources"/> explains how to collect and receive log messages from various sources.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-destinations"/> describes the different methods to store and forward log messages.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-routing-filters"/> explains how to route and sort log messages, and how to use filters to select specific messages.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-global-options"/> lists the global options of &abbrev; and explains how to use them.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-encrypted-transport-tls"/> shows how to secure and authenticate log transport using TLS encryption.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-manipulating-messages"/> describes how to customize message format using templates and macros, how to rewrite and modify messages, and how to use regular expressions.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-parsers"/> describes how to segment and process structured messages like comma-separated values.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-patterndb"/> explains how to identify and process log messages using a pattern database.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-log-statistics"/> details the available statistics that &abbrev; collects about the processed log messages.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-multithreading"/> describes how to configure &abbrev; to use multiple processors, and how to optimize its performance.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-troubleshooting-syslog-ng"/> offers tips to solving problems.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="chapter-examples"/> gives recommendations to configure special features of &abbrev;.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="man-syslog-ng"/> contains the manual pages of the &abbrev; application.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="app-open-source-licenses"/> includes the open source licenses and attributions applicable to &product;.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="appendix-cc"/> includes the text of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-commercial No Derivatives (by-nc-nd) License applicable to The &product; &version; Administrator Guide.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="go01"/> defines the important terms used in this guide.</para>
    <para><xref linkend="syslog-ng-parameter-index"/> provides cross-references to the definitions of options, parameters, and macros available in &abbrev;.</para>
    <para>The <emphasis>Index</emphasis> provides cross-references to important terms used in this guide.</para>
</topic>
