<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE glossary
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../shared/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<glossary xml:id="go01" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <title>Glossary</title>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> alias IP </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An additional IP address assigned to an interface that already has an IP address. The normal and alias IP addresses both refer to the same physical interface.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> authentication </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The process of verifying the authenticity of a user or client before allowing access to a network system or service.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> auditing policy </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The auditing policy determines which events are logged on host running Microsoft Windows operating systems.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry xml:id="glossary-bom">
        <glossterm> BOM </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <xi:include href="../../shared/chunk/para-bom-definition.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> BSD-syslog protocol </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The old syslog protocol standard described in <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://tools.ietf.org/search/rfc3164">RFC 3164</link>. Sometimes also referred to as the legacy-syslog protocol.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> CA </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A Certificate Authority (CA) is an institute that issues certificates.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>certificate</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A certificate is a file that uniquely identifies its owner. Certificates contains information identifying the owner of the certificate, a public key itself, the expiration date of the certificate, the name of the CA that signed the certificate, and some other data.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> client mode </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>In client mode, syslog-ng collects the local logs generated by the host and forwards them through a network connection to the central syslog-ng server or to a relay.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> destination </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A named collection of configured destination drivers.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> destination driver </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A communication method used to send log messages.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> destination, network </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A destination that sends log messages to a remote host (that is, a syslog-ng relay or server) using a network connection.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> destination, local </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A destination that transfers log messages within the host, for example writes them to a file, or passes them to a log analyzing application.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry condition="pe">
        <glossterm> disk buffer </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Premium Edition of syslog-ng can store messages on the local hard disk if the central log server or the network connection to the server becomes unavailable.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> disk queue </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>See <emphasis>disk buffer</emphasis>.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> domain name </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The name of a network, for example: <parameter>balabit.com</parameter>.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> embedded log statement </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A log statement that is included in another log statement to create a complex log path.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> filter </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An expression to select messages.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> fully qualified domain name (FQDN) </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A domain name that specifies its exact location in the tree hierarchy of the Domain Name System (DNS). For example, given a device with a local hostname <userinput>myhost</userinput> and a parent domain name <userinput>example.com</userinput>, the fully qualified domain name is <userinput>myhost.example.com</userinput>.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> gateway </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A device that connects two or more parts of the network, for example: your local intranet and the external network (the Internet). Gateways act as entrances into other networks.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> high availability </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>High availability uses a second syslog-ng server unit to ensure that the logs are received even if the first unit breaks down.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> host </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A computer connected to the network.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> hostname </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A name that identifies a host on the network.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> IETF-syslog protocol </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The syslog-protocol standard developed by the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF), described in <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://tools.ietf.org/search/rfc5424">RFC 5424-5427</link>.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> key pair </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A private key and its related public key. The private key is known only to the owner, while the public key can be freely distributed. Information encrypted with the private key can only be decrypted using the public key.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry condition="pe">
        <glossterm> license </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The syslog-ng license determines the number of distinct hosts (clients and relays) that can connect to the syslog-ng server.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> log path </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A combination of sources, filters, parsers, rewrite rules, and destinations: syslog-ng examines all messages arriving to the sources of the logpath and sends the messages matching all filters to the defined destinations.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry condition="pe">
        <glossterm> logstore </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A binary logfile format that can encrypt, compress, and timestamp log messages.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry condition="pe">
        <glossterm> Long Term Supported release </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Long Term Supported releases are major releases of &abbrev; that are supported for three years after their original release.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> LSH </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>See <emphasis>log source host</emphasis>.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> log source host </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A host or network device (including syslog-ng clients and relays) that sends logs to the syslog-ng server. Log source hosts can be servers, routers, desktop computers, or other devices capable of sending syslog messages or running syslog-ng.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> log statement </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>See <emphasis>log path</emphasis>.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> name server </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A network computer storing the IP addresses corresponding to domain names.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Oracle Instant Client</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The Oracle Instant Client is a small set of libraries, which allow you to connect to an Oracle Database. A subset of the full Oracle Client, it requires minimal installation but has full functionality.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> output buffer </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A part of the memory of the host where syslog-ng stores outgoing log messages if the destination cannot accept the messages immediately.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> output queue </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Messages from the output queue are sent to the target syslog-ng server. The syslog-ng application puts the outgoing messages directly into the output queue, unless the output queue is full. The output queue can hold 64 messages, this is a fixed value and cannot be modified.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> overflow queue </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>See <emphasis>output buffer</emphasis>.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> parser </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A set of rules to segment messages into named fields or columns.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> ping </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A command that sends a message from a host to another host over a network to test connectivity and packet loss.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> port </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A number ranging from 1 to 65535 that identifies the destination application of the transmitted data. For example: SSH commonly uses port 22, web servers (HTTP) use port 80, and so on.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> Public-key authentication </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>An authentication method that uses encryption key pairs to verify the identity of a user or a client.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> regular expression </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A regular expression is a string that describes or matches a set of strings.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> relay mode </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>In relay mode, syslog-ng receives logs through the network from syslog-ng clients and forwards them to the central syslog-ng server using a network connection.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> rewrite rule </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A set of rules to modify selected elements of a log message.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> template </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A user-defined structure that can be used to restructure log messages or automatically generate file names.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> server mode </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>In server mode, syslog-ng acts as a central log-collecting server. It receives messages from syslog-ng clients and relays over the network, and stores them locally in files, or passes them to other applications, for example, log analyzers.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> source </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A named collection of configured source drivers.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> source, network </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A source that receives log messages from a remote host using a network connection, for example, <parameter>network()</parameter>, <parameter>syslog()</parameter>.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> source, local </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A source that receives log messages from within the host, for example, from a file.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> source driver </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A communication method used to receive log messages.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> SSL </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>See <emphasis>TLS</emphasis>.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> syslog-ng </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The syslog-ng application is a flexible and highly scalable system logging application, typically used to manage log messages and implement centralized logging.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> syslog-ng agent </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The syslog-ng Agent for Windows is a commercial log collector and forwarder application for the Microsoft Windows platform. It collects the log messages of the Windows-based host and forwards them to a syslog-ng server using regular or SSL-encrypted TCP connections.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> syslog-ng client </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A host running syslog-ng in client mode.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> syslog-ng Premium Edition</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>The syslog-ng Premium Edition is the commercial version of the open-source application. It offers additional features, like encrypted message transfer and an agent for Microsoft Windows platforms.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> syslog-ng relay </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A host running syslog-ng in relay mode.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> syslog-ng server </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A host running syslog-ng in server mode.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> TLS </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>Transport Layer Security (TLS) and its predecessor, Secure Sockets Layer (SSL), are cryptographic protocols which provide secure communications on the Internet. The &product; application can encrypt the communication between the clients and the server using TLS to prevent unauthorized access to sensitive log messages.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> traceroute </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A command that shows all routing steps (the path of a message) between two hosts.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
    <glossentry>
        <glossterm> UNIX domain socket </glossterm>
        <glossdef>
            <para>A UNIX domain socket (UDS) or IPC socket (inter-procedure call socket) is a virtual socket, used for inter-process communication.</para>
        </glossdef>
    </glossentry>
<!--  -->
</glossary>
