<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
 "/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
  [<!ENTITY logo "http://share.balabit/tt/images/logos">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-admin-guide/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;
  ]
 >
<article id="syslog-ng-guide-whatsnew">
        <articleinfo>
                <title>What is new in &product; &version;</title>
                <corpname>&fullvendor;</corpname>
                <keywordset>
                        <keyword>&product;, &abbrev;, SSH, RDP, VNC, Telnet, Citrix ICA, 4-eyes, audit,
                                record</keyword>
                </keywordset>
                <subjectset>
                        <subject>
                                <subjectterm>&product; &version; features</subjectterm>
                        </subject>
                </subjectset>
                <copyright>
                        <year>2000-2011</year>
                        <holder>&fullvendor;</holder>
                </copyright>
                <edition>First</edition>
                <pubdate>January 18, 2011</pubdate>
                <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                                <imagedata format="GIF" fileref="bb_star.gif"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                                <imagedata format="GIF" fileref="&logo;/bb_star.gif" contentwidth="7cm"/>
                        </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
        </articleinfo>
        <section id="preface">
                <title>Preface</title>
                <para>Welcome to &product; (&abbrev;) version &version; and thank you
                        for choosing our product. This document describes the new features and most
                        important changes since the latest release of &abbrev;. The main aim of
                        this paper is to aid system administrators in planning the migration to the
                        new version of &abbrev;. The following sections describe the news and
                        highlights of &abbrev; &version;.</para>
                <para>This document covers the &product; &version; product. </para>
                <para>As of October 2009 &vendor; has introduced the following support policy:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                                <para>Stable versions, denoted by a two-digit version number ending
                                        with .0 (for example 2.0 or 3.0): Stable branches are supported
                                        for at least 1 year, but no more than 2 stable versions of a
                                        product are supported at a time. Maintenance releases to the
                                        stable branch will contain only bugfixes.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                                <para>Feature versions, denoted by two-digit version number ending
                                        with a non-zero version number (for example 3.1, 3.2 and onwards):
                                        Feature branches will contain enhancements and new features,
                                        presumably 1-3 new feature per release. Only the last of the
                                        feature releases is supported (for example when a new feature
                                        release comes out, the last one becomes unsupported), and
                                        the last feature release becomes the new stable
                                release.</para>
                        </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <note>
                        <para>Releases of the feature branch are tested just like the stable
                                releases; they are not "unstable" development snapshots. The
                                difference between earlier major releases and current feature
                                releases is the smaller number of features contained in a release,
                                and the shorter support periods. If an unstable snapshot or
                                alpha/beta/rc release will be released for public testing, it will
                                be always marked explicitly as such.</para>
                </note>
                <warning>
                        <para>Downgrading from a feature release to an earlier (and thus
                                unsupported) feature release, or to the stable release is not
                                supported: this means that once you upgrade a system from a stable
                                release (for example 1.0) to a feature release (for example 1.1), you will have
                                to keep upgrading to the new feature releases until the next stable
                                version release (for example 2.0) is published, or risk using an
                                unsupported product.</para>
                </warning>
        </section>
        <section id="new-protocols">
                <title>New protocols</title>
                <para>&abbrev; supports the following new protocols and protocol-features.</para>
                <section>
                        <title>Terminal Services Gateway Server Protocol</title>
                        <para>&abbrev; &version; supports the Terminal Services Gateway Server Protocol, so &abbrev; can act as a Terminal Services Gateway (also called Remote Desktop Gateway).</para>
                        <para>Terminal Services Gateway (TS Gateway) is a role service in the Terminal Services server role that allows authorized remote users to connect to resources located on an internal or private network from any Internet-connected device. The accessible resources can be terminal servers, remote applications, remote desktops, and so on.</para>
                        <para>The Terminal Services Gateway Server Protocol is a remote procedure call (RPC) protocol using HTTPS as the transport mechanism, used primarily for tunneling client to server traffic across firewalls. The &product; can act as a Terminal Server Gateway, receiving connections using the Terminal Services Gateway Server Protocol and transferring them to the target servers using the RDP protocol.</para>
                        <para>The Terminal Services Gateway Server Protocol enables inband destination selection, meaning that &abbrev; can extract the address of the target server from the client connections. This greatly simplifies managing connections on &abbrev; without having to encode the name of the target server in the username, which was problematic as the length of the username is limited on many platforms &mdash; especially in Bastion mode.</para>
                </section>
                <section>
                        <title>Citrix ICA</title>
                        <para>&abbrev; &version; supports the Citrix ICA protocols. Reliable connections also known as Common Gateway Protocol (CGP) are also supported.</para>
                        <para>&abbrev; can also act as a SOCKS proxy to permit inband destination selection and the use of connection brokers.</para>
                        <para>Access to complete remote desktops and seamless connections to access only specific applications is supported as well.</para>
                </section>
        </section>
        <section id="general">
                <title>General improvements and changes</title>
                <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Starting with version 3.1, a 64-bit operating system is used to power &abbrev; in order to expose the capabilities of the underlying hardware to the fullest.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>The firmware upgrade process has been streamlined and made more robust. For details on how to upgrade your &abbrev; to version &version;, see <olink targetdoc="scb-guide-upgrade"/>.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>Unconfigured &abbrev; systems (if the Welcome Wizard has not been completed yet) attempt to request an IP address via DHCP from the local DHCP server. If this fails, &abbrev; starts listening for connections on the 192.168.1.1 IP address.</para>
                        </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section id="bap">
                <title>The &bap;</title>
                <para>This section describes the main changes of the &bap; application.</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                                <para>&bapabbrev; can process and replay the audit trails of Citrix ICA connections.</para>
                        </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
        </section>
</article>
