<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">context-id</emphasis>: OPTIONAL &mdash; An identifier to group related log messages when using the pattern database to correlate events. The ID can be a descriptive string describing the events related to the log message (for example, <userinput>ssh-sessions</userinput> for log messages related to SSH traffic), but can also contain macros to generate IDs dynamically. When using macros in IDs, see also the <parameter>context-scope</parameter> attribute. Starting with &abbrev; version <phrase condition="ose">3.5</phrase>, if a message is added to a context, &abbrev; automatically adds the identifier of the context to the <parameter>.classifier.context_id</parameter> macro of the message. For details on correlating messages, see <xref linkend="patterndb-correlation"/>.</para>
        <note>
            <para>The &abbrev; application determines the context of the message <emphasis>after</emphasis> the pattern matching is completed. This means that macros and name-value pairs created by the matching pattern database rule can be used as context-id macros.</para>
        </note>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">context-timeout</emphasis>: OPTIONAL &mdash; The number of seconds the context is stored. Note that for high-traffic log servers, storing open contexts for long time can require significant amount of memory. For details on correlating messages, see <xref linkend="patterndb-correlation"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">context-scope</emphasis>: OPTIONAL &mdash; Specifies which messages belong to the same context. This attribute is used to determine the context of the message if the <parameter>context-id</parameter> does not specify any macros. Usually, <parameter>context-scope</parameter> acts a filter for the context, with <parameter>context-id</parameter> refining the filtering if needed. The following values are available:</para>
        <xi:include href="correlation-context-scope.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
        <note>
            <para>Using the <parameter>context-scope</parameter> attribute is significantly faster than using macros in the <parameter>context-id</parameter> attribute.</para>
        </note>
        <para>For details on correlating messages, see <xref linkend="patterndb-correlation"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
</topic>
