<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <table xml:id="logflags">
        <title>Log statement flags</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>log paths</primary>
            <secondary>flags</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>flags</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm type="parameter">
            <primary>flags</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="60pt"/>
            <thead>
                <row>
                    <entry>Flag</entry>
                    <entry>Description</entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>catchall <indexterm type="parameter">
                            <primary>catchall</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>This flag means that the source of the message is ignored, only the filters of the log path are taken into account when matching messages. A log statement using the <parameter>catchall</parameter> flag processes every message that arrives to any of the defined sources.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>drop-unmatched <indexterm type="parameter">
                            <primary>drop-unmatched</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>This flag means that the message is dropped along a log path when it does not match a filter or is discarded by a parser. Without using the <parameter>drop-unmatched</parameter> flag, &abbrev; would continue to process the message along alternative paths.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>fallback <indexterm type="parameter">
                            <primary>fallback</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </entry>
<!-- FIXME figure/illustration/flow charts needed -->
                    <entry>
                        <para>This flag makes a log statement 'fallback'. Fallback log statements process messages that were not processed by other, 'non-fallback' log statements.</para>
                        <xi:include href="../../shared/chunk/para-flags-processed.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
                    </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>final <indexterm type="parameter">
                            <primary>final</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                        <para>This flag means that the processing of log messages processed by the log statement ends here, other log statements appearing later in the configuration file will not process the messages processed by the log statement labeled as 'final'. Note that this does not necessarily mean that matching messages will be stored only once, as there can be matching log statements processed before the current one (&abbrev; evaluates log statements in the order they appear in the configuration file).</para>
                        <xi:include href="../../shared/chunk/para-flags-processed.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
                    </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <entry>flow-control <indexterm type="parameter">
                            <primary>flow-control</primary>
                        </indexterm>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>Enables flow-control to the log path, meaning that syslog-ng will stop reading messages from the sources of this log statement if the destinations are not able to process the messages at the required speed. If disabled, syslog-ng will drop messages if the destination queues are full. If enabled, syslog-ng will only drop messages if the destination queues/window sizes are improperly sized. For details, see <xref linkend="concepts-flow-control"/>.</entry>
                </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table>
</topic>
