<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  [<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;
  ]
 >
<section xml:id="new-in-syslog-ng-pe-7.0.4" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Highlights of 7.0.4</title>
    <simplesect>
        <title>RHEL6 support</title>
        <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6 platform is now supported. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="supported-platforms"/>.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>New osquery source</title>
        <para>The <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://osquery.io">osquery</link> application allows you to ask questions about your machine using an SQL-like language. For example, you can query running processes, logged in users, installed packages and syslog messages as well. You can make queries on demand, and also schedule them to run regularly.</para>
        <para>The <parameter>osquery()</parameter> source of &abbrev; allows you read the results of periodical osquery queries and automatically parse the messages. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="syslog-ng-source-osquery"/>.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>New HTTP destination</title>
        <para>The &abbrev; application can directly post log messages to web services using the HTTP protocol, without having to use Java.</para>
        <para>HTTPS connection, as well as password- and certificate-based authentication is supported. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="configuring-destinations-http-nonjava"/>.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Look up GeoIP2 data from IP addresses</title>
        <para>The &abbrev; application can lookup IP addresses from an offline GeoIP2 database, and make the retrieved data available in name-value pairs. Depending on the database used, you can access country code, longitude, and latitude information, and many more in addition to what you could access with <parameter>geoip()</parameter>. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="geoip2-parser"/>.</para>
        <para>You can use the <parameter>geoip2</parameter> template function to format messages to contain GeoIP data. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="template-function-geoip2"/>.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>The geoip() parser is deprecated.</title>
        <para>The <parameter>geoip()</parameter> parser is now deprecated. Use the <parameter>geoip2</parameter> parser instead.</para>
    </simplesect>
</section>
