<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../shared/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;
  ]
 >
<section xml:id="new-in-syslog-ng-pe-7.0.2" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Highlights of 7.0.2</title>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Python support: message parsers and template functions</title>
        <para>The Python Log Parser allows you to write your own parser in Python. Practically, that way you can process the log message (or parts of the log message) any way you need. For example, you can import external Python modules to process the messages, query databases to enrich the messages with additional data, and many other things. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="python-parser"/>.</para>
        <para>You can write your own template function in Python. You can define a Python block in your &abbrev; configuration file, and define one or more Python functions in it. You can use these functions as template functions. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="template-function-python"/>.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Monitor &abbrev; more effectively</title>
        <para>The new <parameter>monitoring()</parameter> source allows you to granularly select which statistics of &abbrev; you want to monitor. In addition, the statistics are available as structured name-value pairs, so you can format the output similarly to other log messages. That way, you can easily convert the statistics and metrics, for example, into JSON or WELF format, and send the results into your monitoring database. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="monitor-syslog-ng-statistics-metrics"/>.</para>
        <para>&abbrev; version 7.0.2 also includes the <parameter>monitoring-welf()</parameter> source, which is a preconfigured <parameter>monitoring()</parameter> source that generates statistics messages in WELF format. Starting with version 7.0., &abbrev; uses this driver for new installations to generate statistics (earlier versions use the <parameter>internal()</parameter> source for this purpose).</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Ported from the &abbrev; 6 LTS product line</title>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The functionality of <command>syslog-ng-query</command> application is available in &abbrev; 7.0.2, as part of the <command>syslog-ng-ctl</command> utility. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="syslog-ng-ctl-query"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
</section>
