<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  [<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;
  ]
 >
<section xml:id="new-in-syslog-ng-pe-7.0.5" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Highlights of 7.0.5</title>
    <simplesect>
        <title>XML parser</title>
        <para>A new parser, the XML parser has been added, which processes input in XML format, and then adds the parsed data to the message object. Use this parser to interoperate with applications that produce XML-encoded log messages.</para>
        <para>The XML parser allows you to extract information from XML logs, and use this information in your logging pipeline, for example, in filters, and also to further process the extracted data using syslog-ng or other tools. In addition, parsing XML logs helps you normalize your log messages, and convert them to a common format.</para>
        <para>For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="xml-parser"/>.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Cisco parser</title>
        <para>A new parser, the Cisco parser has been added, which is capable of parsing the log messages of various Cisco devices. The messages of these devices often do not completely comply with the syslog RFCs, making them difficult to parse. The <parameter>cisco-parser()</parameter> of &abbrev; solves this problem, and can separate these log messages to name-value pairs, extracting also the Cisco-specific values.</para>
        <para>For more information, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="cisco-parser"/>.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>New <parameter>systemd-journal()</parameter> source option</title>
        <para>A new <parameter>systemd-journal()</parameter> source option, <parameter>read-old-records()</parameter>, has been added. Previously, &abbrev; started reading records from the journald system service right from the very beginning of the journal. This was often a lengthy process. The new option lets you specify whether you want to read only new records from the journal or all records, starting from the beginning of the journal.</para>
        <para>For more information, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="systemd-journal-options-read-old-records"/>.</para>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Configurable JVM options for Java destinations</title>
        <para>You can now fine-tune your Java Virtual Machine (JVM) options when configuring Elasticsearch, Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS), and Apache Kafka destinations. Previously, settings of the Java Virtual Machine could not be overriden from the &abbrev; configuration file, resulting sometimes in suboptimal memory utilization. The new <parameter>jvm-options()</parameter> allows you to configure these Java settings from &abbrev; as a global option.</para>
        <para>For details, see:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="reference-destination-elasticsearch"/></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="reference-destination-elasticsearch2"/></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="reference-destination-hdfs"/></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="reference-destination-kafka"/></para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="reference-options"/></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Changes in HDFS destination options</title>
        <para>The following changes have been introduced with regards to HDFS files:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">New option <parameter>hdfs-append-enabled()</parameter>:</emphasis> A new option has been added, which enables &abbrev; to append new data to the end of an already existing HDFS file. This means that, when setting this parameter to <userinput>true</userinput>, there is no need anymore to open a new file once a file has been closed.</para>
                <para>For further details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="option-hdfs-append-enabled"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Support for macros in file names and file paths:</emphasis>
                    <parameter>hdfs-file()</parameter> now supports the usage of macros, meaning that &abbrev; can create files on HDFS dynamically, using macros in the file (or directory) name.</para>
                <para>For further details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="hdfs-option-hdfs-file"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>New TLS options</title>
        <para>The following new TLS options have been added:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><parameter>dhparam-file()</parameter>: Allows you to specify a file that contains the Diffie-Hellman parameters for key exchanges, generated by the <parameter>openssl dhparam</parameter> utility. </para>
                <para>For further information, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="tls-options-dhparam-file"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><parameter>ecdh-curve-list()</parameter>: Allows you to specify the curves permitted when using Elliptic Curve Cryptography (ECC).</para>
                <para>For further information, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="tls-options-ecdh-curve-list"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </simplesect>
    <simplesect>
        <title>Oracle Linux 6 platform now supported in &abbrev;</title>
        <para>The Oracle Linux 6 platform is now supported in &abbrev;.</para>
        <para>For a complete list of supported platforms, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="supported-platforms"/>.</para>
    </simplesect>
</section>
