<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  [<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;
  ]
 >
<article xml:id="syslog-ng-pe-guide-whatsnew" xml:lang="en-EN" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>What is new in &product; &version;</title>
        <orgname>&vendor;</orgname>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>syslog-ng, &product;, &abbrev;, logging, log collection, syslog-ng documentation, syslog-ng configuration, syslog-ng manual, system logging, eventlog collection, central log server, log management, &docgithash;</keyword>
        </keywordset>
        <subjectset>
            <subject>
                <subjectterm>&product; &version; features</subjectterm>
            </subject>
        </subjectset>
        <xi:include href="../xml-stylesheet/common/common.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xpointer="common_copyright_bb"/>
        <pubdate>
<?dbtimestamp?>
        </pubdate>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../xml-stylesheet/common/common.xml" xpointer="common_logo_bb"/>
    </info>
    <section xml:id="preface">
        <title>Preface</title>
        <para>Welcome to &product; (&abbrev;) version &version; and thank you for choosing our product. This document describes the new features and most important changes since the latest release of &abbrev;. The main aim of this paper is to aid system administrators in planning the migration to the new version of &abbrev;. The following sections describe the news and highlights of &abbrev; &version;.</para>
        <para>This document covers the &version; feature release of the &product; product.</para>
        <para>The following release policy applies to &product;:</para>

        <xi:include href="../common/version-policy.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="new-in-syslog-ng-pe-6-lts">
        <title>Changes since &abbrev; 5 F6</title>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Parsing <userinput>key=value</userinput> pairs</title>
            <para>The &abbrev; application can separate a message consisting of whitespace or comma-separated <userinput>key=value</userinput> pairs (for example, Postfix log messages) into name-value pairs. You can also specify other separator character instead of the equal sign, for example, colon (<userinput>:</userinput>) to parse MySQL log messages. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="key-value-parser"/>.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Updated TLS ciphers, new parameters</title>
            <para>The OpenSSL application used in &abbrev; has been updated to version 1.0.2, so you can use new, stronger ciphers to protect the communication between your &abbrev; clients and servers. For an updated list of supported ciphers, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="tls-option-cipher-suite"/>.</para>
            <para>Also, you can now specify the curves that are permitted in the connection using the <parameter>list-curves()</parameter> option, and also import Diffie-Hellman parameters from a file using the <parameter>dhparam-file()</parameter> option. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="tlsoptions"/>.</para>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Other changes</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Starting from version 6 LTS, the &abbrev; installer packages (earlier called <userinput>client</userinput> and <userinput>server</userinput> package) are renamed. From now on, the package with the <filename>compact</filename> suffix does not include SQL support. If you do not use the <parameter>sql()</parameter> source or destination on the host, use the <filename>compact</filename> binaries. That way no unnecessary components are installed to your system. Earlier, the names of packages containing <parameter>sql()</parameter> support included the <filename>server</filename> suffix, this suffix has been removed from the package names.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Changes in &agent;</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The graphical interface of the &agent; application now supports version 4.0 of the Microsoft .NET Framework.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Group Policies can be configured directly from the &agent; interface.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When creating a filter based on Event Source names, the Windows Agent interface displayed a list of possible sources. However, the names of this list did not always match the actual name of the Event Source (as displayed in the Event Viewer). From now on, the Windows Agent does not list the possible Event Source names. To create a filter using Event Source names, first find the "Source:" field as shown on the General tab of the Event Viewer, and enter its value in the filter.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Platform changes in &abbrev; 7.0</title>
            <formalpara>
                <title>New platforms in &abbrev; 6 LTS:</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Platforms not supported in &abbrev; 6 LTS:</title>
                <para/>
            </formalpara>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>For a complete list of supported platforms, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="supported-platforms"/>.</para>
        </simplesect>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="new-in-syslog-ng-pe-7">
        <title>Changes between &abbrev; 6 LTS and 7.0</title>

    </section>
</article>
