<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  [<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;
  ]
 >
<article xml:id="syslog-ng-pe-guide-whatsnew" xml:lang="en-EN" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>What is new in &product; &version;</title>
        <orgname>&vendor;</orgname>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>syslog-ng, &product;, &abbrev;, logging, log collection, syslog-ng documentation, syslog-ng configuration, syslog-ng manual, system logging, eventlog collection, central log server, log management, &docgithash;</keyword>
        </keywordset>
        <subjectset>
                <subject>
                        <subjectterm>&product; &version; features</subjectterm>
                </subject>
        </subjectset>
        <xi:include href="../xml-stylesheet/common/common.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xpointer="common_copyright_bb"/>
        <pubdate><?dbtimestamp?></pubdate>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../xml-stylesheet/common/common.xml" xpointer="common_logo_bb"/>
    </info>
    <section xml:id="preface">
        <title>Preface</title>
        <para>Welcome to &product; (&abbrev;) version &version; and thank you for choosing our product. This document describes the new features and most important changes since the latest release of &abbrev;. The main aim of this paper is to aid system administrators in planning the migration to the new version of &abbrev;. The following sections describe the news and highlights of &abbrev; &version;.</para>
        <para>This document covers the &version; feature release of the &product; product. </para>
        <para>As of June 2011, the following release policy applies to &product;:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Long Term Supported or LTS releases</emphasis> (for example, &abbrev; 4 LTS) are supported for 3 years after their original publication date and for 1 year after the next LTS release is published (whichever date is later). The second digit of the revisions of such releases is 0 (for example, &abbrev; 4.0.1). Maintenance releases to LTS releases contain only bugfixes and security updates.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Feature releases</emphasis> (for example, &abbrev; 4 F1) are supported for 6 months after their original publication date and for 2 months after succeeding Feature or LTS Release is published (whichever date is later). Feature releases contain enhancements and new features, presumably 1-3 new feature per release. Only the last of the feature releases is supported (for example when a new feature release comes out, the last one becomes unsupported).</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <warning>
            <para>Downgrading from a feature release to an earlier (and thus unsupported) feature release, or to the previous LTS release is officially not supported, but usually works as long as your &abbrev; configuration file is appropriate for the old &abbrev; version. However, persistent data like the position of the last processed message in a file source will be probably lost.</para>
            <para>Logstore files created with a newer version of &abbrev; might not be readable with an older version of &abbrev;.</para>
        </warning>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Reading messages from the systemd journal</title>
        <para>The systemd journal is a new type of system log storage. This is used, or will be used on most Linux distributions, such as RHEL (from RHEL7), Fedora, CentOS, and so on. The journal can store name-value pairs instead of the traditional system log entries. &abbrev; &version; can directly read log messages from the journal file of platforms using systemd. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="configuring-sources-journal"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Sending e-mail alerts</title>
        <para>An important aspect of logging is alerting on important but rare events. A common way to do that is via e-mail, sent either to people or to services which process them further. The SMTP destination driver allows you to send e-mails based on incoming log messages to one or more addresses. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="configuring-destinations-smtp"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Rewriting multiple macros</title>
        <para>Using the <userinput>groupset</userinput> rewrite rule, you can rewrite multiple macros at the same time, making it easy to modify the values of fields parsed using patterndb or from JSON. You can specify the list of macros manually, or also as a glob pattern. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="rewrite-groupset"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Comparing macro values to a list</title>
        <para>The &abbrev; application can compare the value of a macro to a list of strings. Earlier, if a specific macro had several different values, filtering on the macro values required several filter statements. Now you can specify every expected value in a file, and use the contents of that file in a filter. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="rewrite-groupset"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Creating hashes from macro values</title>
        <para>With the <userinput>hash</userinput> template function, you can create message digests from parts of the log message. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="template-function-hash"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Adding a unique ID to log messages</title>
        <para>HOSTID is a 32-bit number generated by a cryptographically secure pseudorandom number generator. Its purpose is to identify the &abbrev; host, thus it is the same for every message of the host. It can be accessed via the $HOSTID macro (which cannot be rewritten).</para>
        <para>When the global option <userinput>use-uniqid(yes)</userinput> is set, &abbrev; generates this practically unique id for every received or locally generated message. You can add this ID to your messages using the $UNIQID macro. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="global-use-uniqueid"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Support for new platforms</title>
        <para>Version 5 F2 of &pe; supports the following new platforms:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>CentOS 7</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 7 (RHEL 7)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ubuntu 14.04 LTS (Trusy Tahr)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For a complete list of supported platforms, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="supported-platforms"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
		<title>Other changes</title>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>The syslog-ng Agent on Windows application now searches for CA certificates also in the Intermediate Certification Authorities Store.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>So far, the largest message &abbrev; could handle was 64kbyte, because internally &abbrev; represented the messages in a 16-bit nvtable. From now on, &abbrev; uses a 32-bit nvtable, allowing you to receive and manipulate messages much larger than 64kbyte.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</article>
