<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  [<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;
  ]
 >
<article xml:id="syslog-ng-pe-guide-whatsnew" xml:lang="en-EN" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>What is new in &product; &version;</title>
        <orgname>&vendor;</orgname>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>syslog-ng, &product;, &abbrev;, logging, log collection, syslog-ng documentation, syslog-ng configuration, syslog-ng manual, system logging, eventlog collection, central log server, log management, &docgithash;</keyword>
        </keywordset>
        <subjectset>
            <subject>
                <subjectterm>&product; &version; features</subjectterm>
            </subject>
        </subjectset>
        <xi:include href="../xml-stylesheet/common/common.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xpointer="common_copyright_bb"/>
        <pubdate>
<?dbtimestamp?>
        </pubdate>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../xml-stylesheet/common/common.xml" xpointer="common_logo_bb"/>
    </info>
    <section xml:id="preface">
        <title>Preface</title>
        <para>Welcome to &product; (&abbrev;) version &version; and thank you for choosing our product. This document describes the new features and most important changes since the latest release of &abbrev;. The main aim of this paper is to aid system administrators in planning the migration to the new version of &abbrev;. The following sections describe the news and highlights of &abbrev; &version;.</para>
        <para>This document covers the &version; feature release of the &product; product.</para>
        <para>As of June 2011, the following release policy applies to &product;:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Long Term Supported or LTS releases</emphasis> (for example, &abbrev; 4 LTS) are supported for 3 years after their original publication date and for 1 year after the next LTS release is published (whichever date is later). The second digit of the revisions of such releases is 0 (for example, &abbrev; 4.0.1). Maintenance releases to LTS releases contain only bugfixes and security updates.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Feature releases</emphasis> (for example, &abbrev; 4 F1) are supported for 6 months after their original publication date and for 2 months after succeeding Feature or LTS Release is published (whichever date is later). Feature releases contain enhancements and new features, presumably 1-3 new feature per release. Only the last of the feature releases is supported (for example when a new feature release comes out, the last one becomes unsupported).</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <warning>
            <para>Downgrading from a feature release to an earlier (and thus unsupported) feature release, or to the previous LTS release is officially not supported, but usually works as long as your &abbrev; configuration file is appropriate for the old &abbrev; version. However, persistent data like the position of the last processed message in a file source will be probably lost.</para>
            <para>Logstore files created with a newer version of &abbrev; might not be readable with an older version of &abbrev;.</para>
        </warning>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Storing messages in MongoDB database</title>
        <para>MongoDB is a schema-free, document-oriented database, ideal to collect log messages. Since it does not require a predetermined schema, it gives you much more flexibility than the SQL databases, making it it easy to store name-value pairs extracted from log messages. That way, you can conveniently store metadata received in a log message (for example, in the SDATA part of RFC5424-formatted log messages), or other data parsed from the body of the log messages (for example, usernames parsed from login/logout messages). For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="configuring-destinations-mongodb"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Selecting and using name-value pairs</title>
        <para>The &abbrev; application allows you to select and construct name-value pairs from any information already available about the log message, or extracted from the message itself. You can directly use this structured information, for example, in the following places:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><parameter>mongodb()</parameter> destination (for details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="configuring-destinations-mongodb"/>)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem condition="pe">
                <para><parameter>format-welf()</parameter> template function (for details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="template-function-format-welf"/>)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>or in other destinations using the <parameter>format-json()</parameter> template function (for details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="template-function-format-json"/>).</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For details about value-pairs, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="concepts-value-pairs"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Parsing JSON messages</title>
        <para>JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) is a text-based open standard designed for human-readable data interchange. It is used primarily to transmit data between a server and web application, serving as an alternative to XML. The &abbrev; application can separate parts of JSON-encoded log messages to name-value pairs, allowing you to receive structured log messages from such applications, store them, and convert them to other format if needed. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="json-parser"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Converting messages into JSON format</title>
        <para>The &abbrev; application can convert messages or selected value-pairs into JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) format. Including the template function in a message template allows you to store selected information about a log message (that is, its content, macros, or other metadata) in JSON format, or to forward JSON messages to external applications. For details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="template-function-format-json"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Support for new platforms</title>
        <para>Version 5 F1 of &pe; supports the following new platforms:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Debian 7 (wheezy)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>FreeBSD 9</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Oracle Linux 5 and 6</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Solaris 11</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ubuntu 12.04 LTS (Precise Pangolin)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For a complete list of supported platforms, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="supported-platforms"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Unsupported platforms</title>
        <para>Starting with &pe; version 5 F1, the following platforms are not officially supported:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>AIX 5.2 and 5.3</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Debian 3.1 (sarge) and Debian 4.0 (etch)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>FreeBSD 6 and 7</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>HP-UX 11i</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Microsoft Windows XP</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>openSUSE 10.1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Red Hat Enterprise Linux 2 and 3</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>SLES 10 and SLES 10 SP1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Solaris 8</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Tru64</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Ubuntu 8.04 LTS (Hardy Heron)</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For a complete list of supported platforms, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="supported-platforms"/>.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="webhelp-format">
        <title>New documentation format</title>
        <para>The multi-page HTML documentation of &pe; 5 F1 uses a new format:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The Contents is visible on every page, making it easier to navigate the documents.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>You can search the entire document using the Search tab on the sidepane, making it easier and faster to find what you are looking for.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Code examples are syntax-highlighted.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Every page has a download link to the PDF format of the document.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>You can comment on every page to provide us feedback, ask questions about the documentation, or get in touch with us with your &product; related questions.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <figure>
            <title>The new documentation format</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="webhelp.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata format="PNG" align="center" fileref="&imgroot;/webhelp.png" contentwidth="&screenshotsize;"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </section>
</article>
