<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<section xml:id="intro_tutorial_auth" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Collecting log messages is an essential part of managing, maintaining, and troubleshooting IT systems. Since your log messages can contain all kinds of sensitive information, you should make sure that they are kept safe. The easiest way to protect the log messages as they are transferred from your clients to your logserver is to authenticate and encrypt the connection between the client and the server.</para>
    <para>This tutorial shows you step-by-step how to create the certificates required to authenticate your server and your clients, and how to configure &product; (&abbrev;) to send your log messages in an encrypted connection. Installing &abbrev; is not covered, <phrase condition="ose">but <link xmlns:ns1="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ns1:href="https://syslog-ng.org/3rd-party-binaries/">downloading it</link> for your platform and installing it should be easy</phrase><phrase condition="pe">for details, see <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="chapter-install"/></phrase>.</para>
    <para>The tutorial is organized as follows:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para><xref linkend="mutual-authentication-certificates"/> describes how to create the required certificates to encrypt and authenticate the connection between your logserver and your clients. Actually, you can use this part of the tutorial even if you do not use &abbrev;, as it is independent from the logging application you use.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><xref linkend="mutual-authentication-syslog-ng"/> describes how to configure &abbrev; on your clients and your logserver.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para><xref linkend="mutual-authentication-test"/> gives you tips on how to test your configuration to make sure it is really working.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</section>
