<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xml-stylesheet/pdf/dtd/docbookx.dtd"
[  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;]> 
<chapter id="chapter_intro">
	<title>Introduction to syslog-ng</title>
	<para>This chapter introduces the &product; application in a non-technical
		manner, discussing how and why is it useful, and the benefits it offers to an existing IT
		infrastructure. </para>
	<section>
		<title>What syslog-ng is</title>
		<para>The syslog-ng application is a flexible and highly scalable system logging application
			that is ideal for creating centralized and trusted logging solutions. The main features
			of syslog-ng are summarized below.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Reliable log transfer</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application enables
					you to send the log messages of your hosts to remote servers using the latest
					protocol standards. The logs of different servers can be collected and stored
					centrally on dedicated log servers. Transferring log messages using the TCP
					protocol ensures that no messages are lost.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Secure logging using TLS</emphasis>: Log messages may contain
					sensitive information that should not be accessed by third parties. Therefore,
					syslog-ng uses the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol to
					encrypt the communication. TLS also allows the mutual authentication of the host
					and the server using X.509 certificates.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Direct database access</emphasis>: Storing your log messages in a
					database allows you to easily search and query the messages and interoperate
					with log analyzing applications. The syslog-ng application supports the
					following databases: MSSQL, MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, and SQLite.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Heterogeneous environments</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application is
					the ideal choice to collect logs in massively heterogeneous environments using
					several different operating systems and hardware platforms, including Linux,
					Unix, BSD, Sun Solaris, HP-UX, Tru64, and AIX.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Filter and classify</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application can sort
					the incoming log messages based on their content and various parameters like the
					source host, application, and priority. Directories, files, and database tables
					can be created dynamically using macros. Complex filtering using regular
					expressions and boolean operators offers almost unlimited flexibility to forward
					only the important log messages to the selected destinations.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Parse and rewrite</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application can segment
					log messages to named fields or columns, and also modify the values of these
					fields.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>IPv4 and IPv6 support</emphasis>: The syslog-ng application can
					operate in both IPv4 and IPv6 network environments; it can receive and send
					messages to both types of networks.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>What syslog-ng is not</title>
		<para>The syslog-ng application is not log analysis software. It can filter log messages and
			select only the ones matching certain criteria. It can even convert the messages and
			restructure them to a predefined format, or parse the messages and segment them into
			different fields. But syslog-ng cannot interpret and analyze the meaning behind the
			messages, or recognize patterns in the occurrence of different messages.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Why is syslog-ng needed?</title>
		<para>Log messages contain information about the events happening on the hosts. Monitoring
			system events is essential for security and system health monitoring reasons. </para>
		<para>The original syslog protocol separates messages based on the priority of the message
			and the facility sending the message. These two parameters alone are often inadequate to
			consistently classify messages, as many applications might use the same facility
			&mdash; and the facility itself is not even included in the log message. To make
			things worse, many log messages contain unimportant information. The syslog-ng
			application helps you to select only the really interesting messages, and forward them
			to a central server.</para>
		<para>Company policies or other regulations often require log messages to be archived.
			Storing the important messages in a central location greatly simplifies this process.</para>
		<para>For details on how can you use syslog-ng to comply with various regulations, see the
				<emphasis>Regulatory compliance and system logging</emphasis> whitepaper available
			at <ulink url="http://www.balabit.com/support/documentation/"
				>http://www.balabit.com/support/documentation/</ulink></para>
	</section>
	<section id="syslog-ng_whatsnew">
		<title>What is new in &product; &version;?</title>
		<para>Version &version; of &product; includes the following main features:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>&product; &version; uses a new pattern database format dubbed V3 that has several improvements over the older V1 format.</para>
			<!-- FIXME update -->
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>Version &version; of &product; includes the following important changes:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para></para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Who uses syslog-ng?</title>
		<para>The syslog-ng application is used worldwide by companies and institutions who collect
			and manage the logs of several hosts, and want to store them in a centralized, organized
			way. Using syslog-ng is particularly advantageous for:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Internet Service Providers;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Financial institutions and companies requiring policy compliance;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Server, web, and application hosting companies;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Datacenters;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Wide area network (WAN) operators;</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Server farm administrators.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>The following is a list of public references &mdash; companies who use syslog-ng
			in their production environment: </para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Allianz Hungary Insurance Co. (<ulink url="http://www.allianz.hu/"
						>http://www.allianz.hu/</ulink>)</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Navisite Inc. (<ulink url="http://www.navisite.com/"
					>http://www.navisite.com/</ulink>)</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Svenska Handelsbanken AB (<ulink url="http://www.handelsbanken.com/"
						>http://www.handelsbanken.com/</ulink>)</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Swedish National Debt Office (<ulink url="http://www.riksgalden.se"
						>http://www.riksgalden.se</ulink>)</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	<section id="supported_platforms">
		<title>Supported platforms</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>supported architectures</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>supported operating systems</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>The &product; application is highly portable and is known to run on a wide range of hardware architectures (x86, x86_64, SUN Sparc, PowerPC 32 and 64, Alpha) and operating systems, including Linux, BSD, Solaris, IBM AIX, HP-UX, Mac OS X, Cygwin, Tru64, and others.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>The source code of &product; is released under the GPLv2 license and is available at <ulink url="http://www.balabit.com/network-security/syslog-ng/opensource-logging-system/upgrades/#any">http://www.balabit.com/network-security/syslog-ng/opensource-logging-system/upgrades/#any</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Precompiled binary packages provided by BalaBit are available for free for the
			supported Linux and BSD platforms at <ulink
				url="http://www.balabit.com/network-security/syslog-ng/opensource-logging-system/upgrades/"
				>http://www.balabit.com/network-security/syslog-ng/opensource-logging-system/upgrades/</ulink>.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>For &product; packages for Solaris 8-10, visit <ulink url="http://www.sunfreeware.com/">http://www.sunfreeware.com/</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>For &product; packages for IBM AIX 5 and later, visit <ulink url="http://www.perzl.org/aix/index.php?n=Main.Syslog-ng">http://www.perzl.org/aix/index.php?n=Main.Syslog-ng</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>For &product; packages for HP-UX, visit <ulink url="http://hpux.connect.org.uk/hppd/cgi-bin/search?package=on&amp;description=on&amp;term=syslog-ng&amp;Search=Search">http://hpux.connect.org.uk/hppd/cgi-bin/search?package=on&amp;description=on&amp;term=syslog-ng&amp;Search=Search</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>For &product; packages for Mac OS X, visit <ulink url="http://syslog-ng.darwinports.com/">http://syslog-ng.darwinports.com/</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Packages for routers running OpenWRT or a similar embedded Linux distribution are available at <ulink url="http://www.openwrt.org/">http://www.openwrt.org/</ulink></para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</chapter>
