<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xml-stylesheet/pdf/dtd/docbookx.dtd"
 [  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
 %entities;]> 
<chapter id="chapter_examples">
    <title>Best practices and examples</title>
    <para>This chapter discusses some special examples and recommendations.</para>
    <section id="example_general">
        <title>General recommendations</title>
        <para>This section provides general tips and recommendations on using syslog-ng. Some of the
            recommendations are detailed in the subsequent sections.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>facilities</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <listitem>
                <para>Do not base the separation of log messages into different files on the
                        <parameter>facility</parameter> parameter. As several applications and
                    processes can use the same facility, the facility does not identify the
                    application that sent the message. By default, the
                    <parameter>facility</parameter> parameter is not even included in the log
                    message itself. In general, sorting the log messages into several different
                    files can make finding specific log messages difficult. If you must create
                    separate log files, use the application name.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>timestamp</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>Standard log messages include the local time of the sending host, without any
                    time zone information. It is recommended to replace this timestamp with an
                    ISODATE timestamp, because the ISODATE format includes the year and timezone as
                    well. To convert all timestamps to the ISODATE format, include the following
                    line in the syslog-ng configuration file:</para>
                <synopsis>options {ts_format(iso) ; };</synopsis>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>name resolution</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>Resolving the IP addresses of the clients to domain names can decrease the
                    performance of syslog-ng. See <xref linkend="examples_dns"/> for details.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section id="parallel_connections">
        <title>Handling lots of parallel connections</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>parallel connections</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>batch processing</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>parameters</primary>
            <secondary>time_sleep()</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>parameters</primary>
            <secondary>max_connections()</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>When syslog-ng is receiving messages from a large number of TCP or unix-stream
            connections, the CPU usage of syslog-ng might increase even if the number of messages is
            low. By default, syslog-ng processes every message when it is received. To reduce the
            CPU usage, process the incoming messages in batches. To accomplish this, instruct
            syslog-ng to wait for a short time before processing a message. During this period
            additional messages might arrive that can be processed together with the original
            message. To process log messages in batches, set the <parameter>time_sleep()</parameter>
            option (measured in milliseconds) to a non-zero value. Include the following line in
            your syslog-ng configuration:</para>
        <synopsis>options { time_sleep(20); };</synopsis>
        <note>
            <para>It is not recommended to increase the <parameter>time_sleep()</parameter>
                parameter above 100ms, as that might distort timestamps, slow down syslog-ng, and
                cause messages to be dropped.</para>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>parameters</primary>
                <secondary>log_fifo_size()</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>parameters</primary>
                <secondary>log_fetch_limit()</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>When modifying the <parameter>time_sleep()</parameter> option, also adjust the
                    <parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter> and
                <parameter>log_fifo_size()</parameter> options accordingly.</para>
        </note>
        <para>The <parameter>max_connections()</parameter> parameter limits the number of parallel
            connections for the source. </para>
        <para>If adjusting the <parameter>time_sleep()</parameter> option is not desired for some
            reason, an alternative solution is to use <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter>,
                <parameter>udp()</parameter> and <parameter>unix-dgram()</parameter> sources instead
            of <parameter>tcp()</parameter> connections.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="handling_large_load">
        <title>Handling large message load</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>optimizing syslog-ng performance</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>filters</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>regular expressions</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>This section provides tips on optimizing the performance of syslog-ng. Optimizing the
            performance is important for syslog-ng hosts that handle large traffic.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Disable DNS resolution, or resolve hostnames locally. See <xref
                        linkend="examples_dns"/> for details.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Enable flow-control for the TCP sources. See <xref linkend="concepts_flow_control"/>
                    for details.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Do not use the <parameter>usertty()</parameter> destination driver. Under
                    heavy load, the users are not be able to read the messages from the console, and
                    it slows down syslog-ng.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Do not use regular expressions in our filters. Evaluating general regular
                    expressions puts a high load on the CPU. Use simple filter functions and logical
                    operators instead. See <xref linkend="regular_expressions"/> for details.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>When receiving lots of messages using the UDP protocol, increase the size of
                    the UDP receive buffer on the syslog-ng hosts. For information about sizing and
                    modifying the UDP buffer, see <ulink
                        url="http://www.29west.com/docs/THPM/udp-buffer-sizing.html"
                        >UDP Buffer Sizing</ulink>.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <!-- FIXME a sync obsolete, updatelni a flush_lines parameterre - kell egyaltalan? -->
    <!--	<section id="sync">
            <title>The sync() parameter</title>
            
            <indexterm>
            <primary>parameters</primary>
            <secondary>sync()</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The syslog-ng application buffers the log messages to be sent in an output queue. The
            <parameter>sync()</parameter> parameter specifies the number of messages held in
            this buffer.</para>
            <para>Note that syslog-ng does not write all buffered messages into a single chunk; each
            message is written with a single <parameter>write()</parameter> system call.</para>
            <para>For file destinations, the received messages can be written to disk immediately after
            the message is received. To accomplish this, set the <parameter>sync()</parameter>
            option to zero.</para>
            <synopsis>
            options { sync(0); };	
            </synopsis>
            </section>-->

    <section id="examples_dns">
        <title>Using name resolution in syslog-ng</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>name resolution</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>The syslog-ng application can resolve the hostnames of the clients and include them in
            the log messages. However, the performance of syslog-ng is severely degraded if the
            domain name server is unaccessible or slow. Therefore, it is not recommended to resolve
            hostnames in syslog-ng. If you must use name resolution from syslog-ng, consider the
            following: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Use DNS caching. Verify that the DNS cache is large enough to store all
                    important hostnames. (By default, the syslog-ng DNS cache stores
                    <parameter>1007</parameter> entries.)</para>
                <synopsis>options { dns_cache(2000); };</synopsis>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If the IP addresses of the clients change only rarely, set the expiry of the
                    DNS cache large.</para>
                <synopsis>options { dns_cache_expire(87600); };</synopsis>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If possible, resolve the hostnames locally. See <xref
                        linkend="example_local_dns"/> for details. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <note>
            <para>Domain name resolution is important mainly in relay and server mode.</para>
        </note>
        <section id="example_local_dns">
            <title>Resolving hostnames locally </title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>name resolution</primary>
                <secondary>local</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Resolving hostnames locally enables you to display hostnames in the log files for
                frequently used hosts, without having to rely on a DNS server. The known IP address
                &ndash; hostname pairs are stored locally in a file. In the log messages,
                syslog-ng will replace the IP addresses of known hosts with their hostnames. To
                configure local name resolution, complete the following steps:</para>
            <procedure>
                <title>Resolving hostnames locally</title>
                <step>
                    <para>Add the hostnames and the respective IP addresses to the file used for
                        local name resolution. On Linux and UNIX systems, this is the
                            <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file. Consult the documentation of your
                        operating system for details.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Instruct syslog-ng to resolve hostnames locally. Set the
                            <parameter>use_dns()</parameter> option of syslog-ng to
                            <parameter>persist_only</parameter>.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Set the <parameter>dns_cache_hosts()</parameter> option to point to the
                        file storing the hostnames. </para>
                    <synopsis>options { 
        use_dns(persist_only);
        dns_cache_hosts(/etc/hosts); };</synopsis>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="example_chroot">
        <title>Collecting logs from chroot</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>chroots</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>To collect logs from a chroot using a syslog-ng client running on the host, complete
            the following steps:</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Collecting logs from chroot</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata format="PNG" align="center" fileref="chroot01.png"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="&imgroot;/chroot01.png" scale="75"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <procedure>
            <title>Collecting logs from chroot</title>
            <step>
                <para>Create a <filename>/dev</filename> directory within the chroot. The
                    applications running in the chroot send their log messages here.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create a local source in the configuration file of the syslog-ng application
                    running outside the chroot. This source should point to the
                    <filename>/dev/log</filename> file within the chroot (for example to the
                        <filename>/chroot/dev/log</filename> directory).</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Include the source in a log statement.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <note>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>timezone</primary>
                <secondary>in chroots</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>You need to set up timezone information within your chroot as well. This usually
                means creating a symlink to <filename>/etc/localtime</filename>.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section id="example_klogd">
        <title>Replacing klogd on Linux</title>
        <para>The syslog-ng application can replace both the syslogd and klogd daemons on Linux
            hosts. To replace klogd, complete the following steps:</para>
        <procedure>
            <title>Replacing klogd on Linux</title>
            <step>
                <para>Add a file source pointing to <filename>/proc/kmsg</filename> to the syslog-ng
                    configuration file.</para>
                <synopsis>source s_kmsg { file("/proc/kmsg"); };</synopsis>
                <warning>
                    <para>Do not use a pipe source to read <filename>/proc/kmsg</filename>; pipe
                        opens the source in read-write mode and this may cause problems when using
                        SELinux or similar security measures.</para>
                </warning>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Include the source defined in Step 1 in a log path.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Stop klogd.</para>
                <warning>
                    <para>Do not run klogd and syslog-ng simultaneously when using syslog-ng to read
                            <filename>/proc/kmsg</filename>, as it might block syslog-ng.</para>
                </warning>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </section>
    <section id="example_timezones">
        <title>A note on timezones and timestamps</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>timestamp</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>timezones</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>UTC</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>Coordinated Universal Time</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>If the clients run syslog-ng, then use the ISO timestamp, because it includes timezone
            information. That way you do not need to adjust the
            <parameter>recv_time_zone()</parameter> parameter of syslog-ng.</para>
        <para>If you want syslog-ng to output timestamps in Unix (POSIX) time format, use the
                <parameter>S_UNIXTIME</parameter> and <parameter>R_UNIXTIME</parameter> macros. You
            do not need to change any of the timezone related parameters, because the timestamp
            information of incoming messages is converted to Unix time internally, and Unix time is
            a timezone-independent time representation. (Actually, Unix time measures the number of
            seconds elapsed since midnight of Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) January 1, 1970, but
            does not count leap seconds.) </para>
    </section>
    <section id="example_dropping_messages">
        <title>Dropping messages</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>skipping messages</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>dropping messages</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>To skip the processing of a message without sending it to a destination, create a log
            statement with the appropriate filters, but do not include any destination in the
            statement, and use the <parameter>final</parameter> flag. </para>
        <example>
            <title>Skipping messages</title>
            <para>The following log statement drops all <parameter>debug</parameter> level messages
                without any further processing.</para>
            <synopsis>filter demo_debugfilter { level(debug); };
log { source(s_all); filter(demo_debugfilter); flags(final); };</synopsis>
        </example>

    </section>


</chapter>
