<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xml-stylesheet/pdf/dtd/docbookx.dtd"
 [  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
 %entities;]> 
<chapter id="chapter_configuration">
    <title>Configuring syslog-ng</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>configuring syslog-ng</primary>
        <secondary>on Linux/Unix</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>This chapter describes how to configure syslog-ng. </para>
    <section id="config_file">
        <title>The syslog-ng configuration file</title>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>syslog-ng.conf</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>The syslog-ng application is configured by editing the
            <filename>syslog-ng.conf</filename> file. Use any regular text editor application to
            modify the file. The precompiled syslog-ng packages include sample configuration files
            as well.</para>
        <para>Every syslog-ng configuration file must begin with a line containing the version
            information of syslog-ng. For syslog-ng version 3.0, this line looks like:</para>
        <synopsis>@version:3.0</synopsis>
        <para>If the configuration file does not contain the version information, syslog-ng assumes
            that the file is for syslog-ng version 2.x. In this case it interprets the configuration
            and sends warnings about the parts of the configuration that should be updated. Version
            3.0 of syslog-ng will correctly operate with configuration files of version 2.x, but the
            default values of certain parameters are different in 3.0.</para>
        <para>All identifiers, option names and attributes, and any other strings used in the
            syslog-ng configuration file are case sensitive. Objects must be defined before they are
            referenced in another statement.</para>
        <example>
            <title>A simple configuration file</title>
            <para>The following is a very simple configuration file for syslog-ng: it collects the
                internal messages of syslog-ng and the messages from <parameter>/dev/log</parameter>
                into the <filename>/var/log/messages_syslog-ng.log</filename> file.</para>
            <synopsis>@version:3.0
                
source s_local { unix-stream("/dev/log"); internal(); };

destination d_file_normal {file("/var/log/messages_syslog-ng.log"); };

log { source(s_local); destination(d_file); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <tip>
            <para>Before activating a new configuration, check that your configuration file is
                syntactically correct using the <command>syslog-ng --syntax</command> command.</para>
            <para>To activate the configuration, reload the configuration of syslog-ng using the
                    <command>/etc/init.d/syslog-ng reload</command> command.</para>
        </tip>
        <para>The <filename>syslog-ng.conf</filename> and <filename>license.txt</filename> files are
            located under the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/</filename> directory.</para>
        <note>
            <para>Earlier versions of syslog-ng PE stored the configuration and license files under
                different directories, depending on the platform; typically under
                    <filename>/etc/syslog-ng/</filename>.</para>
        </note>
        <!-- <table id="configfile_location">
            <title>The location of syslog-ng.conf on different platforms</title>
            
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Operating System</entry>
                        <entry>Location</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Linux, AIX 5.x</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <filename>/etc/syslog-ng/syslog-ng.conf</filename>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Solaris, HP-UX, FreeBSD</entry>
                        <entry>
                            <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/syslog-ng.conf</filename>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <note>
            <para>On HP-UX and Solaris operating systems the earlier versions of syslog-ng stored
                the configuration file at
                <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/syslog-ng.conf</filename>.</para>
        </note> -->
        <para>On Microsoft Windows platforms the syslog-ng agent stores its configuration in the
            system registry, and can be configured from a graphical interface. See <xref
                linkend="chapter_windows"/> for details.</para>
        <section id="including-config-files">
            <title>Including configuration files</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>syslog-ng.conf</primary>
                <secondary>includes</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>configuration file</primary>
                <secondary>including other files</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The syslog-ng application supports including external files in its configuration
                file, so parts of its configuration can be managed separately. To include the
                contents of a file in the syslog-ng configuration, use the following syntax</para>
            <synopsis>include "filename";</synopsis>
            <para>This imports the entire file into the configuration of syslog-ng, at the location
                of the include statement. If you specify a directory, syslog-ng will try to include
                every file in alphabetic order. When including configuration files, consider the
                following points:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If an object is defined twice (e.g., the original syslog-ng configuration
                        file and the file imported into this configuration file both define the same
                        option, source, or other object), then the object that is defined later in
                        the configuration file will be effective. For example, if you set a global
                        option at the beginning of the configuration file, and later include a file
                        that defines the same option with a different value, then the option defined
                        in the imported file will be used.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Files can be embedded into each other: the included files can contain
                        include statements as well, up to a maximum depth of 15 levels.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Include statements can only be used at top level of the configuration
                        file. For example, the following is correct:</para>
                    <synopsis>@version:3.0
include "example.conf";</synopsis>
                    <para>But the following is not:</para>
                    <synopsis>source s_example {
    include "example.conf"
     };</synopsis>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <warning>
                <para>The syslog-ng application will not start if it cannot find a file that is to
                    be included in its configuration. Always double-check the filenames, paths, and
                    access rights when including configuration files, and use the
                        <command>--syntax-only</command> command-line option to check your
                    configuration.</para>
            </warning>
        </section>

        <section id="logchksign">
            <title>Logging configuration changes</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>syslog-ng.conf</primary>
                <secondary>fingerprint</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>configuration file</primary>
                <secondary>detecting changes</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>logchksign</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Every time syslog-ng is started, or its configuration is reloaded, it
                automatically logs the SHA-1 fingerprint of its configuration file using the
                    <parameter>internal</parameter> message source. That way any modification of the
                configuration of your syslog-ng clients is visible in the central logs. Note that
                the log message does not contain the exact change, nor can the configuration file be
                retrieved from the fingerprint. Only the fact of the configuration change can be
                detected.</para>
            <para>The fingerprint can be examined with the <command>logchksign</command>
                command-line application, which detects that the fingerprint was indeed generated by
                a syslog-ng application. Just paste the hashes from the log message after the
                logchksign command like in the following example:</para>
            <command>bin/logchksign "cfg-fingerprint='832ef664ff79df8afc66cd955c0c8aaa3c343f31',
                cfg-nonce-ndx='0', cfg-signature='785223cfa19ad52b855550be141b00306347b0a9'
            "</command>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section id="defining_global_objects">
        <title>Defining global objects</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>global objects</primary>
            <secondary>defining</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>defining global objects</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para id="global_objects_para1">Global objects (e.g., sources, destinations, log paths, or
            filters) are defined in the syslog-ng configuration file. Object definitions consist of
            the following elements: </para>
        <itemizedlist id="global_objects_syntax">
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Type of the object</emphasis>: One of <parameter>source</parameter>,
                        <parameter>destination</parameter>, <parameter>log</parameter>,
                        <parameter>filter</parameter>, <parameter>parser</parameter>,
                        <parameter>rewrite</parameter> rule, or
                <parameter>template</parameter>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Identifier of the object</emphasis>: A unique name identifying the
                    object. When using a reserved word as an identifier, enclose the identifier in
                    quotation marks.</para>
                <tip>
                    <para>Use identifiers that refer to the type of the object they identify. For
                        example, prefix source objects with <parameter>s_</parameter>, destinations
                        with <parameter>d_</parameter>, and so on. </para>
                </tip>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Parameters</emphasis>: The parameters of the object, enclosed in
                    braces <parameter>{parameters}</parameter>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Semicolon</emphasis>: Object definitions end with a semicolon
                        (<parameter>;</parameter>).</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para id="global_objects_para2">The syntax is summarized as follows:</para>
        <synopsis>type identifier { parameters };</synopsis>
        <para>Objects have parameters; some of them are required, others are optional. Required
            parameters are positional, meaning that they must be specified in a defined order.
            Optional arguments can be specified in any order using the
            <literal>option(value)</literal> format. If a parameter (optional or required) is not
            specified, its default value is used. The parameters and their default values are listed
            in the reference section of the particular object. See <xref linkend="chapter_reference"
            /> for details.</para>
        <example>
            <title>Using required and optional parameters</title>
            <para>The <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter> source driver has a single required
                argument: the name of the socket to listen on. Optional parameters follow the socket
                name in any order, so the following source definitions have the same effect: </para>
            <synopsis>source s_demo_stream1 { 
           unix-stream("/dev/log" max-connections(10) group(log)); };
source s_demo_stream2 { 
           unix-stream("/dev/log" group(log) max-connections(10)); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <para>To add comments to the configuration file, start a line with <parameter>#</parameter>
            and write your comments. These lines are ignored by syslog-ng.</para>
        <synopsis># Comment: This is a stream source
source s_demo_stream { 
           unix-stream("/dev/log" max-connections(10) group(log)); };</synopsis>
        <section id="configfile_syntax">
            <title>Notes about the configuration syntax</title>
            <para>When you are editing the syslog-ng configuration file, note the following points:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When writing the names of options and parameters (or other reserved
                        words), the hyphen (<parameter>-</parameter>) and underscore
                        (<parameter>_</parameter>) characters are equivalent, e.g.,
                            <parameter>max-connections(10)</parameter> and
                            <parameter>max_connections(10)</parameter> are both correct.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Number can be prefixed with <parameter>+</parameter> or
                        <parameter>-</parameter> to indicate positive or negative values. Numbers
                        beginning with zero (<parameter>0</parameter>) or <parameter>0x</parameter>
                        are treated as hexadecimal or octal numbers, respectively.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can use commas (<parameter>,</parameter>) to separate options or other
                        parameters for readability; syslog-ng completely ignores them. The following
                        declarations are equivalent:</para>
                    <synopsis>source s_demo_stream { 
                        unix-stream("/dev/log" max-connections(10) group(log)); };</synopsis>
                    <synopsis>source s_demo_stream { 
                        unix-stream("/dev/log", max-connections(10), group(log)); };</synopsis>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Strings between single quotes (<parameter>'string'</parameter>) are
                        treated literally, you do not have to escape special characters. This makes
                        writing and reading regular expressions much more simple: it is recommended
                        to use single quotes when writing regular expressions.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When enclosing strings between double-quotes
                        (<parameter>"string"</parameter>), you have to escape special characters:
                        e.g., when enclosing a regular expression that uses the
                        <parameter>\</parameter> character to escape a special character, you have
                        to add an extra <parameter>\</parameter> (e.g.,
                        <parameter>"\\n"</parameter>). It is recommended to use single quotes
                        instead.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Enclosing normal strings between double-quotes
                        (<parameter>"string"</parameter>) is not necessary, you can just omit the
                        double-quotes. E.g., when writing filters,
                        <parameter>match("sometext")</parameter> and
                        <parameter>match(sometext)</parameter> will both match for the
                            <parameter>sometext</parameter> string.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When enclosing object IDs (e.g., the name of a destination) between
                        double-quotes (<parameter>"mydestination"</parameter>), the ID can include
                        whitespace as well, e.g.:</para>
                    <synopsis>source "s demo stream" { 
                        unix-stream("/dev/log" max-connections(10) group(log)); };</synopsis>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

        </section>

    </section>
    <section id="sources">
        <title>Sources and source drivers</title>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>sources</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>source drivers</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>A source is where syslog-ng receives log messages. Sources consist of one or more
            drivers, each defining where and how messages are received.</para>
        <para>To define a source, add a source statement to the syslog-ng configuration file using
            the following syntax: <indexterm>
                <primary>destinations</primary>
                <secondary>defining</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <synopsis>source &lt;identifier&gt; { source-driver(params); source-driver(params); ... };</synopsis>
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>A simple source statement</title>
            <para>The following source statement receives messages on the TCP port
                <parameter>1999</parameter> of the interface having the
                <parameter>10.1.2.3</parameter> IP address.</para>
            <synopsis>source s_demo_tcp { tcp(ip(10.1.2.3) port(1999)); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <example>
            <title>A source statement using two source drivers</title>
            <para>The following source statement receives messages on the
                <parameter>1999</parameter> TCP port and the <parameter>1999</parameter> UDP port of
                the interface having the <parameter>10.1.2.3</parameter> IP address.</para>
            <synopsis>source s_demo_two_drivers { 
           tcp(ip(10.1.2.3) port(1999)); 
           udp(ip(10.1.2.3) port(1999)); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <example>
            <title>Setting default priority and facility</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>setting facility</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>overriding facility</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>If the message received by the source does not have a proper syslog header, you
                can use the <parameter>default-facility()</parameter> and
                    <parameter>default-priority()</parameter> options to set the facility and
                priority of the messages. Note that these values are applied only to messages that
                do not set these parameters in their header.</para>
            <synopsis>source headerless_messages { udp(default-facility(syslog) default-priority(emerg)); };</synopsis>
        </example>

        <para>Define a source only once. The same source can be used in several log paths.
            Duplicating sources causes syslog-ng to open the source (TCP/IP port, file, etc.) more
            than once, which might cause problems. For example, include the
            <parameter>/dev/log</parameter> file source only in one source statement, and use this
            statement in more than one log path if needed. </para>
        <para>To collect log messages on a specific platform, it is important to know how the native
                <parameter>syslogd</parameter> communicates on that platform. The following table
            summarizes the operation methods of <parameter>syslogd</parameter> on some of the tested
            platforms:</para>
        <!-- FIXME belevenni a hianyzo, de tamogatott platformokat, es forrasokat pl. AIX, HP-UX, ... 
        osszegyujteni, hogy az egyes platformokon milyen forrasokat kell felvenni ahhoz, 
            hogy a syslog-ng a nativ syslog funkcionalitasat tudja 
        -->
        <table>
            <title>Communication methods used between the applications and syslogd</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>sources</primary>
                <secondary>on different platforms</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Platform</entry>
                        <entry>Method</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Linux</entry>
                        <entry>A <parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> unix socket named
                                <parameter>/dev/log</parameter>; some of the distributions switched
                            over to using <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter>, though applications
                            still work with either method. </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>BSD flavors</entry>
                        <entry>A <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> unix socket named
                                <parameter>/var/run/log</parameter>.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Solaris (2.5 or below)</entry>
                        <entry>An SVR4 style <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> device named
                                <parameter>/dev/log</parameter>.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Solaris (2.6 or above)</entry>
                        <entry>In addition to the <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> device used in
                            earlier versions, 2.6 uses a new multithreaded IPC method called door.
                            By default the door used by <parameter>syslogd</parameter> is
                                <parameter>/etc/.syslog_door</parameter>. </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>HP-UX 11 or later</entry>
                        <entry>HP-UX uses a named pipe called <filename>/dev/log</filename> that is
                            padded to 2048 bytes, e.g., <parameter>source s_hp-ux {pipe ("/dev/log"
                                pad_size(2048)}</parameter>.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <!-- FIXME -->
                        <entry>AIX 5.2 and 5.3</entry>
                        <entry>A <parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> or
                            <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> unix socket called
                            <filename>/dev/log</filename>.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>Each possible communication mechanism has a corresponding source driver in syslog-ng.
            For example, to open a unix socket with <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> style
            communication use the driver <parameter>unix-dgram</parameter>. The same socket using
            the <parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> style &mdash; as used under Linux &mdash;
            is called <parameter>unix-stream</parameter>. </para>
        <example>
            <title>Source statement on a Linux based operating system</title>
            <para>The following source statement collects the following log messages:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>internal()</emphasis>: Messages generated by syslog-ng.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>udp(ip(0.0.0.0) port(514))</emphasis>: Messages arriving to the
                            <parameter>514/UDP</parameter> port of any interface of the host.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>unix-stream("/dev/log");</emphasis>: Messages arriving to the
                            <parameter>/dev/log</parameter> socket.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <synopsis>source s_demo { 
           internal(); 
           udp(ip(0.0.0.0) port(514)); 
           unix-stream("/dev/log"); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <para>The following table lists the source drivers available in syslog-ng.</para>
        <table id="table_source_drivers">
            <title>Source drivers available in syslog-ng</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>source drivers</primary>
                <secondary>list of</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Name</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_sources_internal">internal()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Messages generated internally in syslog-ng.</entry>
                    </row>


                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_sources_file">file()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Opens the specified file and reads messages.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_sources_pipe">pipe(), fifo</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Opens the specified named pipe and reads messages.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="reference_source_program">program()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Opens the specified application and reads messages from its standard
                            output.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_sources_sunstreams">sun-stream(),
                                sun-streams()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Opens the specified <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> device on Solaris
                            systems and reads incoming messages.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_sources_syslog">syslog()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Listens for incoming messages using the new <link
                                linkend="concepts_message_ietfsyslog">IETF-standard syslog
                            protocol</link>.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_sources_tcpudp">tcp(), tcp6()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Listens on the specified TCP port for incoming messages using the
                                <link linkend="concepts_message_bsdsyslog">BSD-syslog
                            protocol</link> over IPv4 and IPv6 networks, respectively.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_sources_tcpudp">udp(), udp6()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Listens on the specified UDP port for incoming messages using the
                                <link linkend="concepts_message_bsdsyslog">BSD-syslog
                            protocol</link> over IPv4 and IPv6 networks, respectively.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_sources_unixstream">unix-dgram()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Opens the specified unix socket in <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter>
                            mode and listens for incoming messages.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_sources_unixstream">unix-stream()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Opens the specified unix socket in <parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter>
                            mode and listens for incoming messages.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>For a complete description of the parameters of the above drivers, see <xref
                linkend="reference_sourcedrivers"/>. </para>

        <section id="configuring_sources_internal">
            <title>Collecting internal messages</title>
            <para>All messages generated internally by syslog-ng use this special source. To collect
                warnings, errors and notices from syslog-ng itself, include this source in one of
                your source statements. </para>
            <synopsis>internal()</synopsis>
            <para>The syslog-ng application will issue a warning upon startup if none of the defined
                log paths reference this driver. </para>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_source_internal)"/>
            <section id="reference_log_statistics">
                <title>Log statistics</title>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>log statistics</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>statistics</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>Periodically, syslog-ng sends a message containing statistics about the
                    received messages, and about any lost messages since the last such message. It
                    includes a <parameter>processed</parameter> entry for every source and
                    destination, listing the number of messages received or sent, and a
                        <parameter>dropped</parameter> entry including the IP address of the server
                    for every destination where syslog-ng has lost messages. The
                        <parameter>center(received)</parameter> entry shows the total number of
                    messages received from every configured sources.</para>
                <para>The following is a sample log statistics message for a configuration that has
                    a single source (<parameter>s_local</parameter>) and a network and a local file
                    destination (<parameter>d_network</parameter> and
                    <parameter>d_local</parameter>, respectively). All incoming messages are sent to
                    both destinations.</para>
                <synopsis>Log statistics;
                    dropped='tcp(AF_INET(192.168.10.1:514))=6439',
                    processed='center(received)=234413',
                    processed='destination(d_tcp)=234413',
                    processed='destination(d_local)=234413',
                    processed='source(s_local)=234413'</synopsis>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>log statistics</primary>
                    <secondary>on unix-socket</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>statistics</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>Log statistics can be also retrieved on-demand using the <command>echo STATS |
                        nc -U var/run/syslog-ng.ctl</command> command. This returns a list of source
                    groups and destinations, as well as the number of processed messages for each.
                    The verbosity of the statistics can be set using the
                    <parameter>stats_level()</parameter> option. See <xref
                        linkend="reference_options"/> for details.</para>
                <note>
                    <para>To query the statistics, you need the OpenBSD-style
                        <command>netcat</command> application. The <command>netcat</command>
                        included in most Linux distributions is a GNU-style version that is not
                        suitable to query the statistics of syslog-ng. An alternative is to use the
                            <command>socat</command> application: <command>echo STATS | socat -vv
                            UNIX-CONNECT:/opt/syslog-ng/var/run/syslog-ng.ctl -</command>.</para>
                </note>
                <!-- FIXME ertelmes peldat, ez nem az igazi, es reszletezni, hogy pontosan mit ir ki
                src.udp;s_local#1;;a;processed;0 src.udp;s_local#1;;a;stamp;0 source;s_local;;a;processed;7
                src.internal;s_local#0;;a;processed;7 
                src.internal;s_local#0;;a;stamp;1222437774
                src.host;;bzorp;d;processed;7 
                src.host;;bzorp;d;stamp;1222437774 
                center;;received;a;processed;0
                src.file;s_local#5;/home/bazsi/logs/input.log;a;processed;0
                src.file;s_local#5;/home/bazsi/logs/input.log;a;stamp;0 destination;d_logstore;;a;processed;7
                center;;queued;a;processed;0
                dst.logstore;d_logstore#0;/home/bazsi/logs/logstore.ls;a;processed;7                                
                 -->
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_sources_file">
            <title>Collecting messages from text files</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>source drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>file()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Collects log messages from plain-text files, e.g., from the logfiles of an Apache
                webserver.</para>
            <para>The syslog-ng application notices if a file is renamed or replaced with a new
                file, so it can correctly follow the file even if logrotation is used. When
                syslog-ng is restarted, it records the position of the last sent log message, and
                continues to send messages from this position after the restart.</para>
            <para>The file driver has a single required parameter specifying the file to open. For
                the list of available optional parameters, see <xref linkend="reference_source_file"
                />. </para>
            <synopsis>Declaration:
                file(filename);</synopsis>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>wildcards</primary>
                <secondary>in file sources</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(reference_file_wildcard)"/>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(reference_file_wildcard_inotify)"/>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_source_file)"/>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_source_file_wildcard)"/>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_source_file_recursive)"/>
            <para>The kernel usually sends log messages to a special file
                (<parameter>/dev/kmsg</parameter> on BSDs, <parameter>/proc/kmsg</parameter> on
                Linux). The <parameter>file()</parameter> driver reads log messages from such files.
                The syslog-ng application can periodically check the file for new log messages if
                the <parameter>follow_freq()</parameter> option is set. </para>
            <note>
                <para>On Linux, the <parameter>klogd</parameter> daemon can be used in addition to
                    syslog-ng to read kernel messages and forward them to syslog-ng.
                        <parameter>klogd</parameter> used to preprocess kernel messages to resolve
                    symbols etc., but as this is deprecated by <parameter>ksymoops</parameter> there
                    is really no point in running both <parameter>klogd</parameter> and syslog-ng in
                    parallel. Also note that running two processes reading
                    <filename>/proc/kmsg</filename> at the same time might result in dead-locks. </para>
                <para>When using syslog-ng to read messages from the <filename>/proc/kmsg</filename>
                    file, syslog-ng automatically disables the <parameter>follow_freq()</parameter>
                    parameter to avoid blocking the file.</para>
            </note>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_sources_pipe">
            <title>Collecting messages from named pipes</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>source drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>pipe()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The pipe driver opens a named pipe with the specified name and listens for
                messages. It is used as the native message delivery protocol on HP-UX.</para>
            <para>The pipe driver has a single required parameter, specifying the filename of the
                pipe to open. For the list of available optional parameters, see <xref
                    linkend="reference_source_pipe"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration:
                pipe(filename);</synopsis>
            <note>
                <para>As of syslog-ng Open Source Edition 3.0.2, pipes are created automatically. In
                    earlier versions, you had to create the pipe using the
                    <command>mkfifo(1)</command> command. </para>
            </note>
            <para>Pipe is very similar to the <parameter>file()</parameter> driver, but there are a
                few differences, for example <parameter>pipe()</parameter> opens its argument in
                read-write mode, therefore it is not recommended to be used on special files like
                    <filename>/proc/kmsg</filename>.</para>
            <warning>
                <para>It is not recommended to use <parameter>pipe()</parameter> on anything else
                    than real pipes. </para>
            </warning>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_source_pipe)"/>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_sources_sunstreams">
            <title>Collecting messages on Sun Solaris</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>source drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>sun-streams()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Solaris uses its <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> framework to send messages to the
                    <parameter>syslogd</parameter> process. Solaris 2.5.1 and above uses an IPC
                called <emphasis>door</emphasis> in addition to <parameter>STREAMS</parameter>, to
                confirm the delivery of a message. The syslog-ng application supports the IPC
                mechanism via the <parameter>door()</parameter> option (see below).</para>
            <note>
                <para>The <parameter>sun-streams()</parameter> driver must be enabled when the
                    syslog-ng application is compiled (see <command>./configure --help</command>).
                    The pre-compiled binaries of syslog-ng Open Source Edition purchased from
                    BalaBit and syslog-ng Premium Edition have this option enabled.</para>
            </note>
            <para>The <parameter>sun-streams()</parameter> driver has a single required argument
                specifying the <parameter>STREAMS</parameter> device to open, and the
                    <parameter>door()</parameter> option. For the list of available optional
                parameters, see <xref linkend="reference_source_sunstreams"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration:
        sun-streams(name_of_the_streams_device door(filename_of_the_door));</synopsis>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_source_sunstreams)"/>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_sources_syslog">
            <title>Collecting messages using the IETF syslog protocol</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>source drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>syslog()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The <parameter>syslog()</parameter> driver enables to receive messages from the
                network using the new standard syslog protocol and message format (also called
                IETF-syslog protocol; described in RFC 5424-28, see <xref
                    linkend="concepts_message_ietfsyslog"/>). UDP, TCP, and TLS-encrypted TCP can
                all be used to transport the messages.</para>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>TLS</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>For the list of available optional parameters, see <xref
                    linkend="reference_source_syslog"/>.</para>
            <!-- FIXME mi a kotelezo parameter? -->
            <synopsis>Declaration:
            syslog(ip() port() transport() options());</synopsis>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_source_syslog)"/>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_sources_tcpudp">
            <title>Collecting messages from remote hosts using the BSD syslog protocol</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>source drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>tcp()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>source drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>tcp6()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>source drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>udp()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>source drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>udp6()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The <parameter>tcp()</parameter>, <parameter>tcp6()</parameter>,
                <parameter>udp()</parameter>, <parameter>udp6()</parameter> drivers can receive
                messages from the network using the TCP and UDP networking protocols. The
                    <parameter>tcp6()</parameter> and <parameter>udp6()</parameter> drivers use the
                IPv6 network protocol, while <parameter>tcp()</parameter> and
                <parameter>udp()</parameter> use IPv4.</para>
            <para>UDP is a simple datagram oriented protocol, which provides "best effort service"
                to transfer messages between hosts. It may lose messages, and no attempt is made at
                the protocol level to retransmit such lost messages. The <emphasis>
                    <link linkend="concepts_message_bsdsyslog">BSD-syslog</link>
                </emphasis> protocol traditionally uses UDP.</para>
            <para>TCP provides connection-oriented service, which basically means that the path of
                the messages is flow-controlled. Along this path, each message is acknowledged, and
                retransmission is done for lost packets. Generally it is safer to use TCP, because
                lost connections can be detected, and no messages get lost, assuming that the TCP
                connection does not break. When a TCP connection is broken the 'in-transit' messages
                that were sent by syslog-ng but not yet received on the other side are lost.
                (Basically these messages are still sitting in the socket buffer of the sending host
                and syslog-ng has no information about the fate of these messages). </para>
            <para>The <parameter>tcp()</parameter> and <parameter>udp()</parameter> drivers do not
                have any required parameters. By default they bind to the
                <parameter>0.0.0.0:514</parameter> address, which means that syslog-ng will listen
                on all available interfaces, port 514. To limit accepted connections to only one
                interface, use the <parameter>localip()</parameter> parameter as described below.
                For the list of available optional parameters, see <xref
                    linkend="reference_source_tcpudp"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration:
                tcp([options]);
                udp([options]);</synopsis>
            <note>
                <para>The tcp port 514 is reserved for use with <command>rshell</command>, so select
                    a different port if syslog-ng and <command>rshell</command> is used at the same
                    time. </para>
            </note>
            <para>If you specify a multicast bind address to <parameter>udp()</parameter> and
                    <parameter>udp6()</parameter>, syslog-ng will automatically join the necessary
                multicast group. TCP does not support multicasting. </para>
            <para>The syslog-ng Premium Edition application supports TLS (Transport Layer Security,
                also known as SSL) for the tcp() and tcp6() drivers. See the TLS-specific options
                below and <xref linkend="tls_serverauth"/> for details. For the list of available
                optional parameters, see <xref linkend="reference_source_sunstreams"/>.</para>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>TLS</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_source_tcpudp)"/>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_sources_unixstream">
            <title>Collecting messages from UNIX domain sockets</title>
            <para>The <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter> and <parameter>unix-dgram()</parameter>
                drivers open an <parameter>AF_UNIX</parameter> socket and start listening on it for
                messages. The <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter> driver is primarily used on Linux
                and uses <parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> semantics (connection oriented, no
                messages are lost); while <parameter>unix-dgram()</parameter> is used on BSDs and
                uses <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> semantics: this may result in lost local
                messages if the system is overloaded. </para>
            <para>To avoid denial of service attacks when using connection-oriented protocols, the
                number of simultaneously accepted connections should be limited. This can be
                achieved using the <parameter>max-connections()</parameter> parameter. The default
                value of this parameter is quite strict, you might have to increase it on a busy
                system. </para>
            <para>Both unix-stream and unix-dgram have a single required argument that specifies the
                filename of the socket to create. For the list of available optional parameters, see
                    <xref linkend="reference_source_unixstream"/></para>
            <synopsis>Declaration: 
                unix-stream(filename [options]);
                unix-dgram(filename [options]);</synopsis>
            <note>
                <para><parameter>syslogd</parameter> on Linux originally used
                    <parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> sockets, but some distributions switched to
                        <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> around 1999 to fix a possible DoS problem.
                    On Linux you can choose to use whichever driver you like as syslog clients
                    automatically detect the socket type being used. </para>
            </note>
            <para>The difference between the unix-stream and unix-dgram drivers is similar to the
                difference between the TCP and UDP network protocols. Use the following guidelines
                to select which driver to use in a particular situation:</para>
            <para>Choose unix-stream if you would choose TCP (stream) instead of UDP (datagram). The
                unix-stream driver offers the following features:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Increased reliability</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Ordered delivery of messages</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Client-side notification of failures</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Choose unix-dgram if you would choose TCP (stream) over UDP (datagram). The
                unix-dgram driver offers the following features:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Decreased possibility of Dos by opening too many connections (a local
                        vulnerability)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Less overhead</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>However, the client does not notice if a message is lost when using the unix-dgram
                driver.</para>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_source_unixstream)"/>
        </section>

    </section>
    <section id="destinations">
        <title>Destinations and destination drivers</title>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>destinations</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>destination drivers</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>A destination is where a log message is sent if the filtering rules match. Similarly
            to sources, destinations consist of one or more drivers, each defining where and how
            messages are sent.</para>
        <tip>
            <para>If no drivers are defined for a destination, all messages sent to the destination
                are discarded. This is equivalent to omitting the destination from the log
                statement.</para>
        </tip>
        <para>To define a destination, add a destination statement to the syslog-ng configuration
            file using the following syntax: <indexterm>
                <primary>destinations</primary>
                <secondary>defining</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <synopsis>destination &lt;identifier&gt; { 
                destination-driver(params); destination-driver(params); ... };</synopsis>
        </para>
        <example>
            <title>A simple destination statement</title>
            <para>The following destination statement sends messages to the TCP port
                <parameter>1999</parameter> of the <parameter>10.1.2.3</parameter> host.</para>
            <synopsis>destination d_demo_tcp { tcp("10.1.2.3" port(1999)); };</synopsis>
            <para>If name resolution is configured, the hostname of the target server can be used as
                well.</para>
            <synopsis>destination d_tcp { tcp("target_host" port(1999); localport(999)); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <para>The following table lists the destination drivers available in syslog-ng.</para>
        <table id="table_destination_drivers">
            <title>Destination drivers available in syslog-ng</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary>list of</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry>Name</entry>
                        <entry>Description</entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_file">file()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Writes messages to the specified file.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_logstore"
                                >logstore()<parameter>*</parameter></link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Writes messages to the specified binary logstore file.
                            <parameter>*</parameter>Available only in syslog-ng Premium
                        Edition.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_pipe">fifo(), pipe()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Writes messages to the specified named pipe.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_program">program()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Forks and launches the specified program, and sends messages to its
                            standard input.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_sql">sql()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Sends messages into an SQL database. In addition to the standard
                            syslog-ng packages, the <parameter>sql()</parameter> destination
                            requires database-specific packages to be installed. Refer to the
                            section appropriate for your platform in <xref linkend="chapter_install"
                            />.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_syslog">syslog()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Sends messages to the specified remote host using the <link
                                linkend="concepts_message_ietfsyslog">IETF-syslog protocol</link>.
                            The IETF standard supports message transport using the UDP, TCP, and TLS
                            networking protocols.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_tcpudp">tcp() and tcp6()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Sends messages to the specified TCP port of a remote host using the
                                <link linkend="concepts_message_bsdsyslog">BSD-syslog
                            protocol</link> over IPv4 and IPv6, respectively.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_tcpudp">udp() and udp6()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Sends messages to the specified UDP port of a remote host using the
                                <link linkend="concepts_message_bsdsyslog">BSD-syslog
                            protocol</link> over IPv4 and IPv6, respectively.</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_unixstream">unix-dgram()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Sends messages to the specified unix socket in
                            <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> style (BSD).</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="configuring_destinations_unixstream">unix-stream()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Sends messages to the specified unix socket in
                            <parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> style (Linux).</entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <link linkend="reference_destination_usertty">usertty()</link>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>Sends messages to the terminal of the specified user, if the user is
                            logged in.</entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>For detailed list of driver parameters, see <xref
                linkend="reference_destinationdrivers"/>. </para>
        <section id="configuring_destinations_file">
            <title>Storing messages in plain-text files</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>file()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The file driver is one of the most important destination drivers in syslog-ng. It
                allows to output messages to the specified text file, or to a set of files. </para>
            <para>The destination filename may include macros which get expanded when the message is
                written, thus a simple <parameter>file()</parameter> driver may create several
                files. For more information on available macros see <xref linkend="reference_macros"
                />. </para>
            <para>If the expanded filename refers to a directory which does not exist, it will be
                created depending on the <parameter>create_dirs()</parameter> setting (both global
                and a per destination option).</para>
            <para>The <parameter>file()</parameter> has a single required parameter that specifies
                the filename that stores the log messages. For the list of available optional
                parameters, see <xref linkend="reference_destination_file"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration:
                file(filename options());</synopsis>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_destination_file)"/>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_destination_file_macro)"/>
            <note>
                <para>When using the <parameter>file()</parameter> destination, update the
                    configuration of your log rotation program to rotate these files. Otherwise, the
                    log files can become very large.</para>
            </note>
            <warning>
                <para>Since the state of each created file must be tracked by syslog-ng, it consumes
                    some memory for each file. If no new messages are written to a file within 60
                    seconds (controlled by the <parameter>time_reap()</parameter> global option), it
                    is closed, and its state is freed. </para>
                <para>Exploiting this, a DoS attack can be mounted against the system. If the number
                    of possible destination files and its needed memory is more than the amount
                    available on the syslog-ng server. </para>
                <para>The most suspicious macro is <parameter>$PROGRAM</parameter>, where the number
                    of possible variations is rather high. Do not use the
                    <parameter>$PROGRAM</parameter> macro in insecure environments.</para>
            </warning>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_destinations_logstore">
            <title>Storing messages in encrypted files</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>logstore</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>encrypted log files</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>logstore()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The <parameter>logstore()</parameter> driver stores log messages in binary files
                that can be encrypted, compressed, checked for integrity, and timestamped by an
                external Timestamping Authority (TSA). Otherwise, it is very similar to the
                    <parameter>file()</parameter> destination.</para>
            <para>Logstore files consist of individual chunks, every chunk can be encrypted,
                compressed, and timestamped separately. Chunks contain log message data, chunk size
                defaults to 128k (about 1MB worth of compressed logs).</para>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>logcat</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>To display the contents of a logstore file, use the <command>logcat</command>
                command supplied with syslog-ng, e.g., <command>logcat
                /var/log/messages.lgs</command>. To display the contents of encrypted log files,
                specify the private key of the certificate used to encrypt the file, e.g.,
                    <command>logcat -k private.key /var/log/messages.lgs</command>. The contents of
                the file are sent to the standard output, so it is possible to use grep and other
                tools to find particular log messages, e.g., <command>logcat /var/log/messages.lgs
                    |grep 192.168.1.1</command>.</para>
            <para>Every record that is stored in the logstore has a unique record ID. The
                    <command>logcat</command> application can quickly jump to a specified record
                using the <command>-- seek</command> option.</para>
            <!-- FIXME pelda, es rendes man page -->
            <para>For files that are in use by syslog-ng, the last chunk that is open cannot be
                read. Chunks are closed when their size reaches the limit set in the
                    <parameter>chunk_size</parameter> parameter, or when the time limit set in the
                    <parameter>chunk_time</parameter> parameter expires and no new message arrives.</para>
            <para>The syslog-ng PE application generates an SHA-1 hash for every chunk to verify the
                integrity of the chunk. The hashes of the chunks are chained together to prevent
                injecting chunks into the logstore file. The syslog-ng application can encrypt the
                logstore using the <parameter>aes128</parameter> algorithm in CBC mode; the hashing
                (HMAC) algorithm is <parameter>hmac-sha1</parameter>. Currently it is not possible
                to use other algorithms.</para>
            <warning>
                <para>If the syslog-ng Premium Edition application or the computer crashes, an
                    unclosed chunk remains at the end of the file. This chunk is marked as broken,
                    its data stays there but is not shown by <command>logcat</command>.</para>
                <!-- FIXME akkor hogy lehet megnezni? -->
            </warning>
            <para>The destination filename may include macros which get expanded when the message is
                written, thus a simple <parameter>logstore()</parameter> driver may create several
                files. For more information on available macros see <xref linkend="reference_macros"
                />. </para>
            <para>If the expanded filename refers to a directory which does not exist, it will be
                created depending on the <parameter>create_dirs()</parameter> setting (both global
                and a per destination option).</para>
            <para>The <parameter>logstore()</parameter> has a single required parameter that
                specifies the filename that stores the log messages. For the list of available
                optional parameters, see <xref linkend="reference_destination_logstore"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration:
                logstore(filename options());</synopsis>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_destination_logstore)"/>
            <note>
                <para>When using the <parameter>logstore()</parameter> destination, update the
                    configuration of your log rotation program to rotate these files. Otherwise, the
                    log files can become very large.</para>
            </note>
            <warning>
                <para>Since the state of each created file must be tracked by syslog-ng, it consumes
                    some memory for each file. If no new messages are written to a file within 60
                    seconds (controlled by the <parameter>time_reap()</parameter> global option), it
                    is closed, and its state is freed. </para>
                <para>Exploiting this, a DoS attack can be mounted against the system. If the number
                    of possible destination files and its needed memory is more than the amount
                    available on the syslog-ng server. </para>
                <para>The most suspicious macro is <parameter>$PROGRAM</parameter>, where the number
                    of possible variations is rather high. Do not use the
                    <parameter>$PROGRAM</parameter> macro in insecure environments.</para>
            </warning>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_destinations_pipe">
            <title>Sending messages to named pipes</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>pipe()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The <parameter>pipe()</parameter> driver sends messages to a named pipe like
                    <filename>/dev/xconsole</filename>. </para>
            <para>The pipe driver has a single required parameter, specifying the filename of the
                pipe to open. The filename can include macros. For the list of available optional
                parameters, see <xref linkend="reference_destination_pipe"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration:
                pipe(filename);</synopsis>
            <warning>
                <para>As of syslog-ng Open Source Edition 3.0.2, pipes are created automatically. In
                    earlier versions, you had to create the pipe using the
                    <command>mkfifo(1)</command> command. </para>
            </warning>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_destination_pipe)"/>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_destinations_program">
            <title>Sending messages to external applications</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>program()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The <parameter>program()</parameter> driver starts an external application or
                script and sends the log messages to its standard input
                (<parameter>stdin</parameter>). </para>
            <para>The <parameter>program()</parameter> driver has a single required parameter,
                specifying a program name to start. The program is executed with the help of the
                current shell, so the command may include both file patterns and I/O redirections.
                For the list of available optional parameters, see <xref
                    linkend="reference_destination_program"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration: 
                program(command_to_run);</synopsis>
            <note>
                <para>The syslog-ng application automatically restarts the external program if it
                    exits for reliability reasons. However it is not recommended to launch programs
                    for single messages, because if the message rate is high, launching several
                    instances of an application might overload the system, resulting in Denial of
                    Service. </para>
            </note>
            <para>Note that the message format does not include the priority and facility values by
                default. To add these values, specify a template for the program destination, as
                shown in the following example.</para>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_destination_program)"/>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_destinations_sql">
            <title>Storing messages in an SQL database</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>sql()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary>database driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The <parameter>sql()</parameter> driver sends messages into an SQL database.
                Currently the Microsoft SQL (MSSQL), MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, and SQLite databases
                are supported.</para>
            <note>
                <!-- FIXME ez meg igaz? OSE? -->
                <para>In order to use the <parameter>sql()</parameter> destination, syslog-ng
                    Premium Edition must run in server mode. Typically, only the central syslog-ng
                    Premium Edition server uses the <parameter>sql()</parameter>
                    destination.<!-- FIXME link a server modera -->
                </para>
            </note>
            <para>The <parameter>sql()</parameter> driver has the following required parameters:</para>
            <!-- FIXME melyek a kotelezo parameterek? -->
            <table>
                <title>Required parameters of the sql() driver</title>
                <tgroup cols="4">
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Name</entry>
                            <entry>Type</entry>
                            <entry>Default</entry>
                            <entry>Description</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                            xpointer="element(sql_option_type)"/>
                        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                            xpointer="element(sql_option_database)"/>
                        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                            xpointer="element(sql_option_table)"/>
                        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                            xpointer="element(sql_option_columns)"/>
                        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml"
                            xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                            xpointer="element(sql_option_values)"/>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>For the list of available optional parameters, see <xref
                    linkend="reference_destination_sql"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration: 
    sql(database_type host_parameters database_parameters [options]);</synopsis>
            <warning>
                <para>The syslog-ng application requires read and write access to the SQL table,
                    otherwise it cannot verify that the destination table exists.</para>
                <para>Currently the syslog-ng application has default schemas for the different
                    databases and uses these defaults if the database schema (e.g., columns and
                    column types) is not defined in the configuration file. However, these schemas
                    will be deprecated and specifying the exact database schema will be required in
                    later versions of syslog-ng. </para>
            </warning>
            <note>
                <para>In addition to the standard syslog-ng packages, the
                    <parameter>sql()</parameter> destination requires database-specific packages to
                    be installed. These packages are automatically installed by the binary syslog-ng
                    installer.</para>
                <para>The <parameter>sql()</parameter> driver is currently not available for every
                    platform that is supported by syslog-ng. For a list of platforms that support
                    the <parameter>sql()</parameter> driver, visit <ulink
                        url="http://www.balabit.com/network-security/syslog-ng/central-syslog-server/"
                        >http://www.balabit.com/network-security/syslog-ng/central-syslog-server/</ulink>.</para>
            </note>
            <para>The <parameter>table</parameter> and <parameter>value</parameter> parameters can
                include macros to create tables and columns dynamically (see <xref
                    linkend="reference_macros"/> for details).</para>
            <warning>
                <para>When using macros in table names, note that some databases limit the maximum
                    allowed length of table names. Consult the documentation of the database for
                    details.</para>
            </warning>
            <para>Inserting the records into the database is performed by a separate thread. The
                syslog-ng application automatically performs the escaping required to insert the
                messages into the database. </para>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_destination_sql)"/>
            <section id="configuring_sql_oracle">
                <title>Using the sql() driver with an Oracle database</title>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>Oracle</primary>
                    <secondary>sql() configuration</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>The Oracle sql destination has some special aspects that are important to
                    note.</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The hostname of the database server is set in the
                                <filename>tnsnames.ora</filename> file, not in the
                            <parameter>host</parameter> parameter of the
                            <parameter>sql()</parameter> destination.</para>
                        <para>Make sure to set the Oracle-related environment variables properly, so
                            syslog-ng and the Oracle client will find the file. The following
                            variables must be set: <parameter>ORACLE_BASE</parameter>,
                                <parameter>ORACLE_HOME</parameter>, and
                            <parameter>ORACLE_SID</parameter>. See the documentation of the Oracle
                            Instant Client for details. </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>As certain database versions limit the maximum length of table names,
                            macros in the table names should be used with care.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <!-- FIXME kiszedni, ha megjavul -->
                        <para>In the current version of syslog-ng PE, the types of database columns
                            must be explicitly set for the Oracle destination. The column used to
                            store the text part of the syslog messages should be able to store
                            messages as long as the longest message permitted by syslog-ng,
                            therefore it is usually recommended to use the
                            <parameter>varchar2</parameter> or <parameter>clob</parameter> column
                            type. (The maximum length of the messages can be set using the
                                <parameter>log_msg_size()</parameter> option.) See the following
                            example for details.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xpointer="element(example_destination_sql_oracle)"/>
            </section>

            <section id="configuring_sql_mssql">
                <title>Using the sql() driver with a Microsoft SQL database</title>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>Microsoft SQL</primary>
                    <secondary>sql() configuration</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>MSSQL</primary>
                    <secondary>sql() configuration</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>The <parameter>mssql</parameter> database driver can access Microsoft SQL
                    (MSSQL) destinations. This driver has some special aspects that are important to
                    note.</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The date format used by the MSSQL database must be explicitly set in
                            the <filename>/etc/locales.conf</filename> file of the syslog-ng server.
                            See the following example for details.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>As certain database versions limit the maximum length of table names,
                            macros in the table names should be used with care.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <!-- FIXME kiszedni, ha megjavul -->
                        <para>In the current version of syslog-ng PE, the types of database columns
                            must be explicitly set for the MSSQL destination. The column used to
                            store the text part of the syslog messages should be able to store
                            messages as long as the longest message permitted by syslog-ng. The
                                <parameter>varchar</parameter> column type can store maximum 4096
                            bytes-long messages. The maximum length of the messages can be set using
                            the <parameter>log_msg_size()</parameter> option. See the following
                            example for details.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Remote access for SQL users must be explicitly enabled on the
                            Microsoft Windows host running the Microsoft SQL Server. See <xref
                                linkend="configure_mssql_server"/> for details.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xpointer="element(example_destination_sql_mssql)"/>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_destinations_syslog">
            <title>Sending messages to a remote logserver using the IETF-syslog protocol</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>syslog()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The <parameter>syslog()</parameter> driver sends messages to a remote host (e.g.,
                a syslog-ng server or relay) on the local intranet or internet using the new
                standard syslog protocol developed by IETF (see <xref
                    linkend="concepts_message_ietfsyslog"/> for details about the new protocol). The
                protocol supports sending messages using the UDP, TCP, or the encrypted TLS
                networking protocols.</para>
            <para>The required arguments of the driver are the address of the destination host
                (where messages should be sent). The transport method (networking protocol) is
                optional, syslog-ng uses the TCP protocol by default. For the list of available
                optional parameters, see <xref linkend="reference_destination_syslog"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration:
                syslog(host transport [options]);</synopsis>
            <note>
                <para>Note that the <parameter>syslog</parameter> destination driver has required
                    parameters, while the source driver defaults to the local bind address, and
                    every parameter is optional. </para>
            </note>
            <para>The <parameter>udp</parameter> transport method automatically sends multicast
                packets if a multicast destination address is specified. The
                <parameter>tcp</parameter> and <parameter>tls</parameter> methods do not support
                multicasting.</para>
            <note>
                <para>The default ports for the different transport protocols are as follows: UDP
                    &mdash; 514; TLS &mdash; 6514.</para>
                <!-- FIXME mi a syslog-TCP default portja? -->
            </note>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_destination_syslog)"/>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_destinations_tcpudp">
            <title>Sending messages to a remote logserver using the legacy BSD-syslog protocol</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>tcp()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>tcp6()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>udp()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>udp6()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The <parameter>tcp()</parameter>, <parameter>tcp6()</parameter>,
                <parameter>udp()</parameter>, and <parameter>udp6()</parameter> drivers send
                messages to another host (e.g., a syslog-ng server or relay) on the local intranet
                or internet using the UDP or TCP protocol. The <parameter>tcp6()</parameter> and
                    <parameter>udp6()</parameter> drivers use the IPv6 network protocol.</para>
            <para>All four drivers have a single required parameter specifying the destination host
                address, where messages should be sent. For the list of available optional
                parameters, see <xref linkend="reference_destination_tcpudp"/>.</para>
            <para>The <parameter>udp()</parameter> and <parameter>udp6()</parameter> drivers
                automatically send multicast packets if a multicast destination address is
                specified. The <parameter>tcp()</parameter> and <parameter>tcp6()</parameter>
                drivers do not support multicasting.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration:
                tcp(host [options]);
                udp(host [options]);
                tcp6(host [options]);
                udp6(host [options]);</synopsis>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_destination_tcpudp)"/>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_destinations_unixstream">
            <title>Sending messages to UNIX domain sockets</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>unix-stream()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>destination drivers</primary>
                <secondary><parameter>unix-dgram()</parameter> driver</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The <parameter>unix-stream()</parameter> and <parameter>unix-dgram()</parameter>
                drivers send messages to a UNIX domain socket in either
                <parameter>SOCK_STREAM</parameter> or <parameter>SOCK_DGRAM</parameter> mode. </para>
            <para>Both drivers have a single required argument specifying the name of the socket to
                connect to. For the list of available optional parameters, see <xref
                    linkend="reference_destination_unixstream"/>.</para>
            <synopsis>Declaration: 
                unix-stream(filename [options]);
                unix-dgram(filename [options]);</synopsis>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(example_destination_unixstream)"/>
        </section>
        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            xpointer="element(reference_destination_usertty)"/>


    </section>
    <section id="logpath">
        <title>Log paths</title>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>log paths</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Log paths determine what happens with the incoming log messages. Messages coming from
            the sources listed in the log statement and matching all the filters are sent to the
            listed destinations.</para>
        <para>To define a log path, add a log statement to the syslog-ng configuration file using
            the following syntax:</para>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>log paths</primary>
            <secondary>defining</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <synopsis id="log_path_synopsis">log {
    source(s1); source(s2); ... 
    optional_element(filter1|parser1|rewrite1); optional_element(filter2|parser2|rewrite2);... 
    destination(d1); destination(d2); ... 
    flags(flag1[, flag2...]);
    };</synopsis>
        <warning>
            <para>Log statements are processed in the order they appear in the configuration file.
            </para>
        </warning>
        <example id="log_statement_example">
            <title>A simple log statement</title>
            <para>The following log statement sends all messages arriving to the localhost to a
                remote server.</para>
            <synopsis>source s_localhost { tcp(ip(127.0.0.1) port(1999) ); };
destination d_tcp { tcp("10.1.2.3" port(1999); localport(999)); };
log { source(s_localhost); destination(d_tcp); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <para>All matching log statements are processed by default, so a single log message might be
            sent to the same destination several times, provided the destination is listed in
            several log statements. </para>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>log paths</primary>
            <secondary>flags</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>flags</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>This default behavior can be changed using the <parameter>flags()</parameter>
            parameter. Flags apply to individual log paths; they are not global options. The
            following flags available in syslog-ng: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>final</emphasis>: Do not send the message to any further
                    destination.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>fallback</emphasis>: Process messages that were not processed by
                    other log paths.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>catchall</emphasis>: Process every message, regardless of its
                    source.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>flow-control</emphasis>: Stop reading messages from the source if
                    the destination cannot accept them. See <xref linkend="concepts_flow_control"
                />.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            xpointer="element(example_logpath_flags)"/>
        <para>For details on the individual flags, see <xref linkend="reference_logflags"/>. The
            effect and use of the <parameter>flow-control</parameter> flag is detailed in <xref
                linkend="concepts_flow_control"/>.</para>
        <note>
            <para>Note that a message goes to <emphasis>every</emphasis> matching destination by
                default. To change this behavior, use the <parameter>final</parameter> flag. See
                    <xref linkend="reference_logflags"/> for details.</para>
        </note>
        <section id="configuring_embedded_logpaths">
            <title>Using embedded log statements</title>
            <para>Embedded log statements (see <xref linkend="concepts_embedded_logpaths"/> ) re-use
                the results of processing messages (e.g., the results of filtering or rewriting) to
                create complex log paths. Embedded log statements use the same syntax as regular log
                statements, but they cannot contain additional sources. To define embedded log
                statements, use the following syntax:</para>
            <synopsis id="log_path_synopsis_embedded">log {
    source(s1); source(s2); ... 
    
    optional_element(filter1|parser1|rewrite1); 
    optional_element(filter2|parser2|rewrite2);... 
    
    destination(d1); destination(d2); ... 
    
    flags(flag1[, flag2...]); 
    
    #embedded log statement
    log
        {
        optional_element(filter1|parser1|rewrite1); 
        optional_element(filter2|parser2|rewrite2);... 
        destination(d1); destination(d2); ...
        #another embedded log statement
        log
        {
            optional_element(filter1|parser1|rewrite1); 
            optional_element(filter2|parser2|rewrite2);... 
            destination(d1); destination(d2); ...};
        };    
        };</synopsis>
            <example id="example_logpath_embedded">
                <title>Using embedded log paths</title>
                <para>The following log path sends every message to the
                    <parameter>d_file1</parameter> and the <parameter>d_file2</parameter>
                    destinations.</para>
                <synopsis>log { source(s_localhost); destination(d_file1); destination(d_file2); };</synopsis>
                <para>The next example is equivalent with the one above, but uses an embedded log
                    statement.</para>
                <synopsis>log { source(s_localhost); destination(d_file1); 
                    log {destination(d_file2); };
};</synopsis>
                <para>The following example sends every message coming from the host
                        <parameter>192.168.1.1</parameter> into the <parameter>d_file1</parameter>
                    destination, and sends every message coming from the host
                    <parameter>192.168.1.1</parameter> and containing the string
                    <parameter>example</parameter> into the <parameter>d_file2</parameter>
                    destination.</para>
                <synopsis>log { source(s_localhost); host(192.168.1.); destination(d_file1); 
                    log {message("example"); destination(d_file2); };
};</synopsis>
                <para>The following example collects logs from multiple source groups and uses the
                        <parameter>source()</parameter> filter in the embedded log statement to
                    select messages of the <parameter>s_network</parameter> source group.</para>
                <synopsis>log { source(s_localhost); source(s_network); destination(d_file1); 
                    log {source(s_network); destination(d_file2); };
                    };</synopsis>
            </example>
        </section>
        <section id="configuring_flow_control">
            <title>Configuring flow-control</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>log paths</primary>
                <secondary>flow-control</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>flow-control</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>preventing message loss</primary>
                <see>flow-control</see>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>parameters</primary>
                <secondary>
                    <parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter>
                </secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>parameters</primary>
                <secondary>
                    <parameter>log_fifo_size()</parameter>
                </secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>parameters</primary>
                <secondary>
                    <parameter>log_iw_size()</parameter>
                </secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>parameters</primary>
                <secondary>
                    <parameter>max_connections()</parameter>
                </secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>output buffer</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>For details on how flow-control works, see <xref linkend="concepts_flow_control"
                />. The summary of the main points is as follows:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The syslog-ng application normally reads a maximum of
                            <parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter> number of messages from a
                        source.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>From TCP and unix-stream sources, syslog-ng reads a maximum of
                            <parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter> from every connection of the
                        source. The number of connections to the source is set using the
                            <parameter>max_connections()</parameter> parameter.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Every destination has an output buffer
                        (<parameter>log_fifo_size()</parameter>).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Flow-control uses a control window to determine if there is free space in
                        the output buffer for new messages. Every source has its own control window;
                            <parameter>log_iw_size()</parameter> parameter sets the size of the
                        control window.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When a source accepts multiple connections, the messages of every
                        connection use the same control window. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The output buffer must be larger than the control window of every source
                        that logs to the destination.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If the control window is full, syslog-ng stops reading messages from the
                        source until some messages are successfully sent to the destination.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If the output buffer becomes full, and neither disk-buffering nor
                        flow-control is used, messages may be lost.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <note>
                <para>If you modify the <parameter>max_connections()</parameter> or the
                        <parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter> parameter, do not forget to adjust
                    the <parameter>log_iw_size()</parameter> and
                    <parameter>log_fifo_size()</parameter> parameters accordingly.</para>
            </note>
            <example>
                <title>Sizing parameters for flow-control</title>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>log paths</primary>
                    <secondary>flow-control</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                    <primary>flow-control</primary>
                    <secondary>example</secondary>
                </indexterm>
                <para>Suppose that syslog-ng has a source that must accept up to 300 parallel
                    connections. Such situation can arise when a network source receives connections
                    from many clients, or if many applications log to the same socket. Therefore,
                    set the <parameter>max_connections()</parameter> parameter of the source to
                        <parameter>300</parameter>. However, the
                    <parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter> (default value: 10) parameter applies
                    to every connection of the source individually, while the
                        <parameter>log_iw_size()</parameter> (default value: 100) parameter applies
                    to the source. In a worst-case scenario, the destination does not accept any
                    messages, while all 300 connections send at least
                    <parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter> number of messages to the source during
                    every poll loop. Therefore, the control window must accommodate at least
                        <parameter>max_connections()</parameter>*<parameter>log_fetch_limit()</parameter>
                    messages to be able to read every incoming message of a poll loop. In the
                    current example this means that (<parameter>log_iw_size()</parameter> should be
                    greater than <parameter>300*10=3000</parameter>. If the control window is
                    smaller than this value, the control window might fill up with messages from the
                    first connections &mdash; causing syslog-ng to read only one message of the
                    last connections in every poll loop. </para>
                <para>The output buffer of the destination must accommodate at least
                        <parameter>log_iw_size()</parameter> messages, but use a greater value: in
                    the current example <parameter>3000*10=30000</parameter> messages. That way all
                    incoming messages of ten poll loops fit in the output buffer. If the output
                    buffer is full, syslog-ng does not read any messages from the source until some
                    messages are successfully sent to the destination.</para>
                <synopsis>source s_localhost { 
            tcp(ip(127.0.0.1) port(1999) max-connections(300)); };
            destination d_tcp { 
            tcp("10.1.2.3" port(1999); localport(999)); log_fifo_size(30000); };
            log { source(s_localhost); destination(d_tcp); flags(flow-control); };</synopsis>
                <para>If other sources send messages to this destination, than the output buffer
                    must be further increased. For example, if a network host with maximum
                        <parameter>100</parameter> connections also logs into the destination, than
                    increase the <parameter>log_fifo_size()</parameter> by
                    <parameter>10000</parameter>.</para>
                <synopsis>source s_localhost { 
            tcp(ip(127.0.0.1) port(1999) max-connections(300)); };
            source s_tcp { 
            tcp(ip(192.168.1.5) port(1999) max-connections(100)); };
            destination d_tcp { 
            tcp("10.1.2.3" port(1999); localport(999)); log_fifo_size(40000); };
            log { source(s_localhost); destination(d_tcp); flags(flow-control); };</synopsis>
            </example>
            <para>See also <xref linkend="parallel_connections"/>.</para>

        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="filters">
        <title>Filters</title>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>filters</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>regular expressions</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>Filters perform log routing within syslog-ng: a message passes the filter if the
            filter expression is true for the particular message. If a log statement includes
            filters, the messages are sent to the destinations only if they pass all filters of the
            log path. For example, a filter can select only the messages originating from a
            particular host. Complex filters can be created using filter functions and logical
            boolean expressions.</para>
        <para>To define a filter, add a filter statement to the syslog-ng configuration file using
            the following syntax:</para>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>filters</primary>
            <secondary>defining</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <synopsis>filter &lt;identifier&gt; { expression; };</synopsis>
        <para>The expression may contain the following elements: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>The functions listed in <xref linkend="filterfunc"/>. Some of the functions
                    accept extended regular expressions as parameters.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Parentheses</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>The boolean operators <parameter>and</parameter>, <parameter>or</parameter>,
                        <parameter>not</parameter></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <example>
            <title>A simple filter statement</title>
            <para>The following filter statement selects the messages that contain the word
                    <parameter>deny</parameter> and come from the host
                <parameter>example</parameter>.</para>
            <synopsis>filter demo_filter { host("example") and match("deny"); };</synopsis>
            <para>For the filter to have effect, include it in a log statement:</para>
            <synopsis>log demo_filteredlog{
        source(s1); source(s2); 
        filter(demo_filter);
        destination(d1); destination(d2); };</synopsis>
            <para>The <parameter>host()</parameter>, <parameter>match()</parameter>, and
                    <parameter>program()</parameter> filter functions accept regular expressions as
                parameters.</para>
            <synopsis>filter demo_regexp_filter { host("system.*1") and match("deny"); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <para>To limit the scope of a filter function, add the <parameter>value()</parameter> option
            and set its scope with a macro. For example, to limit the scope of the
                <parameter>match()</parameter> filter to the text part of the message, use:</para>
        <synopsis>match("keyword" value("MESSAGE"))</synopsis>
        <para>The <parameter>value()</parameter> parameter accepts both built-in macros and
            user-defined ones created with a parser. For details on macros and parsers, see <xref
                linkend="configuring_macros"/> and <xref linkend="configuring_parsers"/>.</para>
        <note>
            <para>When a log statement includes multiple filter statements, syslog-ng sends a
                message to the destination only if all filters are true for the message. In other
                words, the filters are connected with the logical <parameter>AND</parameter>
                operator. In the following example, no message arrives to the destination, because
                the filters are exclusive (the hostname of a client cannot be
                <parameter>example1</parameter> and <parameter>example2</parameter> at the same
                time):</para>
            <synopsis>filter demo_filter1 { host("example1"); };
                filter demo_filter2 { host("example2"); };

                log demo_filteredlog{
                source(s1); source(s2); 
                filter(demo_filter1); filter(demo_filter2);
                destination(d1); destination(d2); };</synopsis>
            <para>To select the messages that come from either host <parameter>example1</parameter>
                or <parameter>example2</parameter>, use a single filter expression:</para>
            <synopsis>filter demo_filter { host("example1") or host("example2"); };
                
                log demo_filteredlog{
                source(s1); source(s2); 
                filter(demo_filter);
                destination(d1); destination(d2); };</synopsis>
        </note>

        <indexterm>
            <primary>regular expressions</primary>
            <secondary>case-insensitive</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>regular expressions</primary>
            <secondary>escaping</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>In the extended regular expressions, the characters <parameter>()[].*?+^$</parameter>
            are used as special symbols. Therefore, these characters have to be preceded with a
            backslash (<parameter>\</parameter>) if they are meant literally. For example, the
                <parameter>\$40</parameter> expression matches the <parameter>$40</parameter>
            string. Backslashes have to be escaped as well if they are meant literally. For example,
            the <parameter>\\d</parameter> expression matches the <parameter>\d</parameter> string.</para>
        <para>By default, all regular expressions are case sensitive. To disable the case
            sensitivity of the expression, add the <parameter>flags(ignore-case)</parameter> option
            to the regular expression.</para>
        <synopsis>filter demo_regexp_insensitive { host("system" flags(ignore-case)); };</synopsis>
        <note>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>filters</primary>
                <secondary>wildcards</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>In regular expressions, the asterisk (<parameter>*</parameter>) character means 0,
                1 or any number of the previous expression. For example, in the
                <parameter>f*ilter</parameter> expression the asterisk means 0 or more f letters.
                This expression matches for the following strings: <parameter>ilter</parameter>,
                    <parameter>filter</parameter>, <parameter>ffilter</parameter>, etc. To achieve
                the wildcard functionality commonly represented by the asterisk character in other
                applications, use <parameter>.*</parameter> in your expressions, e.g.,
                    <parameter>f.*ilter</parameter>.</para>
        </note>
        <para>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>filters</primary>
                <secondary>facility and priority (level) ranges</secondary>
            </indexterm> The <parameter>level()</parameter> filter can select messages corresponding
            to a single importance level, or a level-range. To select messages of a specific level,
            use the name of the level as a filter parameter, e.g., use the following to select
            warning messages:</para>
        <synopsis>level(warning)</synopsis>
        <para>To select a range of levels, include the beginning and the ending level in the filter,
            separated with two dots (<parameter>..</parameter>). For example, to select every
            message of error or higher level, use the following filter:</para>
        <synopsis>level(err..emerg)</synopsis>
        <para>Similarly, messages sent by a range of facilities can also be selected. Note that this
            is only possible when using the name of the facilities. It is not possible to select
            ranges the numerical codes of the facilities.</para>
        <synopsis>facility(local0..local5)</synopsis>
        <para>For a complete list of the available levels and facilities, see <xref
                linkend="reference_filters"/>. </para>
        <para>For a complete description on the above functions, see <xref
                linkend="reference_filters"/>. </para>
        <section id="regular_expressions">
            <title>Optimizing regular expressions in filters</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>filters</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>regular expressions</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>optimizing syslog-ng performance</primary>
                <secondary>regular expressions</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Some filter functions accept regular expressions as parameters. But evaluating
                general regular expressions puts a high load on the CPU, which can cause problems
                when the message traffic is very high. Often the regular expression can be replaced
                with simple filter functions and logical operators. Using simple filters and logical
                operators, the same effect can be achieved at a much lower CPU load.</para>
            <example>
                <title>Optimizing regular expressions in filters</title>
                <para>Suppose you need a filter that matches the following error message logged by
                    the <parameter>xntpd</parameter> NTP daemon:</para>
                <synopsis>xntpd[1567]: time error -1159.777379 is too large (set clock manually);</synopsis>
                <para>The following filter uses regular expressions and matches every instance and
                    variant of this message.</para>
                <synopsis>filter f_demo_regexp {
    program("demo_program") and
    match("time error .* is too large .* set clock manually"); };</synopsis>
                <para>Segmenting the <parameter>match()</parameter> part of this filter into
                    separate <parameter>match()</parameter> functions greatly improves the
                    performance of the filter. </para>
                <synopsis>filter f_demo_optimized_regexp {
    program("demo_program") and
    match("time error") and 
    match("is too large") and 
    match("set clock manually"); };</synopsis>
            </example>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="configuring_macros">
        <!-- FIXME a template+makro, parser es rewrite sectionoket egy kozos sectionbe kellene tenni, es az elejen 
        leirni, hogy hogyan viszonyulnak egymashoz: vannak a makrok, parserrel lehet az uzeneteket sajat makrokra bontani, 
        a rewrite meg ezeket tudja atirni-->
        <title>Templates and macros</title>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>templates</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>The syslog-ng application allows you to define message templates, and reference them
            from every object that can use a template. Templates can be used to create standard
            message formats or filenames. Templates can reference one or more macros (e.g., date,
            the hostname, etc.). See <xref linkend="reference_macros"/> for a list of macros
            available in the Linux/Unix versions of syslog-ng, and <xref
                linkend="windows_message_format"/> for the macros of the syslog-ng Agent for Windows
            application. Fields from the structured data (SD) part of messages using the new
            IETF-syslog standard can also be used as macros.</para>
        <para>Template objects have a single option called <parameter>template_escape</parameter>,
            which is disabled by default (<parameter>template_escape(no)</parameter>). This behavior
            is useful when the messages are passed to an application that cannot handle escaped
            characters properly. Enabling template escaping
            (<parameter>template_escape(yes)</parameter>) causes syslog-ng to escape the
                <parameter>'</parameter> and <parameter>"</parameter> characters from the messages.</para>
        <note>
            <para>In versions 2.1 and earlier, the <parameter>template_escape()</parameter> option
                was enabled by default.</para>
        </note>
        <para>Macros can be included by prefixing the macro name with a <parameter>$</parameter>
            sign, just like in Bourne compatible shells. Regarding braces around macro names, the
            following two formats are equivalent <parameter>"$MSG"</parameter> and
                <parameter>"${MSG}"</parameter>. </para>
        <para>Default values for macros can also be specified by appending the
            <parameter>:-</parameter> characters and the default value to the macro, e.g.,</para>
        <synopsis>${HOST:-default_hostname}</synopsis>
        <note>
            <para>See <xref linkend="windows_message_format"/> for the macros available in the
                syslog-ng Agent for Windows application.</para>
        </note>
        <para id="date_macros">The macros related to the date of the message (e.g.:
                <parameter>ISODATE</parameter>, <parameter>HOUR</parameter>, etc.) have two further
            versions each: one with the <parameter>S_</parameter> and one with the
            <parameter>R_</parameter> prefix (e.g.: <parameter>S_DATE</parameter> and
                <parameter>R_DATE</parameter> ). The <parameter>S_DATE</parameter> macro represents
            the date found in the log message, i.e. when the message was sent by the original
            application. <parameter>R_DATE</parameter> is the date when syslog has received the
            message.</para>
        <para><parameter>DATE</parameter> equals either <parameter>S_DATE</parameter> or
                <parameter>R_DATE</parameter>, depending on the global option set in the now
            deprecated <parameter>use_time_recvd()</parameter> parameter (see <xref
                linkend="reference_options"/>). </para>
        <warning>
            <para>The hostname-related macros (<parameter>FULLHOST</parameter>,
                    <parameter>FULLHOST_FROM</parameter>, <parameter>HOST</parameter>, and
                    <parameter>HOST_FROM</parameter>) do not have any effect if the <link
                    linkend="source_commonoption_keep_hostname">
                    <parameter>keep_hostname()</parameter>
                </link> option is disabled.</para>
        </warning>
        <para>By default, syslog-ng sends messages using the following template: <parameter>$ISODATE
                $HOST $MSGHDR$MSG\n</parameter>. (The <parameter>$MSGHDR$MSG</parameter> part is
            written together because the <parameter>$MSGHDR</parameter> macro includes a trailing
            whitespace.)</para>
        <note>
            <para>Earlier versions of syslog-ng used templates and scripts to send log messages into
                SQL databases. Starting from version 2.1, syslog-ng natively supports direct
                database access using the <parameter>sql()</parameter> destination. See <xref
                    linkend="reference_destination_sql"/> for details.</para>
        </note>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>templates</primary>
            <secondary>defining</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <example>
            <title>Using templates</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>templates</primary>
                <secondary>example</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>The following template (<parameter>t_demo_filetemplate</parameter>) adds the date
                of the message and the name of the host sending the message to the beginning of the
                message text. The template is then used in a file destination: messages sent to this
                destination (<parameter>d_file</parameter>) will use the message format defined in
                the template. </para>
            <synopsis>template t_demo_filetemplate { 
             template("$ISODATE $HOST $MSG\n"); template_escape(no); };          
destination d_file { 
             file("/var/log/messages" template(t_demo_filetemplate)); };</synopsis>
            <para>Templates can also be used inline, if they are used only at a single location. The
                following destination is equivalent with the previous example: </para>
            <synopsis>destination d_file {
                file ("/var/log/messages"
                        template("$ISODATE $HOST $MSG\n") template_escape(no) ); 
                };
            </synopsis>
        </example>
        <!-- <example>
            <title>Feeding messages into an SQL database</title>
            <para>In order to record the log messages in a database, the messages have to be
                formatted in a way recognized by the database application. This can be accomplished
                using templates and macros. The following template creates an SQL
                <parameter>INSERT</parameter> command formatted to fit a database that stores the
                hostname, priority, date, application name, and message parts of the log messages in
                separate fields. </para>
            <synopsis>
template t_sql { 
    template("INSERT INTO logs (host, pri, datetime, program, msg) 
    VALUES (
      '$HOST', '$PRI', '$YEAR-$MONTH-$DAY $HOUR:$MIN:$SEC', '$PROGRAM', '$MSG');\n")
    };</synopsis>
            <para>The Premium Edition of syslog-ng natively supports logging into a database. See
                    <xref linkend="reference_destination_sql"/> for details.
                </para>
        </example>-->
    </section>
    <section id="configuring_parsers">
        <title>Parsing messages</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>parsers</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>message parsing</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>parsing messages</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>segmenting messages</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>splitting messages</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>The syslog-ng application can separate parts of log messages (i.e., the contents of
            the $MSG macro) to named fields (columns). These fields act as user-defined macros that
            can be referenced in message templates, file- and tablenames, etc. </para>
        <para>Parsers are similar to filters: they must be defined in the syslog-ng configuration
            file and used in the log statement.</para>
        <!-- FIXME parsert/rewriteot is lehet inline definialni? -->
        <note>
            <para>The order of filters, rewriting rules, and parsers in the log statement is
                important, as they are processed sequentially.
                <!-- FIXME bovebben, peldaval, filterekhez/rewrite sectionbe is -->
            </para>
        </note>
        <para>To create a parser, define the columns of the message, the delimiter or separator
            characters, and optionally the characters that are used to escape the delimiter
            characters (quote-pairs). For the list of parser parameters, see <xref
                linkend="reference_parsers"/>.</para>
        <synopsis>Declaration:
            parser parser_name {
            csv-parser(column1, column2, ...)
            delimiters()
            quote-pairs()
            };</synopsis>
        <para>Column names work like macros. Always use a prefix to identify the columns of the
            parsers, e.g., <parameter>MYPARSER1.COLUMN1, MYPARSER2.COLUMN2</parameter>, etc. Column
            names starting with a dot (e.g., <parameter>.HOST</parameter>) are reserved for use by
            syslog-ng. </para>
        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            xpointer="element(example_parser)"/>
        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            xpointer="element(example_parser_apache)"/>

        <para>Multiple parsers can be used to split a part of an already parsed message into further
            segments.</para>
        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            xpointer="element(example_parser_multiple)"/>
    </section>
    <section id="configuring_pattern_databases">
        <title>Classifying messages</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>parsers</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>message parsing</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>parsing messages</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>pattern database</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>classifying messages</primary>
            <secondary>configuration</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>message classification</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>To classify messages using a pattern database, include a
            <parameter>db_parser()</parameter> statement in your syslog-ng configuration file using
            the following syntax:</para>
        <synopsis>Declaration:
            parser &lt;identifier&gt; {db_parser(file("&lt;database_filename&gt;"));};</synopsis>
        <example>
            <title>Defining pattern databases</title>
            <para>The following statement uses the database located at
                    <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/var/db/patterndb.xml</filename>.</para>
            <synopsis>parser pattern_db {
            db_parser(
                file("/opt/syslog-ng/var/db/patterndb.xml")
            );
            };</synopsis>
            <para>To apply the patterns on the incoming messages, include the parser in a log
                statement:</para>
            <synopsis>log { 
            source(s_all);
            parser(pattern_db);            
            destination( di_messages_class);
            };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <note>
            <para>The default location of the pattern database file is
                    <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/var/run/patterndb.xml</filename>. The
                <parameter>file</parameter> option of the <parameter>db-parser</parameter> statement
                can be used to specify a different file, thus different db-parser statements can use
                different pattern databases. Later versions of syslog-ng will be able to dynamically
                generate a main database from separate pattern database files.</para>
        </note>
        <para>Note that using the parser in a log statement only performs the classification, but
            does not automatically do anything with the results of the classification. </para>
        <example>
            <title>Using classification results</title>
            <para>The following destination separates the log messages into different files based on
                the class assigned to the pattern that matches the message (e.g., Violation and
                Security type messages are stored in a separate file), and also adds the ID of the
                matching rule to the message: </para>
            <synopsis>destination di_messages_class {
        file("/var/log/messages-${.classifier.class}"       
        template("${.classifier.rule_id};${S_UNIXTIME};${SOURCEIP};${HOST};${PROGRAM};${PID};${MSG}\n")
        template_escape(no)
    );
};</synopsis>
        </example>
        <para>Sample pattern databases are available at the BalaBit Download page <ulink
                url="http://www.balabit.com/network-security/syslog-ng/log-server-appliance/"
                >http://www.balabit.com/network-security/syslog-ng/log-server-appliance/</ulink>.
            Alternatively, you can create your own pattern database as well. See <xref
                linkend="reference_patterndb_schemes"/> for details.</para>
        <!-- FIXME link -->
        <section id="patterndb-filters">
            <title>Using parser results in filters and templates</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>pattern database</primary>
                <secondary>using the results</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>message filtering</primary>
                <secondary>using parsers</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>parsing messages</primary>
                <secondary>filtering parsed messages</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                xpointer="element(patterndb-filtering)/*"/>
        </section>
    </section>

    <section id="configuring_rewrite">
        <title>Rewriting messages</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>rewrite rules</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>rewriting messages</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>sedding messages</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>replacing message text</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>The syslog-ng application can rewrite parts of log
            messages<!--( i.e., the contents of
                the $MSG macro)-->: it can search
            and replace text, and also set a specific field to a specified value. Rewriting messages
            is often used in conjunction with message parsing <xref linkend="configuring_parsers"/>.</para>
        <para>Rewrite rules are similar to filters: they must be defined in the syslog-ng
            configuration file and used in the log statement.</para>
        <!-- FIXME parsert/rewriteot is lehet inline definialni? -->
        <note>
            <para>The order of filters, rewriting rules, and parsers in the log statement is
                important, as they are processed sequentially.
                <!-- FIXME bovebben, peldaval, filterekhez/rewrite sectionbe is -->
            </para>
        </note>
        <para>To create replace a part of the log message, define the string or regular expression
            to replace, the string to replace the original text (macros can be used as well), and
            the field of the message that the rewrite rule should process. Substitution rules can
            operate on any value available via macros, e.g., HOST, MESSAGE, PROGRAM, or any
            user-defined macros created using parsers (see <xref linkend="reference_parsers"/> for
            details.). Substitution rules use the following syntax:</para>
        <synopsis>Declaration:
            rewrite &lt;name_of_the_rule&gt;
                {subst("&lt;string or regular expression to find&gt;", "&lt;replacement string&gt;", value(&lt;field name&gt;), flags());};</synopsis>
        <para>A single substitution rule can include multiple substitutions that are applied
            sequentially to the message. Note that rewriting rules must be included in the log
            statement to have any effect.</para>
        <tip>
            <!-- FIXME ez le van irva valahol mashol is, ill. le kellene legyen -->
            <para>For case-insensitive searches, add the <parameter>flags(ignore-case)</parameter>
                option; to replace every occurrence of the string, add
                <parameter>flags(global)</parameter> option.</para>
        </tip>
        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            xpointer="element(example_rewrite_subst)"/>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>setting message fields</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>To set a field of the message to a specific value, define the string to include in the
            message, and the field where it should be included. Setting a field can operate on any
            value available via macros, e.g., HOST, MESSAGE, PROGRAM, or any user-defined macros
            created using parsers (see <xref linkend="reference_parsers"/> for details.). Note that
            this operation completely replaces any previous value of that field. Use the following
            syntax:</para>
        <synopsis>Declaration:
            rewrite &lt;name_of_the_rule&gt;
                {set("&lt;string to include&gt;", value(&lt;field name&gt;));};</synopsis>
        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            xpointer="element(example_rewrite_set)"/>
    </section>



    <section id="options">
        <title>Configuring global syslog-ng options</title>
        <indexterm significance="preferred">
            <primary>global options</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para id="options_para1">The syslog-ng application has a number of global options governing
            DNS usage, the timestamp format used, and other general points. Each option may have
            parameters, similarly to driver specifications. To set global options, add an option
            statement to the syslog-ng configuration file using the following syntax:</para>
        <synopsis id="options_synopsis">options { option1(params); option2(params); ... };</synopsis>
        <example>
            <title>Using global options</title>
            <para>To disable domain name resolving, add the following line to the syslog-ng
                configuration file:</para>
            <synopsis>options { use_dns(no); };</synopsis>
        </example>
        <para>For a detailed list of the available options, see <xref linkend="reference_options"/>.
            See <xref linkend="chapter_examples"/> for important global options and recommendations
            on their use.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="configuring_diskbuffer">
        <title>Enabling disk-based buffering</title>
        <para>To enable disk-based buffering, use the <parameter>log_disk_fifo_size()</parameter>
            parameter to set the size of the disk buffer in bytes. Note that this value applies to
            every destination separately; every destination will have its own diskbuffer file, even
            if the parameter is set as a global option. For details on how disk-based buffering
            works, see <xref linkend="concepts_diskbuffer"/>. Disk buffers can be used with
                <parameter>tcp()</parameter>, <parameter>tcp6()</parameter>,
            <parameter>syslog()</parameter> (when using the <parameter>tcp</parameter> or
                <parameter>tls</parameter> transport methods), and <parameter>sql()</parameter>
            destinations. The number of messages that the disk buffer can store depends on the size
            (length) of the actual messages. The maximum length of a message is limited by the
                <parameter>log_msg_size()</parameter> parameter, which is 8192 bytes by default. </para>
        <para id="diskbuffer_location"> The disk buffer is located under
                <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/var/</filename> on every platform.</para>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>disk buffer</primary>
            <secondary>location of</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <xi:include href="chapter_reference.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
            xpointer="element(example_diskbuffer)"/>
    </section>


    <section id="tls_serverauth">
        <title>Encrypting log messages with TLS</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>TLS</primary>
            <secondary>configuring</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>authentication</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>encrypting log messages</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>This section describes how to configure TLS encryption in syslog-ng. For the concepts
            of using TLS in syslog-ng, see <xref linkend="concepts_tls"/>.</para>
        <para>Create an X.509 certificate for the syslog-ng server.</para>
        <note id="cert_common_name">
            <para>The <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter (or the <parameter>Common
                    Name</parameter> parameter if the <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter>
                parameter is empty) of the server's certificate must contain the hostname or the IP
                address (as resolved from the syslog-ng clients and relays) of the server (e.g.,
                    <parameter>syslog-ng.example.com</parameter>).</para>
            <para>Alternatively, the <parameter>Common Name</parameter> or the
                    <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter can contain a generic
                hostname, e.g., <parameter>*.example.com</parameter>.</para>
            <para>Note that if the <parameter>Common Name</parameter> of the certificate contains a
                generic hostname, do not specify a specific hostname or an IP address in the
                    <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter.</para>
        </note>
        <para>Complete the following steps on every syslog-ng client host. Examples are provided
            using both the legacy BSD-syslog protocol (using the <parameter>tcp()</parameter>
            driver) and the new IETF-syslog protocol standard (using the
            <parameter>syslog()</parameter> driver):</para>
        <!-- FIXME peldascenario a commonnevrr/altnevtre -->
        <procedure>
            <title>Configuring TLS on the syslog-ng clients</title>
            <step>
                <para>Copy the CA certificate (e.g., <filename>cacert.pem</filename>) of the
                    Certificate Authority that issued the certificate of the syslog-ng server to the
                    syslog-ng client hosts, for example into the
                        <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d</filename> directory. </para>
                <para>Issue the following command on the certificate: <command>openssl x509 -noout
                        -hash -in cacert.pem</command> The result is a hash (e.g.,
                        <parameter>6d2962a8</parameter>), a series of alphanumeric characters based
                    on the Distinguished Name of the certificate. </para>
                <para>Issue the following command to create a symbolic link to the certificate that
                    uses the hash returned by the previous command and the <parameter>.0</parameter>
                    suffix. </para>
                <para>
                    <command>ln -s cacert.pem 6d2962a8.0</command>
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Add a destination statement to the syslog-ng configuration file that uses the
                        <parameter>tls( ca_dir(path_to_ca_directory) )</parameter> option and
                    specify the directory using the CA certificate. The destination must use the
                        <parameter>tcp()</parameter> or <parameter>tcpv6()</parameter> destination
                    driver, and the IP address and port parameters of the driver must point to the
                    syslog-ng server. </para>
                <example>
                    <title>A destination statement using TLS</title>
                    <para>The following destination encrypts the log messages using TLS and sends
                        them to the <parameter>6514/TCP</parameter> port of the syslog-ng server
                        having the <parameter>10.1.2.3</parameter> IP address. </para>
                    <synopsis>destination demo_tls_destination {
                tcp("10.1.2.3" port(6514) 
                    tls( ca_dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d")) ); };</synopsis>
                    <para>A similar statement using the IETF-syslog protocol and thus the
                            <parameter>syslog()</parameter> driver:</para>
                    <synopsis>destination demo_tls_syslog_destination { syslog("10.1.2.3" port(6514)
                        transport("tls")
                        port(3214)
                        tls(ca_dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d")) ); 
};</synopsis>
                </example>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Include the destination created in Step 2 in a log statement. </para>
                <warning>
                    <para>The encrypted connection between the server and the client fails if the
                            <parameter>Common Name</parameter> or the
                        <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter of the server certificate
                        does not contain the hostname or the IP address (as resolved from the
                        syslog-ng clients and relays) of the server.</para>
                    <para>Do not forget to update the certificate files when they expire.</para>
                </warning>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>Complete the following steps on the syslog-ng server:</para>
        <procedure>
            <title>Configuring TLS on the syslog-ng server</title>
            <step>
                <para>Copy the certificate (e.g., <filename>syslog-ng.cert</filename>) of the
                    syslog-ng server to the syslog-ng server host, for example into the
                        <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d</filename> directory. The
                    certificate must be a valid X.509 certificate in PEM format.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Copy the private key (e.g., <filename>syslog-ng.key</filename>) matching the
                    certificate of the syslog-ng server to the syslog-ng server host, for example
                    into the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d</filename> directory. The
                    key must be in PEM format, and must not be password-protected.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Add a source statement to the syslog-ng configuration file that uses the
                        <parameter>tls( key_file(key_file_fullpathname)
                        cert_file(cert_file_fullpathname) )</parameter> option and specify the key
                    and certificate files. The source must use the source driver
                    (<parameter>tcp()</parameter> or <parameter>tcpv6()</parameter>) matching the
                    destination driver used by the syslog-ng client. </para>
                <example>
                    <title>A source statement using TLS</title>
                    <para>The following source receives log messages encrypted using TLS, arriving
                        to the <parameter>1999/TCP</parameter> port of any interface of the
                        syslog-ng server. </para>
                    <synopsis>source demo_tls_source {
           tcp(ip(0.0.0.0) port(1999) 
               tls( key_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/syslog-ng.key") 
                    cert_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/syslog-ng.cert")) ); };</synopsis>
                    <para>A similar source for receiving messages using the IETF-syslog protocol:</para>
                    <synopsis>source demo_tls_syslog_source {                    
                    syslog(ip(0.0.0.0) port(1999)
                    transport("tls")
                    tls( key_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/syslog-ng.key") 
                    cert_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/syslog-ng.cert")) ); };</synopsis>
                </example>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Disable mutual authentication for the source by setting the following TLS
                    option in the source statement: <parameter>tls(
                    peer_verify(optional-untrusted);</parameter></para>
                <para>To configure mutual authentication, see <xref linkend="tls_mutualauth"/>.</para>
                <example>
                    <title>Disabling mutual authentication</title>
                    <para>The following source receives log messages encrypted using TLS, arriving
                        to the <parameter>1999/TCP</parameter> port of any interface of the
                        syslog-ng server. The identity of the syslog-ng client is not verified.</para>
                    <synopsis>source demo_tls_source {
           tcp(ip(0.0.0.0) port(1999) 
               tls( key_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/syslog-ng.key") 
                    cert_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/syslog-ng.cert") 
                    peer_verify(optional-untrusted))  ); };</synopsis>
                    <para>A similar source for receiving messages using the IETF-syslog protocol:</para>
                    <synopsis>source demo_tls_syslog_source {                    
                        syslog(ip(0.0.0.0) port(1999)
                        transport("tls")
                        tls( key_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/syslog-ng.key") 
                        cert_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/syslog-ng.cert") 
                        peer_verify(optional-untrusted))  ); };</synopsis>
                </example>
                <warning>
                    <para>Do not forget to update the certificate and key files when they
                    expire.</para>
                </warning>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>For the details of the available <parameter>tls()</parameter> options, see <xref
                linkend="tlsoptions"/>. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="tls_mutualauth">
        <title>Mutual authentication using TLS</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>TLS</primary>
            <secondary>configuring</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>mutual authentication</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>This section describes how to configure mutual authentication between the syslog-ng
            server and the client. Configuring mutual authentication is similar to configuring TLS
            (see <xref linkend="tls_serverauth"/>), but the server verifies the identity of the
            client as well. Therefore, each client must have a certificate, and the server must have
            the certificate of the CA that issued the certificate of the clients. For the concepts
            of using TLS in syslog-ng, see <xref linkend="concepts_tls"/>.</para>

        <para>Complete the following steps on every syslog-ng client host. Examples are provided
            using both the legacy BSD-syslog protocol (using the <parameter>tcp()</parameter>
            driver) and the new IETF-syslog protocol standard (using the
            <parameter>syslog()</parameter> driver):</para>
        <procedure>
            <title>Configuring TLS on the syslog-ng clients</title>
            <step>
                <para>Create an X.509 certificate for the syslog-ng client.
                    <!--The
                        <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter (or the <parameter>Common
                        Name</parameter> parameter if the <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter>
                    parameter is empty) must contain the hostname or the IP address (as resolved
                    from the syslog-ng clients and relays) of the client.--></para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Copy the certificate (e.g., <filename>client_cert.pem</filename>) and the
                    matching private key (e.g., <filename>client.key</filename>) to the syslog-ng
                    client host, for example into the
                    <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d</filename> directory. The
                    certificate must be a valid X.509 certificate in PEM format and must not be
                    password-protected.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Copy the CA certificate of the Certificate Authority (e.g.,
                        <filename>cacert.pem</filename>) that issued the certificate of the
                    syslog-ng server to the syslog-ng client hosts, for example into the
                        <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d</filename> directory.</para>
                <para>Issue the following command on the certificate: <command>openssl x509 -noout
                        -hash -in cacert.pem</command> The result is a hash (e.g.,
                        <parameter>6d2962a8</parameter>), a series of alphanumeric characters based
                    on the Distinguished Name of the certificate. </para>
                <para>Issue the following command to create a symbolic link to the certificate that
                    uses the hash returned by the previous command and the <parameter>.0</parameter>
                    suffix. </para>
                <para>
                    <command>ln -s cacert.pem 6d2962a8.0</command>
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Add a destination statement to the syslog-ng configuration file that uses the
                        <parameter>tls( ca_dir(path_to_ca_directory) )</parameter> option and
                    specify the directory using the CA certificate. The destination must use the
                        <parameter>tcp()</parameter> or <parameter>tcpv6()</parameter> destination
                    driver, and the IP address and port parameters of the driver must point to the
                    syslog-ng server. Include the client's certificate and private key in the
                        <parameter>tls()</parameter> options.</para>
                <example>
                    <title>A destination statement using mutual authentication</title>
                    <para>The following destination encrypts the log messages using TLS and sends
                        them to the <parameter>1999/TCP</parameter> port of the syslog-ng server
                        having the <parameter>10.1.2.3</parameter> IP address. The private key and
                        the certificate file authenticating the client is also specified.</para>
                    <synopsis>destination demo_tls_destination {
    tcp("10.1.2.3" port(1999) 
        tls( ca_dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d") 
             key_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/client.key")
             cert_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/client_cert.pem")) ); };</synopsis>
                    <synopsis>destination demo_tls_syslog_destination {
    syslog("10.1.2.3" port(1999) 
        transport("tls")
            tls( ca_dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d")
                 key_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/client.key")
                 cert_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/client_cert.pem")) ); };</synopsis>
                </example>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Include the destination created in Step 2 in a log statement. </para>
                <warning>
                    <para>The encrypted connection between the server and the client fails if the
                            <parameter>Common Name</parameter> or the
                        <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter of the server certificate
                        does not the hostname or the IP address (as resolved from the syslog-ng
                        clients and relays) of the server.</para>
                    <para>Do not forget to update the certificate files when they expire.</para>
                </warning>
            </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>Complete the following steps on the syslog-ng server:</para>
        <procedure>
            <title>Configuring TLS on the syslog-ng server</title>
            <step>
                <para>Copy the certificate (e.g., <filename>syslog-ng.cert</filename>) of the
                    syslog-ng server to the syslog-ng server host, for example into the
                        <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d</filename> directory. The
                    certificate must be a valid X.509 certificate in PEM format.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Copy the CA certificate (e.g., <filename>cacert.pem</filename>) of the
                    Certificate Authority that issued the certificate of the syslog-ng clients to
                    the syslog-ng server, for example into the
                        <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d</filename> directory. </para>
                <para>Issue the following command on the certificate: <command>openssl x509 -noout
                        -hash -in cacert.pem</command> The result is a hash (e.g.,
                        <parameter>6d2962a8</parameter>), a series of alphanumeric characters based
                    on the Distinguished Name of the certificate. </para>
                <para>Issue the following command to create a symbolic link to the certificate that
                    uses the hash returned by the previous command and the <parameter>.0</parameter>
                    suffix. </para>
                <para>
                    <command>ln -s cacert.pem 6d2962a8.0</command>
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Copy the private key (e.g., <filename>syslog-ng.key</filename>) matching the
                    certificate of the syslog-ng server to the syslog-ng server host, for example
                    into the <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d</filename> directory. The
                    key must be in PEM format, and must not be password-protected.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Add a source statement to the syslog-ng configuration file that uses the
                        <parameter>tls( key_file(key_file_fullpathname)
                        cert_file(cert_file_fullpathname) )</parameter> option and specify the key
                    and certificate files. The source must use the source driver
                    (<parameter>tcp()</parameter> or <parameter>tcpv6()</parameter>) matching the
                    destination driver used by the syslog-ng client. Also specify the directory
                    storing the certificate of the CA that issued the client's certificate.</para>
                <example>
                    <title>A source statement using TLS</title>
                    <para>The following source receives log messages encrypted using TLS, arriving
                        to the <parameter>1999/TCP</parameter> port of any interface of the
                        syslog-ng server. </para>
                    <synopsis>source demo_tls_source {
           tcp(ip(0.0.0.0) port(1999) 
               tls( key_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/syslog-ng.key") 
                    cert_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/syslog-ng.cert") 
                    ca_dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d")) ); };</synopsis>
                    <para>A similar source for receiving messages using the IETF-syslog protocol:</para>
                    <synopsis>source demo_tls_syslog_source {                    
                        syslog(ip(0.0.0.0) port(1999)
                        transport("tls")
                        tls( key_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/key.d/syslog-ng.key")
                        cert_file("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/cert.d/syslog-ng.cert") 
                        ca_dir("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/syslog-ng/ca.d")) ); };</synopsis>
                </example>
                <warning>
                    <!--<para>The encrypted connection between the server and the client fails if the
                            <parameter>Common Name</parameter> or the
                        <parameter>subject_alt_name</parameter> parameter of the client certificate
                        does not the hostname or the IP address (as resolved from the syslog-ng
                        clients and relays) of the server.</para>-->
                    <para>Do not forget to update the certificate and key files when they
                    expire.</para>
                </warning>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>For the details of the available <parameter>tls()</parameter> options, see <xref
                linkend="tlsoptions"/>. </para>
    </section>

    <section id="configure_clients">
        <title>Configuring syslog-ng clients</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>syslog-ng clients</primary>
            <secondary>configuring</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>To configure syslog-ng on a client host, complete the following steps:</para>
        <procedure>
            <title>Configuring syslog-ng on client hosts</title>
            <step>
                <para>Install the syslog-ng application on the host. See <xref
                        linkend="chapter_install"/> for details installing syslog-ng on specific
                    operating systems.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Configure the local sources that collect the log messages of the host.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create a network destination that points directly to the syslog-ng server, or
                    to a local relay.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create a log statement connecting the local sources to the syslog-ng server or
                    relay.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>If the logs will also be stored locally on the host, create local file
                    destinations.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create a log statement connecting the local sources to the file
                destination.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Set filters and options (e.g., TLS encryption) as necessary.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <example id="example_clientconfig">
            <title>A simple configuration for clients</title>
            <para>The following is a simple configuration file that collects local log messages and
                forwards them to a logserver using the IETF-syslog protocol.</para>
            <synopsis>@version:3.0
               
options { 
            mark_freq(30);
        };
                
source s_local { unix-stream("/dev/log"); internal(); };
 
destination d_syslog_tcp {
             syslog("192.168.1.1" transport("tcp") port(2010));
        };
                
log { source(s_local);destination(d_syslog_tcp); };</synopsis>
        </example>

    </section>

    <section id="configure_relays">
        <title>Configuring syslog-ng relays</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>syslog-ng relays</primary>
            <secondary>configuring</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>To configure syslog-ng on a relay host, complete the following steps:</para>
        <procedure>
            <title>Configuring syslog-ng on relay hosts</title>
            <step>
                <para>Install the syslog-ng application on the host. See <xref
                        linkend="chapter_install"/> for details installing syslog-ng on specific
                    operating systems.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Configure the network sources that collect the log messages sent by the
                    clients.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create a network destination that points to the syslog-ng server.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create a log statement connecting the network sources to the syslog-ng
                server.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Configure the local sources that collect the log messages of the relay
                host.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create a log statement connecting the local sources to the syslog-ng
                server.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Set filters and options (e.g., TLS encryption) as necessary.</para>
                <xi:include href="reference_common.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xpointer="element(note-relaying-hostname)"/>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <para>In relay mode, syslog-ng cannot write messages received from network sources into
            files; the <parameter>file()</parameter> destination is disabled. The following sources
            are network sources: <parameter>syslog()</parameter>, <parameter>tcp()</parameter>,
                <parameter>tcp6()</parameter>, <parameter>udp()</parameter>,
            <parameter>udp6()</parameter>.</para>
        <example id="example_relayconfig">
            <title>A simple configuration for relays</title>
            <para>The following is a simple configuration file that collects local and incoming log
                messages and forwards them to a logserver using the IETF-syslog protocol.</para>
            <synopsis>@version:3.0
                
                options { 
                mark_freq(30);
                keep_hostname(yes);                
                };
                
                source s_local { unix-stream("/dev/log"); internal(); };
                source s_network { syslog(transport(tcp))};
                
                destination d_syslog_tcp {
                syslog("192.168.1.5" transport("tcp") port(2010)
                );
                };
                
                log { source(s_local); source(s_network); 
                      destination(d_syslog_tcp); };</synopsis>
        </example>
    </section>

    <section id="configure_servers">
        <title>Configuring syslog-ng servers</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>syslog-ng servers</primary>
            <secondary>configuring</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>To configure syslog-ng on a server host, complete the following steps:</para>
        <procedure>
            <title>Configuring syslog-ng on server hosts</title>
            <step>
                <para>Install the syslog-ng application on the host. See <xref
                        linkend="chapter_install"/> for details installing syslog-ng on specific
                    operating systems.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Configure the network sources that collect the log messages sent by the
                    clients and relays.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create local destinations that will store the log messages, e.g., files or
                    programs.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create a log statement connecting the network sources to the local
                    destinations.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Configure the local sources that collect the log messages of the syslog-ng
                    server.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Create a log statement connecting the local sources to the local
                destinations.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Set filters, options (e.g., TLS encryption) and other advanced features as
                    necessary.</para>
                <xi:include href="reference_common.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                    xpointer="element(note-relaying-hostname)"/>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <example id="example_serverconfig">
            <title>A simple configuration for servers</title>
            <para>The following is a simple configuration file for syslog-ng Premium Edition that
                collects incoming log messages and stores them in a logstore file.</para>
            <synopsis>@version:3.0
    options { 
        time_reap(30);
        mark_freq(10);
        keep_hostname(yes);
        };
                
    source s_local { unix-stream("/dev/log"); internal();};                
    source s_network { syslog(transport(tcp))};
                
    destination d_logstore { 
        logstore(
            "/var/log/syslog-ng-pe/out/logstore.lgs"
            encrypt_certificate("/opt/syslog-ng/etc/kulcsok/public-certificate.pem")			
            chunk_size(10000) 
            chunk_time(1)
            compress(2)
            owner("root")
            group("root")
            perm(0777)
            ); };
                
    log { source(s_local); source(s_network); destination(d_logstore); };</synopsis>
        </example>
    </section>

    <section id="license">
        <title>Installing and upgrading the license</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>license</primary>
            <secondary>installing</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>The syslog-ng Premium Edition server operates only if a valid license file is present
            on the host. The license file is called <filename>license.txt</filename>, and is located
            in the same directory as the syslog-ng configuration file.</para>
        <warning>
            <para>The <filename>license.txt</filename> file must be readable to the user running the
                syslog-ng process.</para>
        </warning>
        <para>To install a license file, copy it to the directory where the configuration file is
            stored. See <xref linkend="config_file"/> for the location of the license file.</para>
        <para>To upgrade a license file, simply overwrite the old license file with the new one.</para>
        <note>
            <para>The license file is needed only when running syslog-ng Premium Edition in server
                mode.</para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section id="syslog-ng-troubleshooting">
        <title>Troubleshooting syslog-ng</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>troubleshooting</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>error solving</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>syslog-ng</primary>
            <secondary>troubleshooting</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>This section provides tips and guidelines about troubleshooting problems related to
            syslog-ng. Troubleshooting the syslog-ng Agent for Windows application is discussed in
                <xref linkend="windows_troubleshooting"/>.</para>
        <tip>
            <para>As a general rule, first try to get logging the messages to a local file. Once
                this is working, you know that syslog-ng is running correctly and receiving
                messages, and you can proceed to forwarding the messages to the server.</para>
            <para>If the syslog-ng server does not receive the messages, use tcpdump or a similar
                packet sniffer tool on the client to verify that the messages are sent correctly,
                and on the server to verify that it receives the messages.</para>
            <para>If syslog-ng is closing the connections for no apparent reason, be sure to check
                the log messages of syslog-ng. You might also want to run syslog-ng with the
                    <parameter>--verbose</parameter> or <parameter>--debug</parameter> command-line
                options for more-detailed log messages.</para>
            <para>Similarly, build up encrypted connections step-by-step: first create a working
                unencrypted (e.g., TCP) connection, then add TLS encryption, and finally client
                authentication if needed.</para>
        </tip>
        <section id="syslog-ng-core-files">
            <title>Creating syslog-ng core files</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>troubleshooting</primary>
                <secondary>syslog-ng</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>troubleshooting</primary>
                <secondary>core files</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>core files</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>When syslog-ng crashes for some reason, it can create a core file that contains
                important troubleshooting information. To enable core files, complete the following
                procedure:</para>
            <procedure>
                <title>Creating syslog-ng core files</title>
                <step>
                    <para>Core files are produced only if the <parameter>maximum core file
                        size</parameter> ulimit is set to a high value in the init script of
                        syslog-ng.
                        <!-- FIXME ez gyarilag miert nincs benne? Hol kell atirni, fileon belul hova kell tenni?-->
                        Add the following line to the init script of syslog-ng:</para>
                    <synopsis>ulimit -c unlimited</synopsis>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>Verify that syslog-ng has permissions to write the directory it is started
                        from, e.g., <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/sbin/</filename>.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>If syslog-ng crashes, it will create a core file in the directory
                        syslog-ng was started from.</para>
                </step>
                <step>
                    <para>To test that syslog-ng can create a core file, you can create a crash
                        manually. For this, determine the PID of syslog-ng (e.g., using the
                            <command>ps -All|grep syslog-ng</command> command), then issue the
                        following command: <command>kill -ABRT &lt;syslog-ng
                        pid&gt;</command></para>
                    <para>This should create a core file in the current working directory.</para>
                </step>
            </procedure>
        </section>
        <section id="syslog-ng-failure-script">
            <title>Running a failure script</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>troubleshooting</primary>
                <secondary>syslog-ng</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>troubleshooting</primary>
                <secondary>failure scrip</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>failure script</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>When syslog-ng is abnormally terminated, it can execute a user-created failure
                script. This can be used for example to send an automatic e-mail notification. The
                script must be located at
                <filename>/opt/syslog-ng/sbin/syslog-ng-failure</filename>.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="syslog-ng-stop">
            <title>Stopping syslog-ng</title>
            <para>To avoid problems, always use the init scripts to stop syslog-ng
                    (<parameter>/etc/init.d/syslog-ng stop</parameter>), instead of using the
                    <command>kill</command> command. This is especially true on Solaris and HP-UX
                systems, here use <parameter>/etc/init.d/syslog stop</parameter>.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
