<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xml-stylesheet/pdf/dtd/docbookx.dtd"
[  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;]> 
<chapter id="chapter_ibm_sendtosyslog">
	<title>Send To Syslog (SNDSYSLOG) command</title>
	<para>You can use the Send To Syslog (<command>SNDSYSLOG</command>) command to generate your own entries to Syslog-ng. The command can be run from a command line, but you will probably want to use it in your application programs. The command can be added to any CL program to enable your applications to write to the Syslog-ng server. Note that the library ALLSYL100 must be in your library list in order to use the <command>SNDSYSLOG</command> command.</para>
	<table>
		<title>Command parameters</title>
		<tgroup cols="2">
			<tbody>
				<row>
					<entry>SNDSYSLOG</entry>
					<entry>PRIORITY( priority-number )</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry/>
					<entry>FACILITY( facility-number )</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry/>
					<entry>DATE( date )</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry/>
					<entry>TIME( time )</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry/>
					<entry>HOST( host-name | blank )</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry/>
					<entry>TAG ( tag-name )</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry/>
					<entry>MSG( application-message )</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry/>
					<entry>JOB( job-name )</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry/>
					<entry>USER( user-name )</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry/>
					<entry>JOBNO( job-number )</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</table>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>Priority</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>This is the Syslog priority number in the range of 0 to 7. See the documentation in RFC 3164 for information on the meanings of the priority number.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>Facility</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>This is the Syslog facility number in the range of 0 to 23. See the documentation in RFC 3164 for information on the meanings of the facility number.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>Date</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>Provide the date in the format CCYYMMDD where CC is the Century, YY is the year, MM is the month, and DD is the day. This is a character field.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>Time</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>Provide the time in the format HHMMSS using 24-hour time notation.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>Host</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>Provide the host name or the IP address of the host. If you leave this field blank Alliance will use system name from the Network Attributes. Use the Display Network Attributes (<command>DSPNETA</command>) command to view the system name.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>Tag</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>Enter the application name or tag name you want to use for this Syslog entry.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>Message</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>Enter a message to be included in the Syslog entry. The message can be up to 1024 bytes in length. Note that the maximum length of a Syslog entry, including the priority, date, host, tag, and message fields is 1024 bytes. If the resulting message is longer than 1024 bytes it will be truncated to this length and no error message will be sent.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>Job</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>Enter the job name for this Syslog entry. This is an optional field.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>User</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>Enter the user name for this Syslog entry. This is an optional field.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<guimenuitem>Job number</guimenuitem>
			</para>
			<para>Enter the job number for this Syslog entry. This is an optional field.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</chapter>
