<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xml-stylesheet/pdf/dtd/docbookx.dtd"
 [  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
 %entities;]>
<chapter id="preface_sections">
  <!-- <title/> uncommenting the title tag makes this file valid, but causes a warning in the main doc -->
  <section>
    <title>Target audience and prerequisites</title>
    <para>This guide is intended for system administrators and consultants responsible for designing
      and maintaining logging solutions and log centers. It is also useful for IT decision makers
      looking for a tool to implement centralized logging in heterogeneous environments.</para>
    <para>The following skills and knowledge are necessary for a successful syslog-ng
      administrator:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>At least basic system administration knowledge.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>An understanding of networks, TCP/IP protocols, and general network terminology.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem condition="syslog-ng">
        <para>Working knowledge of the UNIX or Linux operating system.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem condition="windows-agent">
        <para>Working knowledge of various Windows operating systems.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem condition="ibm-agent">
        <para>Working knowledge of IBM System i systems.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In-depth knowledge of the logging process of various platforms and
          applications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>An understanding of the legacy syslog (BSD-syslog) protocol (see RFC 3164, available
          at <ulink url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3164.txt"
            >http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3164.txt</ulink>) and the new syslog (IETF-syslog) protocol
          standard (see RFC 5424-5428, available at <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5424"
            >http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5424</ulink>).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="PE-OSE">
    <title>Products covered in this guide</title>
    <para>This guide describes the use of the following syslog-ng versions:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem condition="syslog-ng">
        <para>&product; (PE) &version;.0 and later</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem condition="windows-agent">
        <para>&agent; &version;.0 and later</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem condition="ibm-agent">
        <para>syslog-ng Agent for IBM System i</para>
        <note>
          <para>The syslog-ng Agent for IBM System i is a commercial product independent from
            &product; and must be licensed separately.</para>
          <para>Patrick Townsend &amp; Associates (<ulink url="http://www.patownsend.com"
              >http://www.patownsend.com</ulink>) has partnered with BalaBit IT Security (the
            developer of syslog-ng) to bring the syslog-ng product to the System i platform. The
            syslog-ng PE application can be installed and run as a service directly in the Portable
            Application Solutions Environment (PASE) of the System i platform. Running syslog-ng in
            PASE allows you to transfer the logs of your server applications that are running in the
            PASE to a remote syslog-ng server using UDP, TCP, or SSL-encrypted TCP connections.
            However, syslog-ng alone cannot access the native logs of the IBM System i, for that you
            need the syslog-ng Agent for IBM System i application.</para>
          <para>The syslog-ng Agent for IBM System i application provides extended support for
            sending security, operator, server, and user log information to a syslog-ng server, or
            any syslogd or syslog-ng compatible server. The syslog-ng Agent for IBM System i (also
            called Alliance LogAgent for System i) application can help you bring your IBM System i
            into your Security Information Management strategy to meet regulatory compliance
            requirements and to properly monitor for potential security breaches.</para>
        </note>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Typographical conventions</title>
    <para>Before you start using this guide, it is important to understand the terms and
      typographical conventions used in the documentation. For more information on specialized terms
      and abbreviations used in the documentation, see the <link linkend="syslog-ng_glossary"
        >Glossary</link> at the end of this document.</para>
    <para>The following kinds of text formatting and icons identify special information in the
      document.</para>
    <tip>
      <para>Tips provide best practices and recommendations.</para>
    </tip>
    <!--    <example>
      <title/>
      <para>Examples provide detailed information on an issue, usually with a working
      example.</para>
    </example>-->
    <note>
      <para>Notes provide additional information on a topic and emphasize important facts and
        considerations.</para>
    </note>
    <warning>
      <para>Warnings mark situations where loss of data or misconfiguration of the device is
        possible if the instructions are not obeyed.</para>
    </warning>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <command>Command</command>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Commands you have to execute.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <emphasis>Emphasis</emphasis>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Reference items, additional readings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <filename>/path/to/file</filename>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>File names.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <parameter>Parameters</parameter>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Parameter and attribute names.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guilabel>Label</guilabel>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>GUI output messages or dialog labels.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guimenu>Menu</guimenu>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A submenu in the menu bar.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>
          <guibutton>Button</guibutton>
        </term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Buttons in dialog windows.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section id="contact_and_support">
    <title>Contact and support information</title>
    <para>The &product; and &agent; applications are developed and maintained by BalaBit IT Security
      Ltd. We are located in Budapest, Hungary. Our address is:</para>
    <para>
      <address>
         <street>BalaBit IT Security Ltd.</street>
         <pob>1464 Budapest P.O. BOX 1279</pob>
         <city>Hungary</city>
         <phone>Tel: +36 1 371-0540</phone>
         <fax>Fax: +36 1 208-0875</fax>
         <street>E-mail: info@balabit.com</street>
         <street>Web: <ulink url="http://www.balabit.com/">http://www.balabit.com/</ulink></street>
       </address>
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Sales contact</title>
      <para>You can directly contact us with sales related topics at the e-mail address
          <email>sales@balabit.com</email>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Support contact</title>
      <para>To subscribe to the mailing list of the syslog-ng community, visit <ulink
          url="https://lists.balabit.hu/mailman/listinfo/syslog-ng/"
          >https://lists.balabit.hu/mailman/listinfo/syslog-ng/</ulink>. </para>
      <!--      <para>The syslog-ng Knowledge base is available at 
        <ulink url=" "> </ulink>.</para>
      -->
      <para>To report bugs found in syslog-ng, visit <ulink url="https://bugzilla.balabit.com/"
          >https://bugzilla.balabit.com/</ulink>. </para>
      <para>Product support, including 7x24 online support is available in various packages. For
        support options, visit the following page: <ulink
          url="http://www.balabit.com/support/packages/"
          >http://www.balabit.com/support/packages/</ulink></para>
      <para>You can register your copy of syslog-ng Premium Edition online on the BalaBit website at
          <ulink url="http://www.balabit.com/support/registration/"
          >http://www.balabit.com/support/registration/</ulink>. Registration is a prerequisite for
        all support services. E-mail and telephone support is available for registered users, please
        write or call us for details.</para>
      <para>Support e-mail address: <email>support@balabit.com</email>. </para>
      <para>Support hotline: +36 1 371 0540 (available from 9 AM to 5 PM CET on weekdays)</para>
      <para>The BalaBit Online Support System is available at <ulink url="https://boss.balabit.com/"
          >https://boss.balabit.com/</ulink> and offers 24 hours technical support. This system is
        available only for registered users with a valid support contract and a MyBalaBit account.
        To sign up for MyBalaBit, visit the following page: <ulink
          url="http://www.balabit.com/mybalabit/">http://www.balabit.com/mybalabit/</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Training</title>
      <para>BalaBit IT Security Ltd. holds courses for advanced GNU/Linux system administrators. Our
        experienced system engineers give lectures on syslog-ng administration.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>About this document</title>
    <para>This guide is a work-in-progress document with new versions appearing periodically.</para>
    <para>The latest version of this document can be downloaded from the BalaBit website at <ulink
        url="http://www.balabit.com/support/documentation/"
        >http://www.balabit.com/support/documentation/</ulink>.</para>
    <para>For news and update notifications about the syslog-ng documentation, visit the BalaBit
      Documentation Blog at <ulink url="http://robert.blogs.balabit.com"
        >http://robert.blogs.balabit.com</ulink>.</para>
    <section condition="syslog-ng;windows-agent">
      <title>What is new in this main edition of The <phrase condition="syslog-ng"
          >&product;</phrase><phrase condition="windows-agent">&agent;</phrase><phrase
          condition="ibm-agent">&agenti;</phrase> Administrator Guide?</title>
      <para>The <phrase condition="syslog-ng">&product;</phrase><phrase condition="windows-agent"
          >&agent;</phrase> &version; Administrator Guide contains the following main changes
        compared to earlier editions:</para>
      <itemizedlist condition="syslog-ng">
        <listitem>
          <para>The contents of the guide have been updated for &product; &version;.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The order of chapters has changed: all the chapters about syslog-ng are in the first
            part of the book, while the descriptions of the Windows and System i agents were moved
            back to the second part of the guide.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Earlier editions of the <emphasis>The syslog-ng Administrator Guide</emphasis>
            covered both the open source and the commercial versions of syslog-ng. Starting with
              <emphasis>The syslog-ng 3.1 Administrator Guide</emphasis>, they are discussed in
            separate documents called <emphasis>The syslog-ng Open Source Edition Administrator
              Guide</emphasis> and <emphasis>The syslog-ng Premium Edition Administrator
              Guide</emphasis>, respectively.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The documentation of the &agent; has been moved to a separate document titled
              <emphasis>The &agent; &version; Administrator Guide</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist condition="windows-agent">
        <listitem>
          <para>The contents of the guide have been updated to &agent; &version;.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The documentation of the &agent; has been moved to a separate document titled
              <emphasis>The &agent; &version; Administrator Guide</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Feedback</title>
      <para>Any feedback is greatly appreciated. General comments, errors found in the text, and any
        suggestions about how to improve the documentation is welcome at
          <email>documentation@balabit.com</email>.</para>
    </section>
    <section condition="syslog-ng">
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <para>BalaBit would like to express its gratitude to the syslog-ng users and the syslog-ng
        community for their invaluable help and support.</para>
      <para>Special thanks to Nate Campi for organizing and hosting the syslog-ng FAQ (<ulink
          url="http://campin.net/syslog-ng/faq.html">http://campin.net/syslog-ng/faq.html</ulink>)
        and for his permission to reproduce parts of his work in this guide.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
