<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xml-stylesheet/pdf/dtd/docbookx.dtd"
 [  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
 %entities;]> 
<chapter id="chapter-log-statistics">
    <title>Statistics of syslog-ng</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>statistics</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>log statistics</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>message</primary>
        <secondary>statistics</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>message</primary>
        <secondary>counters</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Periodically, syslog-ng sends a message containing statistics about the
        received messages, and about any lost messages since the last such message. It
        includes a <parameter>processed</parameter> entry for every source and
        destination, listing the number of messages received or sent, and a
            <parameter>dropped</parameter> entry including the IP address of the server
        for every destination where syslog-ng has lost messages. The
            <parameter>center(received)</parameter> entry shows the total number of
        messages received from every configured sources.</para>
    <para>The following is a sample log statistics message for a configuration that has
        a single source (<parameter>s_local</parameter>) and a network and a local file
        destination (<parameter>d_network</parameter> and
        <parameter>d_local</parameter>, respectively). All incoming messages are sent to
        both destinations.</para>
    <synopsis>Log statistics;
        dropped='tcp(AF_INET(192.168.10.1:514))=6439',
        processed='center(received)=234413',
        processed='destination(d_tcp)=234413',
        processed='destination(d_local)=234413',
        processed='source(s_local)=234413'</synopsis>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>log statistics</primary>
        <secondary>on unix-socket</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>message</primary>
        <secondary>statistics</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>statistics</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Log statistics can be also retrieved on-demand using one of the following options:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Use the
                <command>socat</command> application: <command>echo STATS | socat -vv
                UNIX-CONNECT:/opt/syslog-ng/var/run/syslog-ng.ctl -</command></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>If you have an OpenBSD-style
            <command>netcat</command> application installed, use the <command>echo STATS |
            nc -U var/run/syslog-ng.ctl</command> command. Note that the <command>netcat</command> included in most Linux distributions is a GNU-style version that is not
            suitable to query the statistics of syslog-ng.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Starting from &product; version 3.1, &product; includes the syslog-ng-ctl utility. Use the <command>syslog-ng-ctl stats</command> command.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The statistics include a list of source
        groups and destinations, as well as the number of processed messages for each.
        The verbosity of the statistics can be set using the
        <parameter>stats_level()</parameter> option. For details, see <xref
            linkend="reference_options"/>. An example output is shown below.</para>
    <synopsis>src.internal;s_all#0;;a;processed;6445
src.internal;s_all#0;;a;stamp;1268989330
destination;df_auth;;a;processed;404
destination;df_news_dot_notice;;a;processed;0
destination;df_news_dot_err;;a;processed;0
destination;d_ssb;;a;processed;7128
destination;df_uucp;;a;processed;0
source;s_all;;a;processed;7128
destination;df_mail;;a;processed;0
destination;df_user;;a;processed;1
destination;df_daemon;;a;processed;1
destination;df_debug;;a;processed;15
destination;df_messages;;a;processed;54
destination;dp_xconsole;;a;processed;671
dst.tcp;d_network#0;10.50.0.111:514;a;dropped;5080
dst.tcp;d_network#0;10.50.0.111:514;a;processed;7128
dst.tcp;d_network#0;10.50.0.111:514;a;stored;2048
destination;df_syslog;;a;processed;6724
destination;df_facility_dot_warn;;a;processed;0
destination;df_news_dot_crit;;a;processed;0
destination;df_lpr;;a;processed;0
destination;du_all;;a;processed;0
destination;df_facility_dot_info;;a;processed;0
center;;received;a;processed;0
destination;df_kern;;a;processed;70
center;;queued;a;processed;0
destination;df_facility_dot_err;;a;processed;0</synopsis>
    <para>The statistics are semicolon separated; every line contains statistics for a particular object (for example source, destination, tag, and so on). The statistics have the following fields:</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>The type of the object (for example <parameter>dst.file</parameter>, <parameter>tag</parameter>, <parameter>src.facility</parameter>)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The ID of the object used in the syslog-ng configuration file, for example <parameter>d_internal</parameter> or <parameter>source.src_tcp</parameter>. The <parameter>#0</parameter> part means that this is the first destination in the destination group.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The instance ID (destination) of the object, for example the filename of a file destination, or the name of the application for a program source or destination.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The status of the object. One of the following:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><parameter>a</parameter> - active. At the time of quering the statistics, the source or the destination was still alive (it continuously received statistical data).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><parameter>d</parameter> - dynamic. Such objects may not be continuously available, for example, like statistics based on the sender's hostname.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><parameter>o</parameter> - This object was once active, but stopped receiving messages. (For example a dynamic object may disappear and become orphan.)</para>
                    <note>
                        <para>The &abbrev; application stores the statistics of the objects when &abbrev; is reloaded. However, if the configuration of &abbrev; was changed since the last reload, the statistics of orphaned objects are deleted.</para>
                    </note>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The type of the statistics:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><parameter>processed</parameter>: The number of messages that successfully reached their destination driver.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><parameter>dropped</parameter>: The number of dropped messages &mdash; &abbrev; could not send the messages to the destination and the output buffer got full, so messages were dropped by the destination driver.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><parameter>stored</parameter>: The number of messages stored in the message queue of the destination driver, waiting to be sent to the destination.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><parameter>suppressed</parameter>: The number of suppressed messages (if the <parameter>suppress()</parameter> feature is enabled).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><parameter>stamp</parameter>: The UNIX timestamp of the last message sent to the destination.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The number of such messages.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <note>
        <para>Certain statistics are available only if the <parameter>stats-level()</parameter> option is set to a higher value.</para>
        <para>When receiving messages with non-standard facility values (that is, higher than 23), these messages will be listed as <parameter>other</parameter> facility instead of their facility number.</para>
    </note>
</chapter>
