<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;]> 
<chapter xml:id="chapter_ibm_install" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
	<title>Installation of &agenti;</title>
	
	<section>
		<title>Pre-requisites</title>
		<para>The &agenti; product runs on any version of IBM OS/400 or i5/OS from V5R1 and later.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Installing from an Internet download</title>
		<para>When you download the &agentabbrev; product from the web site, you must unzip the product. You software provider will supply a pass phrase for extracting the files. See the Readme.txt file in the download for instructions on how to copy the software to the System i using FTP. Once you transfer the Save file to the System i you will restore the library <command>ALLSYL100</command>.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Upgrading &agenti;</title>
		<para>To upgrade the &agentabbrev; product you must first end the <command>ALLSYL100</command> subsystem and rename the library:</para>
		<synopsis>Endsbs sbs(allsyl100) option(*immed)
		Rnmobj obj(allsyl100) objtype(*lib) newobj(allsylold)</synopsis>
		<para>After renaming the library you can install the  new version using the Internet download.</para>
		<para>After installing the new version use the Apply Release Upgrade option on the Installation menu to copy your configuration information from the old library to the new version.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Reverting to a previous version after an upgrade</title>
		<para>You can revert to a previous version of the product by renaming the new library to a save name, and then renaming the old version to the library <command>ALLSYL100</command>. This will restore the previous version.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>License codes</title>
		<para>Before you can configure and use the &agentabbrev; agent and server you must enter a temporary or permanent license code. Please contact your software supplier to receive the license code. The Open Source Edition of the syslog server does not require a license code to operate.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Historical QAUDJRN messages</title>
		<para>If you will be sending system audit journal information to Syslog-ng you may wish to delete older journal receivers before starting the process. &agentabbrev; collects journal entries from the beginning of the current chain of journal receivers. The date of all log entries is the date of the actual journal entry, but there may be a lot of historical information that you do not want to process. You should consider making a permanent backup of system audit journals before deleting them. Use the Work With Journal Attributes (<command>WRKJRNA</command>) command to view the journal receivers for the <command>QAUDJRN</command> journal.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
