<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../shared/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
  %entities;]>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="configuring">
    <title>Configuring &abbrev;</title>
    <para>The syslog-ng application reads incoming messages and forwards them to the selected <emphasis>destinations</emphasis>. The syslog-ng application can receive messages from files, remote hosts, and other <emphasis>sources</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>Log messages enter syslog-ng in one of the defined sources, and are sent to one or more <emphasis>destinations</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>Sources and destinations are independent objects: <emphasis>log paths</emphasis> define what syslog-ng does with a message, connecting the sources to the destinations. A log path consists of one or more sources and one or more destinations, messages arriving from a source are sent to every destination listed in the log path. A log path defined in syslog-ng is called a <emphasis>log statement</emphasis>.</para>
    <para>There are many other optional elements, like filters, parsers, etc., but in this guide we focus on a core syslog-ng feature: reliable logging.</para>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="proc-conf-enabling-disk.xml"/>
    <section condition="pe6">
        <title><trademark>Reliable Transfer Protocol</trademark>
        </title>
        <xi:include href="../syslog-ng-guide-admin/chapters/chapter-rltp.xml" xpointer="para-rltp-intro" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
        <para>To make RLTP work, you have to enable it on the server and on all participating clients as well. In the following example, a minimum working configuration is provided; for additional options, including TLS configuration, refer to <olink targetdoc="syslog-ng-pe-guide-admin" targetptr="chapter-rltp"/>.</para>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="proc-conf-syslog-server.xml"/>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="proc-conf-syslog-winclient.xml"/>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="proc-conf-syslog-linuxclient.xml"/>
    </section>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="proc-conf-macros.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="proc-conf-store-messages.xml"/>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="proc-conf-relay.xml"/>
</section>
