<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix SYSTEM "../../xml-stylesheet/pdf/dtd/docbookx.dtd"
 [  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../../syslog-ng-admin-guide/syslog-ng-entities.ent">
 %entities;]> 
<appendix id="app_eula">
    <title>BalaBit syslog-ng Premium Edition License contract </title>
    <section>
        <title>SUBJECT OF THE LICENSE CONTRACT</title>
        <para>This License Contract is entered into by and between BalaBit and Licensee and sets out
            the terms and conditions under which Licensee and/or Licensee’s Authorized Subsidiaries
            may use the BalaBit syslog-ng Premium Edition product.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>DEFINITIONS</title>
        <para>In this License Contract, the following words shall have the following meanings:</para>
        <para>Company name: <emphasis role="b">BalaBit IT Security Ltd.</emphasis></para>
        <para>Registered office: H-1115 Budapest, Bártfai u. 54. Hungary</para>
        <para>Company registration number: 01-09-687127</para>
        <para>Tax number: HU11996468</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>WORDS AND EXPRESSIONS</title>

        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Annexed Software</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Any third party software that is a not a BalaBit Product contained
                                in the install media of the BalaBit Product.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Authorized Subsidiary</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Any subsidiary organization: (i) in which Licensee possesses more
                                than fifty percent (50%) of the voting power and (ii) which is
                                located within the Territory.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>BalaBit Product</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Any software, hardware or service Licensed, sold, or provided by
                                BalaBit including any installation, education, support and warranty
                                services, with the exception of the Annexed Software.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>License Contract</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>The present BalaBit syslog-ng Premium Edition License
                            Contract.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Product Documentation</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Any documentation referring to the BalaBit syslog-ng Premium
                                Edition or any module thereof, with special regard to the
                                administration guide, the product description, the installation
                                guide, user guides and manuals.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Number of Log Source Hosts</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>
                                <literal>Number of all host or server computers including virtual
                                    machines, active or passive networking devices from which a
                                    BalaBit syslog-ng Premium Edition server receives log
                                messages.</literal>
                            </para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Protected Objects</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>The entire BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>
                                software including all of its modules, all the related Product
                                Documentation; the source code, the structure of the databases, all
                                registered information reflecting the structure of the BalaBit
                                    <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal> and all the
                                adaptation and copies of the Protected Objects that presently exist
                                or that are to be developed in the future, or any product falling
                                under the copyright of BalaBit.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal></para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>The BalaBit Product designed for aggregate, filter, format, send
                                or receive over network or local connection the log messages and
                                eventlogs as defined by the Product Description.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Warranty Period</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>The period of twelve (12) months from the date of delivery of the
                                BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal> to
                            Licensee.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>Territory</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>The countries or areas specified above in respect of which
                                Licensee shall be entitled to install and/or use BalaBit
                                    <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition.</literal></para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>

                    <row>
                        <entry>
                            <para>End-user Certificate</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                            <para>The document signed by Licensor which contains a) identification
                                data of Licensee; b) configuration of BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng
                                    Premium Edition</literal> , maximum Number of Log Source Hosts
                                and designation of Licensed modules thereof; c) designation of the
                                Territory; d) declaration of the parties on accepting the terms and
                                conditions of this License Contract; and e) declaration of Licensee
                                that is in receipt of the install media and the hardware
                            appliance.</para>
                        </entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>LICENSE GRANTS AND RESTRICTIONS</title>
        <para>For the BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>licensed under this
            License Contract, BalaBit grants to Licensee a non-exclusive, non-transferable,
            perpetual license to use such BalaBit Product under the terms and conditions of this
            License Contract and the applicable End-user Certificate.</para>

        <para>Licensee shall use the BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>in the in
            the configuration and in the quantities specified in the End-user Certificate within the
            Territory.</para>

        <para>On the install media (CD-ROM) all modules of the BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium
                Edition</literal>will be presented, however, Licensee shall not be entitled to use
            any module which was not Licensed to it. Access rights to modules and maximum Number of
            Log Source Hosts are controlled by an “electronic key” accompanying the BalaBit
                <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>.</para>

        <para>Licensee shall be entitled to make one back-up copy of the install media containing
            the BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>.</para>

        <para>Licensee shall make available the Protected Objects at its disposal solely to its own
            employees and those of the Authorized Subsidiaries.</para>

        <para>Licensee shall take all reasonable steps to protect BalaBit’s rights with respect to
            the Protected Objects with special regard and care to protecting it from any
            unauthorized access.</para>

        <para>Licensee shall, in 5 working days, properly answer the queries of BalaBit referring to
            the actual usage conditions of the BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium
            Edition</literal>that may differ or allegedly differs from the License conditions.</para>

        <para>Licensee shall not modify the BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>in
            any way, with special regard to the functions inspecting the usage of the software.
            Licensee shall install the code permitting the usage of the BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng
                Premium Edition</literal>according to the provisions defined for it by BalaBit.
            Licensee may not modify or cancel such codes. Configuration settings of the BalaBit
                <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>in accordance with the possibilities
            offered by the system shall not be construed as modification of the software.</para>

        <para>Licensee shall only be entitled to analyze the structure of the BalaBit Products
            (decompilation or reverse- engineering) if concurrent operation with a software
            developed by a third party is necessary, and upon request to supply the information
            required for concurrent operation BalaBit does not provide such information within 60
            days from the receipt of such a request.</para>

        <para>These user actions are limited to parts of the BalaBit Product which are necessary for
            concurrent operation.<emphasis role="i">Any information obtained as a result of applying
                the previous Section (i) cannot be used for purposes other than concurrent operation
                with the BalaBit Product; (ii) cannot be disclosed to third parties unless it is
                necessary for concurrent operation with the BalaBit Product; (iii) cannot be used
                for the development, production or distribution of a different software which is
                similar to the BalaBit Product in its form of expression, or for any other act
                violating copyright.</emphasis></para>

        <para>
            <emphasis>For any Annexed Software contained by the same install media as the BalaBit
                Product, the terms and conditions defined by its copyright owner shall be properly
                applied. BalaBit does not grant any License rights to any Annexed
            Software.</emphasis>
        </para>

        <para>Any usage of the BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>exceeding the
            limits and restrictions defined in this License Contract shall qualify as material
            breach of the License Contract.</para>

        <para>The Number of Log Source Hosts shall not exceed the amount defined in the End-user
            Certificate.</para>

        <para>Licensee shall have the right to obtain and use content updates only if Licensee
            concludes a maintenance contract that includes such content updates, or if Licensee has
            otherwise separately acquired the right to obtain and use such content updates. This
            License Contract does not otherwise permit Licensee to obtain and use content
        updates.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>SUBSIDIARIES</title>
        <para>Authorized Subsidiaries may also utilize the services of the BalaBit
                <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>under the terms and conditions of this
            License Contract. Any Authorized Subsidiary utilizing any service of the BalaBit
                <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>will be deemed to have accepted the
            terms and conditions of this License Contract.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHTS</title>
        <para>Licensee agrees that BalaBit owns all rights, titles, and interests related to the
            BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>and all of BalaBit's patents,
            trademarks, trade names, inventions, copyrights, know-how, and trade secrets relating to
            the design, manufacture, operation or service of the BalaBit Products.</para>

        <para>The use by Licensee of any of these intellectual property rights is authorized only
            for the purposes set forth herein, and upon termination of this License Contract for any
            reason, such authorization shall cease.</para>

        <para>The BalaBit Products are Licensed only for internal business purposes in every case,
            under the condition that such License does not convey any license, expressly or by
            implication, to manufacture, duplicate or otherwise copy or reproduce any of the BalaBit
            Products. No other rights than expressly stated herein are granted to Licensee.</para>

        <para>Licensee will take appropriate steps with its Authorized Subsidiaries, as BalaBit may
            request, to inform them of and assure compliance with the restrictions contained in the
            License Contract.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>TRADE MARKS</title>
        <para>BalaBit hereby grants to Licensee the non-exclusive right to use the trade marks of
            the BalaBit Products in the Territory in accordance with the terms and for the duration
            of this License Contract.</para>

        <para>BalaBit makes no representation or warranty as to the validity or enforceability of
            the trade marks, nor as to whether these infringe any intellectual property rights of
            third parties in the Territory.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>NEGLIGENT INFRINGEMENT</title>

        <para>In case of negligent infringement of BalaBit’s rights with respect to the BalaBit
                <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>, committed by violating the
            restrictions and limitations defined by this License Contract, Licensee shall pay
            liquidated damages to BalaBit. The amount of the liquidated damages shall be twice as
            much as the price of the BalaBit Product concerned, on BalaBit’s current Price
        List.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY INDEMNIFICATION</title>
        <para>BalaBit shall pay all damages, costs and reasonable attorney’s fees awarded against
            Licensee in connection with any claim brought against Licensee to the extent that such
            claim is based on a claim that Licensee’s authorized use of the BalaBit Product
            infringes a patent, copyright, trademark or trade secret. Licensee shall notify BalaBit
            in writing of any such claim as soon as Licensee learns of it and shall cooperate fully
            with BalaBit in connection with the defense of that claim. BalaBit shall have sole
            control of that defense (including without limitation the right to settle the claim).</para>
        <para>If Licensee is prohibited from using any BalaBit Product due to an infringement claim,
            or if BalaBit believes that any BalaBit Product is likely to become the subject of an
            infringement claim, BalaBit shall at its sole option, either: (i) obtain the right for
            Licensee to continue to use such BalaBit Product, (ii) replace or modify the BalaBit
            Product so as to make such BalaBit Product non-infringing and substantially comparable
            in functionality or (iii) refund to Licensee the amount paid for such infringing BalaBit
            Product and provide a pro-rated refund of any unused, prepaid maintenance fees paid by
            Licensee, in exchange for Licensee’s return of such BalaBit Product to BalaBit.</para>

        <para>Notwithstanding the above, BalaBit will have no liability for any infringement claim
            to the extent that it is based upon: (i) modification of the BalaBit Product other than
            by BalaBit, (ii) use of the BalaBit Product in combination with any product not
            specifically authorized by BalaBit to be combined with the BalaBitProduct or (iii) use
            of the BalaBit Product in an unauthorized manner for which it was not designed.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>LICENSE FEE</title>

        <para>The allowed maximum Number of the Log Source Hosts, the configuration and the modules
            licensed shall serve as the calculation base of the License fee.</para>

        <para>Licensee acknowledges that payment of the License fees is a condition of lawful usage.</para>

        <para>License fees do not contain any installation or post charges.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>WARRANTIES</title>
        <para>BalaBit warrants that during the Warranty Period, the magnetic or optical media upon
            which the BalaBit Product is recorded will not be defective under normal use. BalaBit
            will replace any defective media returned to it, accompanied by a dated proof of
            purchase, within the Warranty Period at no charge to Licensee. Upon receipt of the
            allegedly defective BalaBit Product, BalaBit will at its option, deliver a replacement
            BalaBit Product or BalaBit's current equivalent to Licensee at no additional cost.
            BalaBit will bear the delivery charges to Licensee for the replacement Product.</para>

        <para>In case of installation by BalaBit, BalaBit warrants that during the Warranty Period,
            the BalaBit <literal>syslog-ng Premium Edition</literal>, under normal use in the
            operating environment defined by BalaBit, and without unauthorized modification, will
            perform in substantial compliance with the Product Documentation accompanying the
            BalaBit Product, when used on that hardware for which it was installed, in compliance
            with the provisions of the user manuals and the recommendations of BalaBit. The date of
            the notification sent to BalaBit shall qualify as the date of the failure. Licensee
            shall do its best to mitigate the consequences of that failure. If, during the Warranty
            Period, the BalaBit Product fails to comply with this warranty, and such failure is
            reported by Licensee to BalaBit within the Warranty Period, BalaBit’s sole obligation
            and liability for breach of this warranty is, at BalaBit’s sole option, either: (i) to
            correct such failure, (ii) to replace the defective BalaBit Product or (iii) to refund
            the license fees paid by Licensee for the applicable BalaBit Product.</para>


    </section>
    <section>
        <title>
            <emphasis role="i">DISCLAIMER OF WARRANTIES</emphasis>
        </title>

        <para>EXCEPT AS SET OUT IN THIS LICENSE CONTRACT, BALABIT MAKES NO WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND
            WITH RESPECT TO THE BALABIT SYSLOG-NG PREMIUM EDITION. TO THE MAXIMUM EXTENT PERMITTED
            BY APPLICABLE LAW, BALABIT EXCLUDES ANY OTHER WARRANTIES, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO
            ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF SATISFACTORY QUALITY, MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A
            PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NON-INFRINGEMENT OF INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHTS.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>LIMITATION OF LIABILITY</title>
        <para>SOME STATES AND COUNTRIES, INCLUDING MEMBER COUNTRIES OF THE EUROPEAN UNION, DO NOT
            ALLOW THE LIMITATION OR EXCLUSION OF LIABILITY FOR INCIDENTAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
            AND, THEREFORE, THE FOLLOWING LIMITATION OR EXCLUSION MAY NOT APPLY TO THIS LICENSE
            CONTRACT IN THOSE STATES AND COUNTRIES. TO THE MAXIMUM EXTENT PERMITTED BY APPLICABLE
            LAW AND REGARDLESS OF WHETHER ANY REMEDY SET OUT IN THIS LICENSE CONTRACT FAILS OF ITS
            ESSENTIAL PURPOSE, IN NO EVENT SHALL BALABIT BE LIABLE TO LICENSEE FOR ANY SPECIAL,
            CONSEQUENTIAL, INDIRECT OR SIMILAR DAMAGES OR LOST PROFITS OR LOST DATA ARISING OUT OF
            THE USE OR INABILITY TO USE THE BALABIT SYSLOG-NG PREMIUM EDITION EVEN IF BALABIT HAS
            BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.</para>

        <para>IN NO CASE SHALL BALABIT’S TOTAL LIABILITY UNDER THIS LICENSE CONTRACT EXCEED THE FEES
            PAID BY LICENSEE FOR THE BALABIT SYSLOG-NG PREMIUM EDITION LICENSED UNDER THIS LICENSE
            CONTRACT.</para>


    </section>
    <section>
        <title>DURATION AND TERMINATION</title>
        <para>This License Contract shall come into effect on the date of signature of the End-user
            Certificate by the duly authorized representative of BalaBit.</para>
        <para>Licensee may terminate the License Contract at any time by written notice sent to
            BalaBit and by simultaneously destroying all copies of the Protected Objects licensed
            under this License Contract.</para>

        <para>BalaBit may terminate this License Contract with immediate effect by written notice to
            Licensee, if Licensee is in material or persistent breach of the License Contract and
            either that breach is incapable of remedy or Licensee shall have failed to remedy that
            breach within 30 days after receiving written notice requiring it to remedy that
        breach.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>AMENDMENTS</title>

        <para>Save as expressly provided in this License Contract, no amendment or variation of this
            License Contract shall be effective unless in writing and signed by a duly authorized
            representative of the parties to it.</para>


    </section>
    <section>
        <title>WAIVER</title>
        <para>The failure of a party to exercise or enforce any right under this License Contract
            shall not be deemed to be a waiver of that right nor operate to bar the exercise or
            enforcement of it at any time or times thereafter.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>SEVERABILITY</title>
        <para>If any part of this License Contract becomes invalid, illegal or unenforceable, the
            parties shall in such an event negotiate in good faith in order to agree on the terms of
            a mutually satisfactory provision to be substituted for the invalid, illegal or
            unenforceable provision which as nearly as possible validly gives effect to their
            intentions as expressed in this License Contract.</para>

    </section>

    <section>
        <title>NOTICES</title>
        <para>Any notice required to be given pursuant to this License Contract shall be in writing
            and shall be given by delivering the notice by hand, or by sending the same by prepaid
            first class post (airmail if to an address outside the country of posting) to the
            address of the relevant party set out in this License Contract or such other address as
            either party notifies to the other from time to time. Any notice given according to the
            above procedure shall be deemed to have been given at the time of delivery (if delivered
            by hand) and when received (if sent by post).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title> MISCELLANEOUS </title>

        <para>Headings are for convenience only and shall be ignored in interpreting this License
            Contract.</para>

        <para>This License Contract and the rights granted in this License Contract may not be
            assigned, sublicensed or otherwise transferred in whole or in part by Licensee without
            BalaBit’s prior written consent. This consent shall not be unreasonably withheld or
            delayed.</para>
        <para>An independent third party auditor, reasonably acceptable to BalaBit and Licensee, may
            upon reasonable notice to Licensee and during normal business hours, but not more often
            than once each year, inspect Licensee’s relevant records in order to confirm that usage
            of the BalaBit syslog-ng Premium Edition complies with the terms and conditions of this
            License Contract. BalaBit shall bear the costs of such audit. All audits shall be
            subject to the reasonable safety and security policies and procedures of Licensee.</para>
        <para>This License Contract constitutes the entire agreement between the parties with regard
            to the subject matter hereof.</para>
        <para>Any modification of this License Contract must be in writing and signed by both
            parties.</para>

    </section>
</appendix>
