<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
 [  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../syslog-ng-entities.ent">
 %entities;]>
<topic xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
    <para>The syslog-ng application reads incoming messages and forwards them to the selected <emphasis>destinations</emphasis>. The syslog-ng application can receive messages from files, remote hosts, and other <emphasis>sources</emphasis>.</para>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>destinations</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Log messages enter syslog-ng in one of the defined sources, and are sent to one or more <emphasis>destinations</emphasis>.</para>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>log paths</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>log statements</primary>
        <secondary>log paths</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Sources and destinations are independent objects, <emphasis>log paths</emphasis> define what syslog-ng does with a message, connecting the sources to the destinations. A log path consists of one or more sources and one or more destinations: messages arriving from a source are sent to every destination listed in the log path. A log path defined in syslog-ng is called a <emphasis>log statement</emphasis>.</para>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>filters</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Optionally, log paths can include <emphasis>filters</emphasis>. Filters are rules that select only certain messages, for example, selecting only messages sent by a specific application. If a log path includes filters, syslog-ng sends only the messages satisfying the filter rules to the destinations set in the log path.</para>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>parsers</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>rewrite rules</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>Other optional elements that can appear in log statements are <emphasis>parsers</emphasis> and <emphasis>rewriting rules</emphasis>. Parsers segment messages into different fields to help processing the messages, while rewrite rules modify the messages by adding, replacing, or removing parts of the messages.</para>
</topic>
